<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-11-27T21:03:03+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Yassine Taoudi-Benchekroun</title><subtitle>PhD Candidate at the Institute of Neuroinformatics, ETH Zurich.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The North Star of My PhD (Part 2)</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/phd-north-star-continued/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The North Star of My PhD (Part 2)"/><published>2024-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/phd-north-star-continued</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/phd-north-star-continued/"><![CDATA[<p>You may have heard of System 1 &amp; System 2 thinking paradigms for AI - inspired from Cognitive Science theory. Greg Brockman (OpenAI’s CEO) Tweeted this a couple of weeks ago, upon release of OpenAI’s latest model “OpenAI o1”. So what’s System 1 &amp; System 2 thinking? And what can it teach us about the strengths, limitations and research avenues of AI research?</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/north_star_phd_2/brockman-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/north_star_phd_2/brockman-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/north_star_phd_2/brockman-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/north_star_phd_2/brockman" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="system-1-and-system-2---a-paradigm-for-progress-in-ai-research">System 1 and System 2 - A Paradigm for Progress in AI Research</h2> <p>In his famous book “Thinking, Fast and Slow”, Daniel Kahneman popularized the concepts of <em>System 1</em> and <em>System 2</em> thinking. <em>System 1</em> refers to humans’ fast, intuitive, and automatic thought processes that requires little effort or conscious control. It’s what drives quick judgments, emotional reactions, instinctive decisions etc… Some typical examples of System 1 thinking are recognizing a friend’s face, understanding simple words (e.g. a STOP sign), or driving a car on an empty road. <em>System 2</em>, on the other hand, is our slower, more deliberate, and analytical thinking mode. It involves conscious reasoning, complex problem-solving, or long term planning. Examples of System 2 thinking include solving a complex math problem, choosing what flight you’ll take to arrive on vacation, or learning a new skill. Both System 1 and System 2 thinking continuously interact with one another.</p> <p>This has become a popular perspective of our intelligence, and often used by the Machine Learning community <d-footnote>NeurIPS now even has a "system 2 workshop": https://openreview.net/group?id=NeurIPS.cc/2024/Workshop/Sys2-Reasoning </d-footnote>. Among the many things System 1 thinking is useful for, one thing of particular importance is the <em>filtering</em> through tools and memories to tackle a given situation. Imagine yourself unexpectedly being asked about a Calculus problem by a friend. Almost immediately, you are able to filter out the entirety of what you know from Algebra, Physics, Biology, and the rest of your knowledge space, and start thinking about a very very small subset of possible solutions to the problem. It then becomes a slower thinking process (system 2), but on a very small <strong>search space</strong> compared to the entirety of the toolbox that your brain possesses.</p> <p>Even more important than reducing the search space, the system 1 filtering allowed you to already have the right <strong>representation</strong> of the problem. You instinctively know that thinking about a mathematics problem is not the same as thinking about a music or cooking problem - the question that your friend asked you has a specific and adapted representation, and start your system 2 thinking process with the right “cognitive organization”. Often, you’ll realize that you have the wrong representation of the problem, and “need to think about it differently” - this is your System 2 communicating with your system 1.</p> <p>In effect, system 1 unconsciously molds your cognition in the right frame to solve daily problems an learn new skills. It just immediately extracts the right tools from your toolbox, without you ever realizing that it did. All you now have to do is think a bit whether to start working with the hammer or the nail - but never were you suggested to use a computer or a watch or a car to put that nail on the wall.</p> <h2 id="can-neural-networks-do-system-1">Can Neural Networks do System 1?</h2> <p>Yes, but they also are not so good at it. Let’s dive in.</p> <h3 id="neural-networks-are-quintessential-system-1">Neural Networks are quintessential System 1</h3> <p>Neural Networks are essentially “System 1 Thinkers” - in pretty much all their variations and forms. What fundamentally makes Neural Networks <em>System 1</em> thinkers can be summed up to a few points:</p> <ul> <li>The speed at which they produce a response is <em>irrespective of the complexity</em> of what they must process. It’s only constrained by the architectural and computational constrains of the neural network - just like “reflexes” in humans are constrained by the time constants of neural cells and other physiological factors. This is also analogous to the concept of “intuition” in humans - however complex a problem may be, we often have immediate intuitions over what the solution might be. This argument is central to the point - this immediate intuition allows to vastly reduce and guide the search space - it’s a pre-requisite to be able to solve the problem in reasonable time-span. System 2 thinking cannot function without a robust System 1 thinking. This argument is also central to the point in showing that System 1 thinking is not sufficient: currently, an LLM would take the same amount of time to compute “Hi, how are you doing?” as “26.9*124^7” - by virtue of it being the same number of input tokens.</li> <li>It is virtually impossible to obtain a “human interpretable” explanation to why NNs output response X as opposed to response Y, Z etc… All System 1 processes are indeed unexplained to humans - they just emerge as a function of architecture (native) and weights (trained).</li> <li>Neural Networks produce “<em>latent representation</em>” of stimuli and states. A good analogy in humans is the set of expectations one has when encountering a situation, as well as the attention on specific details of the situation. Only recognizing a person that comes talk to you at your desk creates a space of expectation and bounds your behavior in an immediate way. It also channels your attention on that interaction, rather than your other colleague typing on their computer or what’s going on outside the window. This is something I find particularly interesting that I also attribute to System 1 thinking. In symbolic terms - it’s a matter of shrinking the action space to search over in response to stimuli.</li> </ul> <h3 id="foundation-models-as-generalist-system-1-models">Foundation Models as generalist System 1 models</h3> <p><em>Foundation Models</em> are models that have been trained by large corporations/institutions on vast amount of training data. Some are open source, and some are not. Some focus on language, some on vision, and some on time series, and some on everything. Foundation Models can be considered the first general-purpose System 1 models. As Neural Networks, they perfectly fit the aforementioned categorization as System 1 models. What is novel and interesting in Foundation Models in that spirit, compared to the vast amount of NNs that have been trained and deployed in the past decades, is the diversity of their training data - they are unlike narrow NN which can only navigate specific problems for which they were trained for. They are trained on different kinds of input format, and most importantly, on a <em>very high</em> diversity of “topics”. This enables them to do <em>in-context learning</em> and <em>knowledge interpolation</em>. This makes them capable of dealing with new problem instances that are completely novel, in a way that has never been seen before - as long as the prompt resembles what these models have been trained on before. The reality is that the amount of training data they have been trained on is so vast that there are very little things that one might ask that have never been looked at by the model. Essentially, they are quite capable of having a good initial estimate of how to tackle pretty much any situation. Of course, we know countless papers that expose the failure modes of these models, but they always answer on topic. I believe this is analogous to us having to tackle daily situations without System 2 thinking - we’d be able to be on topic most of the times, but would much too frequently fail to have the right behavior or give the right answer to the problems we’re asked. It’s analogous to us only having intuition, but never slow deliberate thinking.</p> <p>Their training modality also enables them to quickly adapt to new categories of knowledge that one may want to fine tune them on. The great paper <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-11786-6">A critique of Pure Learning</a> argued that biological brains learn very little - they are just incredibly well wired as a result millennia of genetic evolution, and adapt incredibly fast to new environments. One can think of Foundation models as such - models that have been trained on such vast amount of data that their architecture and weights are perfectly suited to learn new tasks quickly. This is what we see in practice - your average computer vision model is not trained from scratch anymore - one always loads a pre-trained model and fine tunes with their own (often-limited) data - and that usually does the job well <d-footnote>compared to training from scratch. Of course, these models still have significant issues.</d-footnote>.</p> <h3 id="whats-missing-for-good-system-1-thinking">What’s missing for good system 1 thinking?</h3> <p>In short: interaction and grounding.</p> <h4 id="interaction">Interaction</h4> <p>A fundamental aspect of our learning and intelligence, and of our developing intuitions about how things in the world work is through both <em>exposure</em> and <em>interaction</em> with these things. As I argue in my <a href="/_posts/2024-10-10-phd-north-star.md">previous post</a>, taking the number “3” as a demonstrating example: <em>“not only do we learn what “three” means by being shown three fingers, three pens, or three heads on Cerebrus’ head, but we also learn how to say three words, draw three lines, eat three meals a day. The concept “three” is not only seen but also <strong>interacted</strong> with, and even <strong>produced</strong> in a wide range of different contexts. Its meaning and representation in our brain is multi faceted and highly malleable - specifically because we have *actively</em> learned about it through interaction and production, as opposed to just <em>passively</em> through exposure.*. Learning from data is not enough.</p> <p>One research direction that tries to go beyond passively learning from data is the one of World Models. According to Claude, “World Models work by learning to create internal, predictive representations of an environment that allow an AI agent to simulate potential scenarios, forecast outcomes, and make more intelligent decisions by “dreaming” or exploring hypothetical trajectories before taking actual actions.”</p> <p>In the original World Model paper <d-footnote>arXiv:1803.10122v4</d-footnote>, Ha &amp; Schmidhuber write:</p> <blockquote> <p>“One way of understanding the predictive model inside of our brains is that it might not be about &gt;just predicting the future in general, but predicting future sensory data given our current motor &gt;actions.</p> </blockquote> <p>By attempting to predict future sensory input (data) based on current actions, one essentially gets this sense of interaction - one can see the direct effect of their actions on the world, and most importantly, accordingly correct their prediction errors in a more grounded way. Working with World Models come with plenty of other advantages (and limitations), but this will be for another blogpost. This research direction is a major one of my PhD.</p> <h4 id="grounding">Grounding</h4> <p>Symbolic grounding is a fundamental question in AI, which looks at how abstract symbolic representations (like words, concepts, or logical statements) acquire meaning and connection to real-world sensory experiences and perceptual data. Many make the argument that Neural Networks simply do not learn good symbolic representations by learning in the statistical way they do. However, some people argue otherwise. Ellie Pavlick dedicated an <a href="convincingly(https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rsta.2022.0041)">entire (and beautiful) article</a> to outlining counterarguments to the common criticism of LLMs: 1) their lack of symbolic structure and 2) their lack of grounding. She points to research that, instead of showing failures of Neural Networks and using this as an argument against symbolic structure or grounding, looks at the representations that models use under the hood, which paints a much more positive picture.</p> <p>Long story short, I am now a bit unsure what to think about this.</p> <h2 id="can-neural-networks-do-system-2">Can Neural Networks do System 2?</h2> <h3 id="traditional-system-2---planners-and-search">Traditional System 2 - Planners And Search</h3> <h3 id="whats-missing">What’s Missing</h3> <h2 id="how-do-we-connect-system-1-and-system-2">How do we connect System 1 and System 2?</h2> <h3 id="chain-of-thought--test-time-training">Chain-Of-Thought &amp; Test-Time-Training</h3> <h3 id="neuro-symbolic-approaches">Neuro-Symbolic Approaches</h3> <h3 id="what-does-neuroscience-tell-us-about-system-1-and-system-2-thinking">What does Neuroscience tell us about System 1 and System 2 thinking?</h3> <p>&lt;!– - name: System 1 and System 2 - A Paradigm for Progress in AI Research</p> <ul> <li>name: Can Neural Networks do System 1?</li> <li>subsections: <ul> <li>name: Neural Networks are quintessential System 1</li> <li>name: Foundation Models as generalist System 1 models</li> <li>name: What’s missing for good system 1 thinking?</li> </ul> </li> <li>name: Can Neural Networks do System 2?</li> <li>subsections: <ul> <li>name: Traditional System 2 - Planners And Search</li> <li>name: What’s Missing</li> </ul> </li> <li>name: How do we connect System 1 and System 2?</li> <li>subsections: <ul> <li>name: Chain-Of-Thought &amp; Test-Time-Training</li> <li>name: Neuro-Symbolic Approaches</li> <li>name: What does Neuroscience tell us about System 1 and System 2 thinking? –&gt;</li> </ul> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You may have heard of System 1 &amp; System 2 thinking paradigms for AI - inspired from Cognitive Science theory. Greg Brockman (OpenAI’s CEO) Tweeted this a couple of weeks ago, upon release of OpenAI’s latest model “OpenAI o1”. So what’s System 1 &amp; System 2 thinking? And what can it teach us about the strengths, limitations and research avenues of AI research?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cape Town</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/cape-town/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cape Town"/><published>2024-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/cape-town</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/cape-town/"><![CDATA[<p>“<em>It looks like a movie scene where they tried to show that humanity is united</em>”</p> <p>DISLCAIMER: All thoughts shared here are personal opinions and impressions based on the small amount of things I have seen during my five days in Cape Town. I did not do in-depth research on what I discuss, which may make my analysis very superficial in some instances.</p> <h2 id="context">Context</h2> <p>In early October, Anas told me about a conference he would attend in Cape Town, South Africa - The Africa Tech Festival. He half-jokingly told me I should join him. Obviously, I laughed - as I’m in the middle of my PhD, with important deadlines coming soon, the middle of November 2024 was certainly not the right time to go a journey to the other side of the world. “I’ll get you a speaker role at the conference, so it counts as work” he’d say. And he said the same to a couple of other close friends of his. In the end, not only he convinced me to fly, but we also did manage to get me a speaker role at the conference. I was offered to be on two panels: “<em>Executing the AI Vision: Fine-Tuning Tactical Integration for Maximum Enterprise Impact</em>” and “<em>Panel: Mastering the Market with AI: Building a Competitive Advantage</em>”. And well, and of course, I accepted both.</p> <p>So here I am, joining Anas (and his friend Josiah, who also got seduced by Anas’ offer and flew from London) in Cape Town, in the middle of November and PhD chaos. And oh boy - I don’t regret coming.</p> <h2 id="the-conference">The Conference</h2> <p>This is, perhaps ironically, the least interesting part of the blogpost.</p> <p>My impressions of the conference are very similar to my impressions of Gitex (see my thoughts <a href="/_posts/2024-06-04-gitex.md">here</a>). The African tech space is putting an incredible and inspiring amount of work and effort on the continent. What was interesting about the African Tech Festival compared to Gitex is that it was a different population <d-footnte>We didn't see a single Moroccan person.&lt;/d-footnote&gt;. I remember Gitex to be full of Maghrebis and people from the Arab world, as well as many people from closer subsaharan countries, while this one was either Europeans/Americans or people from Southern African countries. Interestingly, there were more Europeans at this conference than Gitex - depsite the geographical proximity to Europe that Gitex has. It reflects a reality about this place - Europeans/Americans are much more present business-wise in Cape Town <d-footnote>I say Cape Town, and not South Africa, purposely. This city is a bit like London - a different country within a country </d-footnote> than they are in Morocco.</d-footnte></p> <p>Regarding the content of the conference, and the average attitude of people - I’d say it really was the same as Gitex - lots of people talking about tech or other buzzword of the sort for their business, without solid understanding of what’s going on. And of course, everyone talks about adapting things to the African market, and the challenge of doing so. Interestingly, I had a conversation with a man after my panel who complained about this narrative of “fixing everything for Africa” (as a reaction to me talking about the need to get data bases for African languages for Language Models etc..). Well, he is right in the sense that this narrative is a political one, that drives divide between the west and Africa. Local adaptation is needed in every country one thinks about going to - it’s not only a problem in Africa. In that sense - why are we talking about Tech for Africa, and why are we not just talking about Tech, which we happen to talk about in Africa.</p> <p>But is this really legitimate of a thing to say? Can we really talk about “Tech” independantly of the Africa suffixe, when talking about it here? Well, I have mixed feeligs about this. The reality is that there is close to 0 Deep Tech here - no research, no novel development, and no groundbreaking creativity. It’s always borrowing ideas and tools from the West, and adapting them to the local reality.</p> <p>I think the Disapora is key in this equation. Companies, and families that can afford it, should keep sending people studying/working in the west, and learning about what’s going on. At the same time, the quality of universities here has to improve. We don’t need African tech, we need Tech that happens to be invented on African soil, by African people - and Bootstraping our way through it the way we are currently doing it might not cut it - especially with how fast the rest of the world is going.</p> <p>At the end of the day, this is how you attract talents, and not opportunists. While Gitex and African Tech Festival have been amazing and inspiring, I feel like the wave of work motivated immigration here is more centered around opportunism, and the illusion of “faster, easier” <d-footnote>It's neither faster nor easier</d-footnote> growth <d-footnote>There is however less competition </d-footnote>. I’m always inspired by companies who do open-source science, and end up attracting talents along the way because they do cool open work that everyone knows about <d-footnote>Meta and Google are probably top examples of this, as opposed to Apple, or more recently, the wave of people leaving OpenAI. </d-footnote>.</p> <h2 id="notes-to-myself">Notes To Myself</h2> <ul> <li>The second panel “<em>Panel: Mastering the Market with AI: Building a Competitive Advantage</em>” was a bit of an issue, as it was Marketing centric. I shouldn’t have accepted to do this because I knew I wouldn’t really be able to say much - and indeed I was right. But I managed in the end. I realized halfway through chatting with the other panelsits (45 minutes before the panel) that I was better off moderating and letting them talk about their field, and I managed to make that happen without an issue because our moderator was not prepared either. Perhaps that was the biggest issue, that we did not have proper modertation and time for preparation based on the questions. I think back of my piano teacher (Alex) advice: “don’t ever play in public if you are not ready to give 100% - I always play as if Herbie Hanckock was listenning to me, because you never know what people film and put out there these days, or how they remember your image”. I’m probably better off refusing (even if tempting) opportunities where I won’t properly shine, rather than do them and be mid. In this case it was fine because I ended up doing ok, but it could have been worse.</li> <li>I shake my legs when I’m eager to answer and anxious, and people saw this in the public. I also speak too fast.</li> </ul> <h2 id="impressions">Impressions</h2> <h3 id="first-impressions">First Impressions</h3> <p>Of course, you can’t fly to South Africa without having heard about how bad the segregation is, about its presence 30 years after the end of Apartheid.</p> <p>I felt aspects of this even before landing on South African land. Indeed, the last 10 minutes of our flight, we had the chance to fly around, with a beautiful weather, over Cape Town. We oversaw, within the span of a few seconds, marvellous Californian Style villas with swimming pools, shortly followed by kilometers of slums as we were approaching the airport. Indeed, the airport is surrounded by them, and so is the city. The city is also filled with stunning neighbourhoods, and beautiful villas - and I am sure that I don’t need to specify which populations dominates each habitation.</p> <p>Let’s dive in.</p> <h3 id="segregation-and-disparities">Segregation and Disparities</h3> <p>There are three distinct “ethnicities” in Cape Town - the white South Africans (Afrikaners), the black South Africans, and the “colored” people.</p> <p>I saw neighbourhoods, or restaurants where not a single white person was around, or similarly, where not a single black person was around. It’s evident that the mixing is limited, and that the different populations have their own lifestyles. Obviously, one instantly notices that the average wealth, education and access levels are much higher in white communities than black communities.</p> <p>The different communities of South Africa do not have to mix - they only have to respect one another. They are different cultures, communities, and this is exactly the strength of this country. While one may see a country where communities do not mingle, I chose to see a country where communities peacefully cohabit and work together to build a greater life - and that is incredibly powerful.</p> <p>Gabie, a french speaking black woman from Gabon who works in Energies, has been living in Cape Town for 11 years, and assured me that she did not feel any “segregation”. Sure, there is often no mixing, but she never felt discriminated or looked at differently because she was black - and so since she started her studies in Cape Town.</p> <h2 id="kindness">Kindness</h2> <p>People were really so kind. Every Uber driver, every waiter, every local we’ve interacted with were just so incredibly kind. But indeed - we mostly interacted with workers in low-qualified jobs, and most of them were immigrants themselves from surrounding African countries (Somalia, Zimbabwe, Mozambique, Botswana etc…).</p> <p>Still, pretty much every interaction we’ve had was filled with what felt like genuine kindness. Not the kind of “interested” or “fake” kindness that one would experience in the US for example - small talk always felt genuine, and people constantly smiled.</p> <h3 id="cape-town-overseas-european-city">Cape Town, Overseas European City?</h3> <p>It often felt like we were in Europe. Oranjezicht City Farm was perhaps the most European place of all - it really felt like walking around Borough Market, or similar, in London. Indeed, the population was mostly white, and the habits, shops, decoration and vibe was all very Western.</p> <p>Antony, a pretty well established Brit in the African Tech space, who lives in Cape Town, described Cape Town as the entry door for Westerners to the world of Africa. It has most components of what Africa is about, but still is “Western enough” that the cultural shock is not too big for investors and techies - which soothes them into the territory.</p> <h3 id="national-identity-and-the-rainbow-nation">National Identity and The Rainbow Nation</h3> <p>The Rainbow Nation - that’s really what it is. Cape Town felt like an immigration hub, where everyone was welcome, and could do what they wanted. The African version of the American dream! What’s most interesting is that this is felt accross all layers of society. I’ll remember on the first day a conversation with the Uber driver who told me that he found in South Africa a place where he could live the way he wanted, free of the extreme social pressures of his country (Rwanda).</p> <p>So it’s not only Techies and investors who come here for freedom, good work opportunities and peaceful life - it’s everyone.</p> <p>What’s interesting however is that this sense of freedom leads to a different sense of belonging and nationalism. The “nationalism” feels somewhat weaker because it’s bather in multiculturalism. It’s very obvious when we compare to Morocco, which feels significantly more nationalist for instance, with a lot less immigration, and a much more unified identity and culture - and a clear (peaceful) “fight” against the rest of the world. It’s as if Morocco was this big football team, ready to fight against other teams. South Africa, in contrast, is not a football team, but rather a football pitch - they are happy to welcome anyone who’s willing to play a good game of football.</p> <h2 id="stories">Stories</h2> <p>Just a bunch of memorable stories from our trip. This is me writing to my 60 year old self, and hopefully, my kids or even grandkids lol. Hopefully, Anas’ kids too.</p> <ul> <li>First Uber Driver: My first uber driver, who drove Anas and myself from the airport to the airbnb, was from Rwanda. He fled the country a couple years prior in search of better life conditions, and of freedom from the violence and civil war in his country. And let’s say it worked quite well. He got married with another immigrant from Rwanda, and they have 8 children together. Yes, 8. Oh, and the oldest child is 12 years old - you do the maths there. But he did say that 8 was enough, more would be too much work otherwise. On another note, he had to pay “la Dotte” to marry his wife. Yes, flat cash payment to the family of the bride is still done in some cultures.</li> <li>Free food: They just give free food here. Josiah ordered some rice and chicken, and they delivered 3 times the quantity he had ordered - just like this. Anas had the same when he ordered a Pizza, and got 4 delivered, for no reason. In general, it’s representative of South African culture - they don’t count there, they just are generous with their time, energy, and food. It’s all “chill”.</li> <li>Tetouan/Venezuelan Jew: While at the conference, this friend of ours (let’s call him James) told us about this person (let’s call him Rodriguo). James, who is straight, made a comment about Rodriguo being hot - no one knew nor had seen Rodriguo before. A couple minutes later, James comes back to us and continues talking about Rodriguo: “I feel like I’ve seen this guy before for some reason”. Eventually, James realizes that his own ex dated Rodriguo right before him. It however doesn’t end well. The next day, while at a party with the conference people, we actually see Rodriguo speaking to a friend of ours, and engage conversation with him. While he is a bit of a prick, we do end up vibing and chatting, because it so happens that Rodriguo’s family is Moroccan, and that he visits every year, and knows every important person in the Moroccan Tech Ecosystem. Rodriguo’s family, who is from Tetouan, migrated to Venezuela in the 60s after the Protectorate ended, and kept close ties with Morocco, effectively coming back almost every year. It’s of the utmost important to his grandmother to go pray on the graves of her parents and grandparents in the Tetouan cemetery every time she comes back.</li> <li>Bird fly as high as bin bags: While admiring the view from our 12th floor appartment, I noticed a confidently flying black bird. It took me a few seconds to realize that it wasn’t a bird, but actually a bin bag. I saw this as a metaphore of what this country was about: “a mix between San Fransisco and the Lion King”, or a place where greatness is often very close from chaos and misery. It so turns out that Cape Town is filled with a specific species of black birds, called “Redwing Starlings”, who have the peculiarity of having a beautiful orange color on the inner side of their wings - which is hidden when they are not flying. Anas called them the “Louboutin birds”.</li> <li>Cheap Labour: One can tell how cheap the labour is with the amount of unnecessary staff that one can see everywhere - staff which really doesn’t do much. Ever single room of the MOCCA museum had someone working there and watching over the art. Sure, maybe that’s normal for a museum because one needs to ensure that the art is not touched, but it really was like that everywhere. It seems that tourism and a select rich few are driving the entirety of the economy, and enabling an ocean of not-very-productive jobs. Of course, all this staff is drafted from the big wave of immigration from African countries - and that’s one of the things that drives this feeling of “segregation”. All the lower-paying jobs are taken by black-people.</li> <li>Security: A good way to understand how unsafe Cape Town is, is to notice how much security is present everywhere one goes. Of course, tourists, because of devaluation of the REN, and a higher purchasing power, will tend to go in “golden-gated” communities, where one sees a very significant amount of security, all the time. The building of our airbnb had 2 security guards at the entrance, 24/7. Every villa is filled with cameras, and very likely has security-staff inside.</li> <li>This life is getting weirder and weirder: Here we were, on a random Wednesday evening, at the Hyatt lobby in Cape Town, meeting with friends whom we did not know were in Cape Town, whom we know from London. Of course, it had to be at the Hyatt.</li> <li>“Refa7tina bel dikrayat”: Translates to “You elevated us with memories”. Anas’ grand grand mother used to say this to Anas’ grandfather when he was taking her out to the restaurant. It was such a special thing for her to go to the restaurant, that while she was there, she was already acknowledging that this would become a beautiful memory.</li> <li>G. and the very productive business dinner: X invested in G.’s company, and was to meet G properly in person in Cape Town for dinner. Being an advisor and good friend of X, I was invited to join them for dinner, which was a lot of fun. Halfway through dinner, when the mood had gotten informal <d-footnote>(X, G and myself are around the same age - late 20s)</d-footnote>, G notices in a table nearby a very beautiful woman, and jokingly expresses interest and curiosity. I can understand why he went to speak to her, she resembled Louisa, and looked almost as beautiful as her. When the dinner finished, when went out, said goodbye, and while we were getting in the Uber, he jokingly hinted at wanting to go back inside to talk to her. X and I went on with our evening and forgot about this, but the next day we get a screenshot of that girl having texted him. Well done G - I owe you dinner in Morocco if you ever come by.</li> <li>Saoudis doing Saoudi things: “How much redbull?” he asked to a walking-seller. “30 RENs (1.5 euros)”. “Lower price, lower price!”. Dude you’re filthy rich wtf and a humble worker is asking you a very normal price for a Redbull - WTF.</li> <li>Camp’s Bay: We had our first evening at Camp’s Bay, which he thought was absolutely marvelous of a place, on the seafront, somehow like Palm Beach in California. We dreamed about having a house there. But then we were told by someone that Camp’s Bay really was just where all the “exited founders” retired. The new place to be became Clifton. Funnily enough, we visited an apartment in Camp’s Bay - and yeah we don’t really want to be there. Now we know Constantia is where it’s at.</li> <li>Berti: One incredibly sweet South African lady, Berti, sold us a few products in a cute little shop of a marvelous <a href="https://www.thecellars-hohenorthotel.com/">hotel</a>. Her family emigrated from Switzerland more than 70 years ago, and she spent all of her life here. She was very sad because she unfortunately cannot leave South Africa, because of how expensive it is for her to come here, given the devaluation of the REN. That was sad.</li> <li>Kind and subtle waiter: While at the restaurant, Anas and I had a difficult conversation where he shed a few tears. One waiter was passing by to take back our plates, and saw Anas tearing up. A few minutes later, I stood up to go to the bathroom and she asked me “are you having a good afternoon sir?”. Having answered (a bit too) positively, she admitted having asked because she “saw [my] friend crying”. I assured her that things were alright, and she smiled, and that was it. So much class and consideration in this gesture.</li> </ul> <h2 id="places-visited-and-recommendations">Places Visited And Recommendations</h2> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.thecellars-hohenorthotel.com/">The Cellars-Hohenort</a></li> <li><a href="https://ozcf.co.za/ozcfmarket/">Oranjezicht market</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.gigirooftop.com/">Gigi Rooftop Restaurant</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.tablemountain.net/">Table Mountain</a></li> <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfpFVv9595G_GZ6Pw32_Cg27K8p7gmG63NVEiwiak-5PVlaDg/viewform">Lionshead Mountain, and Will’s group hike</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.kovecollection.co.za/the-bungalow/">The Bungalow</a></li> <li><a href="https://clubkloof.com/">Club Koof</a></li> </ul> ]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“It looks like a movie scene where they tried to show that humanity is united”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The North Star of My PhD (Part 1)</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/phd-north-star/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The North Star of My PhD (Part 1)"/><published>2024-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/phd-north-star</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/phd-north-star/"><![CDATA[<p>For the past 9 months, I have been spending a vast amount of time thinking and reading about a large variety of Machine Learning and Neuroscience problems and methods. I’m often asked what my PhD is about <d-footnote>Hi dad</d-footnote> - and I struggle to answer. This is my attempt at answering.</p> <h1 id="part-1---the-arc-challenge-a-north-star-benchmark-to-my-phd">Part 1 - The ARC Challenge, A North Star Benchmark to my PhD</h1> <p>Great inventions often hold hidden secrets that only reveal themselves with time. This is what I think of Francois Chollet’s <a href="https://arcprize.org/">Abstraction And Reasoning Corpus (ARC) Challenge</a>, which has, since I have started thinking about it in August 2022, made me, and countless others, think about an ocean of different problems and research avenues. This small dataset of little and simple visual puzzles somehow still holds bullet-proof to the entirety of modern Deep Learning (including the latest iterations of LLMs), and encompasses the vast majority of modern “Artificial Intelligence” challenges.</p> <p>The goal of my PhD is not to solve ARC. However, my PhD somehow keeps ARC as a <em>North Star</em> - a source of inspiration, to think and internalize all the sub-challenges one should think of to make progress on ARC - to make progress on better Deep Learning, and maybe even, dare I say it, make progress towards Artificial-General-Intelligence (AGI).</p> <p>In this essay, I will introduce some of these sub-problems and discuss some works that I believe to be of great possible impact. Before diving in, let’s first go through a little prelude about the ARC challenge, what makes it special, and why it remains unsolved by State-Of-The-Art Deep Learning.</p> <h2 id="what-is-arc">What is ARC?</h2> <p>The Abstraction and Reasoning Corpus (ARC) is an ensemble of IQ-test like puzzles <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01547">proposed by Francois Chollet in 2019</a>. Chollet introduced ARC as a benchmark on which both humans and AI systems could fairly compete, aiming to steer AI research in a different direction. Indeed, Chollet argued that while everyone was constantly talking about AGI, the community had no clue of how to measure it, and that the current benchmarks and methodologies, overly led to overfitting to single tasks - which is not representative of <em>intelligence</em>. His aim was to create a different benchmark, one that would be difficult to solve with the classical Deep Learning framework - one that would force us to rethink how we do Artificial Intelligence.</p> <p>The structure of ARC is elegantly simple, and indeed unlike any machine learning benchmark at the time. Solvers are presented with a set of <em>training</em> (demonstration) examples, each consisting of input-output pairs in grid format. The challenge is to infer the underlying rule that transforms the input grid into its corresponding output grid, then apply the inferred rule to a new <em>test</em> input grid. To top it all, there are only 800 puzzles publicly available - all very different from one another - a very low amount of data for today’s Deep Learning standards and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2001.08361">scaling laws</a>.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/north_star_phd/ARC_Examples-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/north_star_phd/ARC_Examples-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/north_star_phd/ARC_Examples-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/north_star_phd/ARC_Examples" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>The ARC “world” is clearly defined. It is always built from n&gt;2 training (demonstration) examples, and a single testing grid where one must apply the rule from the demonstration to the new grid. The grids are always sized between 1x1 and 30x30 pixels. Each pixel can take any of 10 colors - represented by numbers from 0 to 9. While clearly defined, the ARC-world is also particularly “open-ended”, as the concepts that can be represented and which make up rules are… well.. open-ended. Chollet defined what a solver agent (human or computational) should know of to be able to solve the tasks (paraphrasing Chollet and <a href="https://aiguide.substack.com/p/why-the-abstraction-and-reasoning">Melanie Mitchell</a>):</p> <ul> <li><em>Objectness</em>: knowledge that the world can be parsed into <em>objects</em> that have certain physical properties</li> <li><em>Numerosity</em>: knowledge of small quantities and notions of “smallest,” “largest,” “greater than,” “less than,” etc</li> <li><em>Geometry and Topology</em>: knowledge of lines, simple shapes, symmetries, containment, and copying</li> <li><em>Agents and Goals</em>: knowledge that some entities are <em>agents</em> who have their own intentions and act to achieve goals</li> </ul> <p>But how do we go about teaching a model about all of these stuff? Like <em>actually</em> teach it what e.g. a “line” is, and all the different things lines can represent and be used for? Let’s think about why we understand this as humans first.</p> <h2 id="why-can-humans-solve-arc-perfectly">Why can humans solve ARC perfectly?</h2> <p>A “traditionally” smart human can solve <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UakqL6Pj9xo&amp;t=53s&amp;ab_channel=DwarkeshPatel">100% of ARC tasks</a>, and Amazon Turk workers can solve ARC tasks <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2409.01374v1">with 75% to 85% accuracy</a>.</p> <p>But <strong>why</strong>? Why do humans manage so well compared to machines, without any pre-training? We do not have the answer to this question as there is no definite “neuroscience” explanation to our capacity to reason and generalize. However, we can analyze some patterns of capabilities that us humans have to understand what allows us to solve ARC tasks.</p> <p>Humans learn about all of the concepts in use in ARC through years of <em>exposure</em> and <em>interaction</em>. Let’s take the concept of number “three” or “3” as an example. Not only do we learn what “three” means by being shown three fingers, three pens, or three heads on Cerebrus’ head, but we also learn how to say three words, draw three lines, eat three meals a day. The concept “three” is not only seen but also <strong>interacted</strong> with, and even <strong>produced</strong> in a wide range of different contexts. Its meaning and representation in our brain is multi faceted and highly malleable - specifically because we have <em>actively</em> learned about it through interaction and production, as opposed to just <em>passively</em> through exposure.</p> <p>Because this is not a scientific paper, I’ll allow myself an analogy with my other passion - music. When learning to improvise music, there is a lot of theory that one can learn about: scales, harmonies, voicing etc… One can learn all the theory in the world and analyze as much music as they can, but there is nothing replacing actively practicing the concepts learned on one’s instrument over and over to fully internalize them. Once the concepts are internalized - one can just stop thinking about them in a strict way, and can freely develop an intuition - a <em>feel</em> - to combine all the different concepts together, on the spot, effortlessly and without rationalization. <d-footnote>Today, it's common to use the word "grok" to express this deep internalization of a given concept. The AI model of X (former Twitter) is named Grok. I think that's cool. </d-footnote>.</p> <p>This active form of learning through interaction leads us to better internalize concepts, and a wide variety of them that we unconsciously interact with daily. While this internalization is already a strong advantage compared to modern Deep Learning systems, our edge over them doesn’t stop there. We are also able to effortlessly <strong>compose</strong> between these different concepts in novel contexts - by virtue of having internalized them the way we did. Because we properly internalized the concept of “three”, or the concept “squares”, we can on the fly compose them, even in completely novel ways, and understand everything that one can do with these. This is indeed only possible if the essence of these concepts and ideas are properly internalized - which Deep Learning can never achieve through learning by being exposed to data.</p> <p>Besides composing concepts, we also have immediate <strong>intuitions</strong> over which concepts to use when first encountering a situation. This is exactly what happens when you look at the ARC puzzles - just by virtue of seeing the colors, grid like structures, and shapes, you immediately discard the toolbox of Maxwell’s equations, driving a car, or even Dancing a Waltz. You only need to search through the plausible solutions that are reasonably applicable to the domain you are now facing - and that’s mostly intuition. Of course, you need to try a bunch of different ideas, but the ideas you try are all pretty reasonable given the context, and the time you need to reach a solution subsequently dramatically shrinks. Imagine if you had to consider every single thing you know of to solve these puzzles?</p> <p>All these aspects are crucial to our intelligence, and they are missing from modern Deep Learning systems, and are exactly the type of things that ARC is meant to test for.</p> <h2 id="why-does-machine-learning-suck-at-arc">Why does Machine Learning suck at ARC?</h2> <p>One thing Deep Learning is very good at is “memorization”. This means fitting a training data distribution curve, in such a way that everything that is close enough to what has been seen before can be correctly dealt with. It reminds me of my own self in high school, where we had been introduced to Newton’s Laws. While we had already studied integration and differentiation in Mathematics class, I was just completely unable to use the concepts and apply them to Newton’s laws (or any Physics related concepts). I had “<em>memorized</em>” how to solve the maths exercises about differentiation and integration, but I hadn’t “<em>understood</em>” what integration and differentiation really were about.</p> <p>Modern Deep Learning is exactly like high-school me - incentivized to do “shortcut learning” and minimize a loss function (like when I was maximizing my high school math grades), while never really understanding what things really mean. And this is precisely why ARC has, five year after its release, still not been solved. It is designed to prevent any form of <em>memorization</em>, as all puzzles are very different, and very little data is available. It is designed to test <em>understanding</em> and <em>learning efficiency</em> - as a solver must have a good intuition and conceptualization of the different concepts of the puzzles, and manage to figure out how to use them with very little amount of context. It is designed to need <em>composing</em> of different types of knowledge, and so with very little amount of context.</p> <p>Five years after its release, ARC indeed held its promise, as it still is very far from having satisfying solutions. State-Of-The-Art Large Language Models (LLMs) are nowhere near solving it <d-footnote> albeit the recent efforts of [Ryan Greenblatt](https://redwoodresearch.substack.com/p/getting-50-sota-on-arc-agi-with-gpt) made us doubt for a brief moment.</d-footnote>, and the current best solution comes from a team which, although doing great work, is vastly over-fitting to ARC, which I believe to be somewhat against the spirit of the challenge.</p> <h2 id="the-importance-of-benchmarks-and-the-perils-of-goodharts-law">The importance of Benchmarks, and the perils of Goodhart’s Law</h2> <p>Besides important scientific insights into what artificial intelligence (or simply “intelligence”) are about, the ARC Challenge taught me quite a few important things.</p> <p>One central idea is how essential benchmarks are to steer progress. Chollet noted in his essay that the entirety of the ML community was focused on benchmarks that ultimately measures “skill”, as opposed to “intelligence”. Skill, through unlimited training data, is not what makes any agent intelligent. <em>Skill acquisition efficiency</em> however, is much more interesting, because it underlies the potential of a given algorithm to learn new things and adapt when needed - which is what Chollet considers to be a hallmark of intelligence. This strongly reminded me of <a href="https://www.8vc.com/resources/lessons-from-peter-thiel">Peter Thiel’s hiring philosophy</a>: “The key in hiring is to value potential skill rather than currently existing skill — potential skill is based on intelligence rather than training”.</p> <p>This realization by Chollet was no news to most people that had seriously thought about the problem - but the genius of his effort was to provide a benchmark that controlled for what he thought were ways to different (and better) AI research. And well, 6 years after its publication (an eternity in the world of AI), people still talk about this, and it subtly steers the community towards a different kind of progress.</p> <p>This is what works in AI, and what works in the world - humans always try to signal quality by performing on some metric, and end up optimizing (and often “over-optimizing”) for that specific metric, which ultimately steers evolution. In AI, this really is particularly efficient - if the community judges one benchmark as interesting, one can just let “<a href="https://x.com/TBen_Yassine/status/1801296865654177913">graduate student descent</a>” do its job, and a plethora of methods improving performance on this metric will follow.</p> <p>Obviously, the other side of the coin is the well known Goodhart Law “When a metric becomes the target, it stops being a good metric”. And that applies to ARC too, even if it was specifically designed to avoid overfitting <d-footnote>the current SOTA solutions from MindsAI uses a fine tuned transformer on a ton of algorithmically generated ARC-like tasks and all the tricks in the books to optimize performance on transformers is clearly overfitting to ARC. </d-footnote></p> <p>Ultimately, there is no benchmark that cannot be gamed with enough time an effort. This is why it’s important to use multiple metrics, and to keep on updating the metrics. Most importantly, it’s important to regularly ask ourselves the question, as a community, company or organization - what do we really want to achieve? And what would achieving it look like?</p> <p>So what do we really want to achieve in AI research? And what would achieving it look like?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For the past 9 months, I have been spending a vast amount of time thinking and reading about a large variety of Machine Learning and Neuroscience problems and methods. I’m often asked what my PhD is about Hi dad - and I struggle to answer. This is my attempt at answering.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to make conversation with a PhD student?</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/hiring-phds/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to make conversation with a PhD student?"/><published>2024-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/hiring-phds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/hiring-phds/"><![CDATA[<p>I often heard employers express frustration over their experience hiring and working with PhD graduates in their companies. Employers either hire PhD graduates expecting incredible performance and quality of work on all aspects, or don’t even bother hiring them because they are “over-qualified”, “overly theoretical”, and “disconnected from reality”.</p> <p>I think this is all a bit like trying to drink soup with a fork - it certainly won’t work, but that doesn’t mean the fork can never be useful.</p> <p>In this post, I try to tell you about what forks can be used for, what different types of forks exist, and how to pick the best one for your needs.</p> <h2 id="what-are-phd-students-good-and-bad-at">What Are PhD Students good (and bad) at?</h2> <p>Every PhD student goes through a unique path to graduate - influenced by the working environment, their supervisors, the project/field they are working on, and their own personality. To understand what a PhD can be good at, it’s important to investigate key aspects of a PhD journey.</p> <p>So what should you try to dig into to understand what the PhD student you have in front of you is made of?</p> <h3 id="phd-idiosyncrasy-1---finding-a-niche">PhD idiosyncrasy 1 - Finding a Niche</h3> <p><strong>Why is this super important within a PhD</strong></p> <p>The greatest challenge of a PhD is to find a niche to work on and contribute to. Finding that niche, that research question, is often significantly harder than finding the answer. The space of possibilities, the existing literature… it’s just so all vast and endless… One needs to fully integrate and balance 1) their ambitions, expertise, weaknesses, 2) the state-of-the-art of their field, and 3) the realities and resources of people they work, all into a cohesive direction to have maximal impact without suffering too much.</p> <p>It’s very unlike the corporate world where it is permissible to have two companies doing exactly the same thing and competing against one another. The great ambition of the researcher is to be unique, to bring radically novel ideas to the community <d-footnote>Wink Wink Jurgen Schmidhuber </d-footnote>. This is also the great peril of the academic - by being obsessed with being novel and unique, they often risk locking themselves in territories only relevant to their own self.</p> <p>The great challenge of the PhD student is to find that one north star in their research, that guides them to work on ideas they can pursue better than anyone else, but which are also interesting to other humans.</p> <p><strong>The different styles of doing it</strong></p> <p>Broadly, there are two ways through which PhD students build their research. In each case, the student is lost in some way.</p> <ol> <li><strong>PhD 1: Lost in a Sports Pitch:</strong> The supervisor already has a <strong>clear</strong> idea of what they want to student to do <d-footnote>In my lab, we often speak of "Supervisor-2-real-gap", to signify the gap between what a supervisor thinks is feasible vs what is actually feasible. So I insist on **clear** here - some supervisors really know well what they want and how to achieve it, and some only have a broad idea. The latter category lead to experience # 2. </d-footnote>, and the students don’t really have to investigate much besides putting to reality the ideas of the supervisor, and adding their own spice to it. These PhD experiences are a bit like experiences of expert athletes - in need of becoming the best of the bests at that one specific sport in which pitch they happened to have gotten stuck in. They need the best sports coach and training-mates in town, as well as great resources and equipment to be competitive. It’s hard in its own way.</li> <li><strong>PhD 2: Lost in the Ocean</strong>: The supervisor only has a <strong>loose</strong> idea of what they want the student to do, leaving it up to the students to determine the specific direction of their research. In this case, the challenge shifts entirely—it’s about finding land before you run out of energy. One knows they can reach land by swimming in any direction, but some paths are longer, some are stormier, and some are filled with sharks. You must feel the Ocean, ask nearby swimmers how they chose their direction, then decide on your own, commit, and keep swimming. It’s not about getting there faster than everyone else (like PhD 1), but about the story of how you reached land, and the critical things you learned along the way about the Ocean - that everyone can learn something from.</li> </ol> <p><strong>How can you leverage this knowledge in your company</strong></p> <p>Well, the first thing you should do is to try to understand how the PhD applicants found their research path. How they took risks, how they played things safe, how they made things work when it was not going well. Get them to describe it in as much depth as possible - you’ll find a myriad of stories that will shine great light into the personality of the applicant.</p> <p>Some will have gone through experience 1 but felt suffocated by it, and some will have gone through experience 2 and enjoyed the struggle of it all. These ones you may want to give bigger projects to, longer term ideas that need deep thinking and slow refinement.</p> <p>Others will have gone through experience 2 but almost failed to make it to land, or gone through experience 1 and did great in that setting. These ones, you should give clear directions to, and shorter term, tangible goals.</p> <p>In all cases, by discussing these issues, you should get a queue of whether your applicant is driven by big questions, the kind that can make an industry shift in a different direction, or if they are driven by solving one little problem after another - and getting things done well.</p> <p>At the end of the day, the real superpower that all PhD student must acquire is the ability to find that niche and exploit it well. Most employers see the hyperspecialization of PhD graduates as a problem, because the niche doesn’t translate well to “real world” needs - but that completely omits the process through which they went through to actually hyperspecialize. If you know how to do things well, you can work with them to find a new unexplored niche within your industry, and get them to find insights, and work on things that no one else has found before.</p> <h3 id="phd-idiosyncrasy-2---framing-the-niche">PhD idiosyncrasy 2 - Framing the niche</h3> <p><strong>Why is this super important within a PhD</strong></p> <p>“Creatives have two masters: the art and the medium. Only serve the art, and you won’t find an audience. Only serve the medium, and your work will lose its soul. It’s the dance between them that makes a successful creative.” <d-footnote> Quote by the wonderful David Perell" </d-footnote>.</p> <p>PhD students must communicate their research - they must publish papers, go to conferences, discuss it with peers, and get their work out. It’s also the way for them to meet people to work with, but more on that later. The way they do is extremely individual, and can show a lot about their way of doing things.</p> <p><strong>The different styles of doing it</strong></p> <p>“PhD students suck at writing the first two pages of a papers” <d-footnote>From a coffee chat conversation with Prof. Thilo Stadelmann </d-footnote>.</p> <p>PhD students are often fantastic appendix writers - writing these long memos that almost no one will read but are technically very precise and are the foundations the ideas are. Often, these PhD students will also be horrible at writing an introduction (the first two pages of the paper) - where one must contextualize within the literature, and dream big about the potential impact and outlook of the science. This can be <strong>by design</strong>, i.e. the given student is not good at contextualizing, or <strong>circumstantial</strong>, i.e. the student is so deep into the science that they haven’t had the chance to reflect on it in a long time.</p> <p>Sometimes it will be the other way around - some PhDs are very good at story telling and contextualization and not so good at the details. This is more rare though.</p> <p>If you are lucky, you find someone who can do both - they exist. In any case, you should figure out what is it they’re good at.</p> <p><strong>How can you leverage this knowledge in your company</strong></p> <p>Spend time investigating how they write, and how they communicate their work - even if you don’t understand it, you should be able to get the info of what was their preferred mode of functioning.</p> <h3 id="phd-idiosyncrasy-3---collaborating-within-your-niche">PhD Idiosyncrasy 3 - Collaborating within your niche</h3> <h2 id="interview-questions-to-ask-a-phd-graduate">Interview questions to ask a PhD Graduate</h2> <h3 id="what-was-your-favorite-paper-and-why">What was your favorite paper, and why?</h3> <p>This is a great question to understand what the PhD graduate in front of you finds beauty and passion in - what they look up to. I think this is super important to understand a person - understanding what they admire and why they admire it. I remember asking a dear-to-my heart Oncologist about her favorite paper. She mentioned an opinion paper <d-footnote> https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adg7671 </d-footnote> from an Oncologist, whose own son had died from Cancer at 10 years old. He reflected in this short opinion paper about this taught him of his experience being on the other side of the table - and how it humbled him to be a better doctor. I learned a lot about this person from that answer.</p> <p>A lot of students don’t have a favorite paper, nor can they even think of a paper they really liked. To me that’s a pretty strong indicator that I might not want to work with this person - how do you spend 3-6 years of your life doing something, reading and writing papers, and not having one paper that actually strongly impacted you in some way?</p> <h3 id="how-was-your-relationship-with-your-supervisor-what-were-their-strength-and-weaknesses">How was your relationship with your supervisor? What were their strength and weaknesses?</h3> <p>We all have been asked the infamous question “what your strengths and weaknesses” in interviews. And we all agree this question is not a good proxy for figuring out the answer to the question. Instead, I believe a great question is to ask about the strengths and weaknesses of the PhD supervisor of the candidate. There are two reasons for this:</p> <ol> <li>Most often, asking person X about another person Y’s strengths and weaknesses is actually the best way to find out about X’s strengths and weaknesses. People often look up to things that they wish they were better at, and find weaknesses out of things they feel they are better at themselves.</li> <li>No PhD student is indifferent to their advisor. The relationships are very often complex, difficult, changing in time, and source of tension. It’s a very good way to figure out the value system of the students - both through what worked with the supervisor, and what they wished had worked better. It’s also a good way to figure out what to expect from working with someone - will they be needy or independent? Will they be confident (even arrogant) or will they need constant support to shine?</li> </ol> <h3 id="who-has-been-the-most-important-person-to-the-success-of-your-phd-and-why">Who has been the most important person to the success of your PhD, and why?</h3> <p>In a similar spirit to the question about papers, but people oriented this time. A PhD is not completed alone - many people are instrumental in reaching the finish line. Some people who inspired you, guided you, picked you up when you were lost, or simply were present and brought you some joy every day to keep pushing. PhDs are often very lonely - but reflecting over the people whom were important to their success will tell you about the kind of human support and inspiration they need.</p> <h3 id="not-a-question-rather-an-obligation---read-the-thesis-of-your-interviewee">Not a question, rather an obligation - Read the thesis of your interviewee.</h3> <p>No need to read it all, but you should at least skim through it. It will immediately become clear how your student thinks and what they are naturally comfortable in doing. There often are no clear guidelines on how to write a PhD thesis - thus making students go rather freestyle on their writing. Some will put a lot of effort into it, some won’t. Some will write lenghty and accessible introductions, with fantastic contextualization and perspective, and some will uniquely focus on the “meat” of their science and write lengthy pages of proofs and technical perspectives.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I often heard employers express frustration over their experience hiring and working with PhD graduates in their companies. Employers either hire PhD graduates expecting incredible performance and quality of work on all aspects, or don’t even bother hiring them because they are “over-qualified”, “overly theoretical”, and “disconnected from reality”.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How 8 Gringos Gave a Speech at an Uzbek Wedding Where No One Spoke English</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/uzbekistan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How 8 Gringos Gave a Speech at an Uzbek Wedding Where No One Spoke English"/><published>2024-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/uzbekistan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/uzbekistan/"><![CDATA[<p>In June 2024, I had the chance to travel to Uzbekistan for 10 days, visit the cities of Samarkand and Bukhara, and most importantly, extensively interact with my friend Amir’s family <d-footnote>Although living in Uzbekistan and fluent in Uzbek, they consider themselves (ethnically) Tajik, as it is their first language and their ethnicity of origin. As such, they clearly differentiate themselves from Uzbek peope.</d-footnote> and attend the wedding of his cousin - <em>Dilshod Aka</em>. This trip was nothing short of extraordinary, and I try here to give an overview of why. I attempted in this blogpost to synthetize the most interesting stories and observations about my stay in Uzbekistan - a country with rich historical relevance, strong culture and traditions, and most importantly, a country still very preserved from the cultural dilution caused by globalization and mass tourism.</p> <p>Before jumping in, I’d like to extend my sincerest gratitude to Amir for organizing this trip, introducing us to his loving family, and translating the many idiosyncrasies of the Uzbek <d-footnote>Ethnically Tajik, not Uzbek.</d-footnote> society. I’d also like to thank Dilshod Aka for having us at his wedding, taking care of us throughout the entire trip, and always entertaining us with jokes and good spirit - I wish him and his <em>Kelin</em> <d-footnote>Refers to newly-wed woman. More info on this in the "Random stories and fun facts" section of the blogpost. </d-footnote> all the best for the life they are starting together.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/uzbekistan/trio_uzbek-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/uzbekistan/trio_uzbek-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/uzbekistan/trio_uzbek-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/uzbekistan/trio_uzbek.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="prelude---an-ode-to-friendship-hospitality-and-internationalization">Prelude - an Ode to Friendship, Hospitality and Internationalization</h2> <p>The story of my presence in Uzbekistan can be traced back to 2007, when Amir (11 years old at the time) and his family unexpectedly won the green card lottery and left their traditional Uzbek life in Samarkand to move to the U.S.A. In another part of the world, Ayush (around the same age as Amir), born in India, relocates with his family to the U.S.A due to his father’s work. Amir and Ayush attended the same high school in New Jersey. The great <strong>friendship</strong> that brought me to Uzbekistan started when Amir spotted the only “culturally brown” <d-footnote>directly quoting Amir</d-footnote> kid at school, and with the hope of showing off his Bollywood knowledge, approached Ayush with a shy “Hey, what’s up?”.</p> <p>Fast forward to 2023, where Ayush and I, both living in Zurich and studying at ETH, end up joining the same music band, and start hanging out - the beginning of another great <strong>friendship</strong>.</p> <p>Amir’s cousin, Dilshod Aka, has finally found <d-footnote> finding her was a long and tedious process </d-footnote> the one and set a date to get married in June, and Amir decided to pause his accountant life in New York City and attend the wedding. Eager to share the beauty of his country with his friends, he kindly asks whether a few extra seats can be left for his friends at the wedding. Dilshod Aka and his family, being the incredibly <strong>hospitable</strong> and loving people that they are, happily agree. Amir invites his closest friends, Jordan, Jake and Ayush. Funnily enough, Ayush (having already visited Uzbekistan with Amir) gives himself green card to invite his own Zurich Friends to the wedding - the more the merrier he says. And this is how I got invited to Dilshod Aka’s wedding, while having met Amir only once before, and never knowing the existence of the groom Dilshod Aka.</p> <p>In the end, we were a very <strong>international</strong> group of 8 foreigners (as Latin Americans say, a group of 8 <em>gringos</em>) present at the wedding: two Americans, one Dutch, one German, one Moroccan (me), one Indian, one Chinese-American and one Swiss. And of course, we were with our Uzbek-American host Amir during the entire trip, who took us around and translated the many conversations we had with his family members and with different locals we met throughout our journey.</p> <p>Now that the context of my presence at this wedding has been presented, let’s dig into what this trip was like!</p> <h2 id="context-and-history">Context and history</h2> <p>Some of the stories and observations I will discuss are best understood with some historical context in mind. However, if you know the situation of the country, or if you don’t really care about history, feel free to skip this part and move on to the next section.</p> <h3 id="between-persia-the-mongols-and-ussr">Between Persia, the Mongols and USSR</h3> <p>Uzbekistan, situated in Central Asia, has historically been at the crossroads of multiple significant and diverse cultural, political, and religious movements, mainly due to its position along the Silk Road. The Persians established a presence in the region, substantially establishing growth and prosperity through trade. This era saw the area become an important centre during the Islamic Golden Age, with prominent intellectuals hanging out in Bukhara or Samarkand, such as Ibn Sina or Omar El Khayyam.</p> <p>The Persian influence was ended by the Mongol invasion led by Genghis Khan. A few generations later, Timur, descendant of the Mongol elite, established Samarkand as the capital of the vast Timurid Empire. Other great leaders, from the same lineage, came after Timur, notably the astronomer Ulugh Bek, who carried on the heritage of Samarkand as a renowned center of scientific study.</p> <p>Later, Babur, a descendant of both Timur and Genghis Khan, shifted his focus eastward, conquering parts of India and founding the Mughal Empire. While Uzbekistan was not directly part of the Mughal Empire, it remained culturally connected to this powerful dynasty.</p> <p>From the 19th century onward, Uzbekistan, along with much of Central Asia, was gradually incorporated into the Russian Empire. Tashkent, the current capital, became the political center of Russian Turkestan. This Russian influence continued until the dissolution of the Soviet Union in 1991, after which Uzbekistan declared its independence.</p> <p>This simplified historical context exemplifies the wide range of cultural influences that have shaped Uzbekistan throughout its history. Persian culture dominated for several centuries. The Mongol invasion led to a golden age of knowledge and science. Islam was a constant presence, both through Persian influence and during Timurid empire reign. The Mughal Empire, founded by Babur (who was born in present-day Uzbekistan), extended its influence to India. Finally, Russian and Soviet rule left their mark on the country. All of these diverse influences remain perceptible within modern day Uzbekistan.</p> <h3 id="languages">Languages</h3> <p>The influence of all these cultures is directly sensed through the diversity of languages that are spoken in Uzbekistan, and the different influences these languages have.</p> <p>The current official state language is <em>Uzbek</em>, which is a Turkic language, and written primarily in Latin alphabet since 1993. Indeed, after the fall of the Soviet union, Uzbekistan wanted to get rid of as much Russian influence as possible - so they enforced Latin alphabet as opposed to Cyrillic to write Uzbek - which had been in place since the 1920s. Educational establishments today only teach the Latin notation, even though the Cyrillic notation is all over the place, especially amongst older generations. Fun story: a Tunisian/Turkish friend whom we met in Bukhara spoke an entire conversation in a restaurant with an Uzbek lady - my friend spoke Turkish while the waiter answered in Uzbek, and they understood each other.</p> <p><em>Tajik</em> is another commonly spoken language in Uzbekistan, particularly in the cities of Bukhara and Samarkand (where we were) because of the population of ethnic Tajiks, which is dominant in these two cities (close to modern-day Tajikistan border). The Tajik language is a dialect of Persian. While Persian is written in Persian characters (very similar to Arabic alphabet), Tajik is almost exclusively written in Cyrillic. It is not taught in schools - and is left as a spoken language between Tajik people of the region.</p> <p>Samarkand and Bukhara are mostly inhabited by ethnically Tajik people because of their significances during the various Persian dynasties (notably Timurid, Khwarazmian and Samanid). Interestingly, Tajikistan has a high population of ethnically Uzbek or Uzbek speaking people than Uzbekistan has Tajiks. In the 1900s, Soviets purposely drew borders this way to prevent countries from becoming ethnically homogeneous, and reducing the chances of possible revolution/uprising.</p> <p><em>Russian</em> is a bit like the English of the region - the common denominator for all surrounding countries. This is the language people do business with, both within Uzbekistan and across the region. The current relations between Uzbekistan and the Russian language are obviously difficult - seen by some as a language they don’t want to have anything to do with anymore, and by others as a prominent language of Uzbek history, widely spoken and useful in the region. It is today not recognized as an official language, but some people are pushing for it to be recognized as such.</p> <h3 id="end-of-dictatorship-opening-up-to-the-world-and-tourism">End of dictatorship, opening up to the world and tourism</h3> <p>In 2016, Uzbekistan’s first (authoritarian) president Islam Karimov passed - and that was the beginning of a (positive?) set of changes in the country. The new president Mirziyoyev started a gradual liberalization process, opening up the political system (although it still is far from being a democracy per se). Regional relations were drastically improved, particularly with Tajikistan and Kyrgyzstan. Media have significantly more freedom, and a subsequent freedom of what people consume over the internet - you can imagine the influence of the internet in this country. Foreign investments became more attractive, with privatization efforts from originally state-owned companies. Bref, a large set of measures of the sort that basically started putting Uzbekistan on the international map, as a safe, flourishing, open, and good country to deal with. That’s what brought me there - despite us being 300 km away from the Afghan border where things are currently much less joyful.</p> <p>What I’d like you to remember from this is that Uzbekistan has essentially opened up less than 10 years ago. This process of opening up takes a lot of time, but is typically accelerated with the increase of tourism and now available access to internet. We are still in the early days of Open-Uzbekistan; early days where incredibly few people speak English, and people still live very strong and <em>non-diluted</em> cultural norms. If you are lucky enough to travel to Uzbekistan and interact with the local people, you’ll be interacting with people that might have almost never seen people from a different part of the world, let aside spoken to them. And that’s an incredible way to experience a new culture - raw, pure and untouched - and that’s what it felt like for us, and what made it so fascinating to me.</p> <h2 id="disjoint-observations">Disjoint observations</h2> <h3 id="lost-and-found-in-translation">Lost (and found) in translation</h3> <p>The entire trip was a game of translation - cultural and linguistic - where Amir had to translate both the conversations we were having with locals and his family, as well as the background behind some of the things we’d observe and ask him about. Thankfully, not everything had to be translated - particularly to Ayush (Indian) and myself (Moroccan). Ayush, fluent in Hindi, and I, fluent in Arabic could understand multiple words of Tajik; even more importantly, we could understand and relate to many cultural norms that we observed within their society. Regarding the similarities between Tajik and Arabic, this is not very surprising given that Tajik is essentially a Persian dialect, and Persian and Arabic do share a lot of words, but I had not realized this before arriving there - so I took note and was amazed by the similarities between my language and a language I had never heard about before. Here is a list of these words, most often pronounced slightly differently, and funnily enough, written in Cyrillic…</p> <ul> <li>Amir: Means prince in both Arabic and Tajik. Interestingly, it also means rich in Hindi and Urdu.</li> <li>Maalem: Professor in both Tajik and Arabic. the root of the word can also be found in different contexts, similar to arabic “3ilm”</li> <li>Ostad: Professor in Arabic and Tajik</li> <li>Kitab: Book in Arabic, Tajik, Hindi and Urdu</li> <li>Rahmat: Thank you in Tajik, which relates to “ra7mat” in Arabic, signifying thankfulness and blessing.</li> <li>Mosibat: disaster in Tajik and Arabic</li> <li>Fil: Elephant in Tajik and Arabic</li> <li>Faqat: only in Tajik and Arabi</li> <li>Osmon: translates to “sky”, and very close to “Samaa” which is the arabic word for it. Interestingly, it means “atmosphere” or “surrounding” in Urdu.</li> <li>Istiqlol: independance</li> <li>Vaqt: time in Hindi, Arabic and Tajik</li> <li>Shoukour: greatfulness in Tajik, which is the same as “Shoukr” in Arabic</li> <li>Nassib: destiny in Tajik and Hindi, and arabic</li> <li>Khizmat: in Tajik, refers to the duty to work for your family, for your elders, or simply for a bigger cause. It is service without asking anything in return. We first hear this word during the wedding, were Dilshohd Aka’s cousins were on duty, essentially neither seating at the table eating, nor enjoy a regular evening. They had to take care of guests, make sure everything was going right and sort out anything that might have gone wrong. It’s interesting because Khizma in Arabic refers to work, but without this extended connotation. I can in Tajik - not simply “work”. Work in Arabic is “Khidma”.</li> <li>Lakin: “But” in arabic and Tajik.</li> </ul> <h3 id="relation-to-islam">Relation to Islam</h3> <p>This was perhaps the biggest surprise for me - as I come from a Muslim country and was raised Muslim myself.</p> <p>Uzbek people mostly identify as Muslim, but are rarely seriously practicing religion. They rarely pray, read or learn the scripture, or fast during Ramadan. I even heard that it was often more common for people to go to church rather than mosques. However, people now speak about Islam all the time, and have it tightly embedded in their traditions - and so despite it officially being a secular state. Prayers were told during wedding, and every single (male) person whom I told I was Moroccan to hugged me when they realized I too was Muslim. This is also visible in the architecture, as mosques are order of magnitudes better built, designed and cared for than virtually every other construction in the country.</p> <p>Their relation to Islam feels very different than the one we have in Arab countries. I for instance find incredibly curious that no one speaks a word of Arabic, yet they (some of them) can recite a few verses of the Quran (just the basics though). This is something I have trouble comprehending - believing in a book which language they use everyday without understanding. While they are not the only country in this case (e.g. Indonesia), it was my first time being exposed to this - and I found it rather intriguing.</p> <p>Another interesting point is how common it is to drink alcohol for Uzbek people - certainly, this must have remained from the Soviet influence, but it seems to be totally normalized and not hidden - which is completely different from Arab countries where Alcohol is taboo and hidden (not consumed in public).</p> <p>One must note however that Islam, although historically present since the early days of Islam, has seen a very important rise in the recent years, with many Uzbek people becoming increasingly radical and serious in their practice, especially in younger generations - which many Uzbek people do not particularly appreciate. Perhaps the best testimony of this is a story we heard from Amir’s aunt, <em>Khola</em> who is a primary school teacher in Samarkand. She shared with us that the school refused to accept little girls wearing the headscarf, and that they’d always demand the girls take them off. Often, the girls would not accept to take their headscarf away, and the school would put the names of the girls on a “watch list” <d-footnote>the exact phrasing for this got lost in translation</d-footnote>. This would be impossible to do in Morocco for example, where little girls wearing headscarf is totally normal and accepted. <em>Khola</em> certainly agreed with the measure from the school, and expressed clear reluctance to this new wave of “Islamization”, even criticizing some of her own family members who, as she says, become overly religious in the last few years. She said: “Uzbekistan doesn’t have a tradition of extreme Islam - it is not us - we are open minded and moderate in our practice.”.</p> <h3 id="men-and-women-dynamics">Men and Women dynamics</h3> <p>This also was fascinating to me, because it felt so different from what I am used to experience.</p> <p>I’ll always recall the great surprise I felt on our first evening in the new and modern (and gentrified) neighbourhood of “Silk Road Samarkand”, and seeing local women dressed in a very liberal way - with colourful dresses, long hair down, taking pictures of themselves, and a complete feeling of safety and confidence in their attitude. This is not necessarily the norm in most Arab countries - at least not so freely in public places.</p> <p>In contrast, in this exact same place of great freedom for women, I observed that practically no table had men and women seating together in it. Single families (husband + wife + kids) would seat together, but as soon as more than one couple was dining, men and women had separate tables, and did not talk to one another. The kids, of course, would always be seated with the women, while men did men things at their table.</p> <p>This was also very clear at the wedding, where amongst 20 tables, our table of foreigners was the only one where men and women were seating together - all other tables were either men only or women only. Naturally, when it came to dancing, men and women would never dance together either - two distinct groups formed and danced independently with one another. In fact, virtually the only Uzbek woman I made eye contact with at the wedding was the professional dancer they had hired who was the only person dancing with both men and women. Yes, I didn’t make eye contact with the bride either - but more on that later.</p> <p>In general, the social norms behind male/female dynamics are rather strict in Uzbekistan. There is little culture of dating - mostly a culture of finding and committing to a life partnership. <d-footnote>I later learned that this dating culture is becoming more popular in younger generations, especially in Tashkent. It's also more and more depicted in Uzbek cinema and TV shows, which somewhat impact the reality of people. </d-footnote>. The alternative for men is looking for women “to have fun with” - whom men openly say that they would never marry. Uzbek women are protected within their family before they find a husband, often not allowed to travel and engage in some activities to protect their reputation and keep them suited for a good marriage. Women get married young, and once they do, engage very little with other men in social settings - especially outside of their direct family.</p> <p>One thing that I also found fascinating was that it was perceived as very rude to ask too many questions about the wife of people we’d interact with, or see pictures of them. You would never see an Uzbek person with a picture of their wife as a background picture on their phone for instance. Of course (lol), you’re allowed to ask for a picture of the girl if the relationship is not serious, but as soon as marriage is on the table and the intentions are serious, don’t you dare asking for a picture of the wife, complimenting how she looks, or anything remotely similar to this.</p> <p>It overall was fascinating to me that women dress so freely, often do not wear headscarf, yet are perceived and treated in a strict and conservative way - more so than most Arab/Muslim countries. And men take these traditions incredibly seriously when it comes to their wives! These traditions are however never forced by law (such as in Saudi Arabia or Iran for instanca), but they are engrained in the social normals for everyone - and people willingly follow them.</p> <h3 id="social-classes-and-attitude-towards-money">Social classes, and attitude towards money</h3> <p>It’s usually rather straightforward for me to see through social dynamics and “classes” - I did not manage to in Uzbekistan.</p> <p>It felt like there wasn’t any strong social fracture between working, middle and high-earning classes - as if all of them peacefully lived together, in a not so different way. Being African (and having several Indian, European, North and South American friends), I know very well that countries, especially “developing countries”, often have notable high-earning classes that are clearly distinguished in their way of life from the rest of the population. I did not see anything resembling this in the two cities we have visited in Uzbekistan. Maybe I just didn’t see them? Maybe they are hidden? Maybe they all are in Tashkent? We actually were staying in one of the rich neighbourhoods of Samarkand, and it certainly didn’t feel as strongly disparate compared to other countries I know. Of course, some people have more money than others, but it never felt like it really mattered much.</p> <p>I discussed this with Amir, and he agreed that it also felt to him like people lived rather homogeneously together, and that people who had more money were not at all living in lavish and ostentatious ways. He suggested that there might be more of this going on in the capital Tashkent - but that ostentation and strong social fracture from wealth was not a significant thing in Uzbekistan.</p> <p>I also asked Amir a more specific question about marriage to try to get a queue of what was going on in terms of social expectations and ways people had of “climbing the social ladder”. Amir told us that socio economic status was not a major determining factor for marriage - women do not particularly seek wealth when choosing life partners. The ability of a man to provide decent life conditions is enough for him to be considered a suitable partner.</p> <p>Now I am not sure why I observed this, nor whether it is accurate. It might be very different in Tashkent, the capital, which is closer culturally to Russia, and where all big companies and government officials reside. But hearing from Amir that wealth did not matter so much for marriage was definitely not something I expected. And what comforts me in my position about “class homogeneity” is that I never felt like people were hungry for money.</p> <p><strong>Attitude towards money</strong></p> <p>Tips are not really a thing in Uzbekistan. In fact, many people will almost get offended if you try to leave a tip. We had to ask one of our waiters who had given us stellar service whether he’d be okay to accept a tip. Although he accepted, he was initially reluctant and slightly embarrassed about it. Strange in a country where the living wage is so low?</p> <p>The many touristy shops we went to - the kind of shops and sellers that usually take great pleasure in ripping off tourists - always gave us reasonable prices. Of course, they were to be negotiated, but we never managed to get them under 20% under the initial asking price. In Morocco, I know that they would, without shame, ask you for 3 times what the product is actually worth, and you’d negotiate for a long time with them, and that’d be completely normal. Uzbek shop-owners did not appreciate us negotiating for too long, and again, never accepted to go below ~20% of the original asking price (and we tried! Remember I am Moroccan and can negotiate…).</p> <p>Perhaps the most shocking of all to me were taxi drivers. We’d always take uber-like taxis (to avoid getting scammed) where the price was calculated on the app, and we’d have to pay in cash at the end of the ride. Often, we’d have rides that would cost us something like 21000 UZS (~2 USD). If we gave 20.000 + 5.000 in bills, since they often did not have the change, they would always rather give us back the 5.000 and be paid less than they should rather than keep the 5.000 and get paid more than they should. This was unheard of to me, taxi drivers preferring to be paid slightly less than slightly more!</p> <p>Both the “classes” dynamics and attitude towards money feel somewhat concordant. It feels like people live pious and decent lives, where what matters most is to be there for one’s family and children. Money is important of course, but it’s not the most important thing in life - values, respect and integrity are significantly above money.</p> <p>Globalization and liberalization have a very bad history with “values, respect, integrity and greed”. Will Uzbekistan get corrupted through external influences, increase of tourism and globalization? They probably will, but I hope they won’t - because this was certainly one thing that made Uzbek people so great and different from what I was used to experience.</p> <h3 id="hospitality">Hospitality</h3> <p>Indeed, respect, moderation and integrity are not the only goods traits of Uzbek people. They are also incredibly hospitable - and guests are above everything else. I could relate to a lot of this being from Morocco.</p> <p>If you need a story of hospitality, you should just read again the context of my visit in Uzbekistan: me and 7 other people were invited to a wedding of someone we had never heard of before in our lives! Our presence was not just one or two extra plates, we had entire tables to ourselves during the receptions!</p> <p>Dilshod Aka (the groom), and the entirety of Amir’s family were so kind with us during our entire stay and took us around Samarkand at multiple instances despite being busy with the wedding preparation. I even remember Dilshod Aka who <em>invited all of us</em> to lunch the day after his wedding…</p> <h3 id="children">Children</h3> <p>Children are most certainly sacred in Uzbekistan. They are brought everywhere with their family when the family goes out, and obviously are the central goal of Uzbek life. We have been asked on multiple instances whether we had children - with everyone wishing us as many children as possible, as quickly as possible - as if it was the most obvious of things that we would want to have children.</p> <p>On that regard, I was indeed struck by the large number of kids I saw and interacted with. These interactions were always amazing and striking to me in many ways. I cannot remember seeing a single kid crying during the entire trip - and all of them were (if not asleep) always smiling and playing. Most importantly, I did not see a single kind doom scrolling TikTok or Youtube or some silly Ipad Video game. I am not sure if it’s because Uzbek people cannot afford tablets for their kids or if it’s not in the culture to give electronics to your kids, but whatever it is, kids were playing with one another and always were respectful of adults. I’ll forever cherish an interaction with a 3-4 year old little girl in the train to Bukhara, who was playing with a little balloon (and whatever she could find on her way) by going back and forth through the wagon. I’d play some form of hide and seek with her (where I’d somehow hide in my seat), and she laughed during the entire 10-15 minutes we played together. She was loud when laughing, but not a single passenger in the train complained - everyone was fine with it and smiled through the interaction. The mother was around, and made sure that the kid was not doing anything silly and not being too bothersome for the passengers, but she mostly let her be - and indeed she was.</p> <p>I am not sure how they educate their kids there, but I have never seen such a high concentration of kids, as well educated and well behaved as the ones in Uzbekistan - and let me state this again - not a single kid on their iPad or their parents phone - even at the wedding ceremony!!!</p> <h3 id="food-dont-want-this-to-be-a-food-blog-so-ill-keep-it-short-lol-">Food <d-footnote>Don't want this to be a food blog so I'll keep it short lol </d-footnote></h3> <p>The food was simple, but incredibly tasty and tasteful. The main advantage that Uzbekistan has is the quality of its ingredients, the greatness of its herbs - mainly dill, which they put virtually everywhere, and of course, the low price of food production. They also eat a lot of meat - like at every dish. None of us was vegetarian thankfully, so we all enjoyed it :). The bread was also quite good and fresh. You’d see it sold in the market amongst fresh products rather than in bakeries, which was not something I had seen before.</p> <p>I’ll mainly remember how tasty the tomatoes, onions, cucumbers, beetroots, chickpeas and fruits were. Peaches, nectarines, watermelons, melons… All incredibly sweet and delicious!</p> <h2 id="wedding-day">Wedding day</h2> <p>I’ll try here to give an overview of how the wedding unfolded, and some interesting details about traditions and norms.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/uzbekistan/group-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/uzbekistan/group-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/uzbekistan/group-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/uzbekistan/group.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="chronological-tale-of-the-celebrations">Chronological tale of the celebrations</h3> <h4 id="pre-wedding-day---mens-event">Pre-Wedding Day - Men’s event</h4> <p>The first event we were invited to was a men only event, at <em>8 in the morning</em>. It’s a breakfast, which starts with a series of prayers before people start eating. No loud music, no particular animation nor dancing - just the men on the groom’s side having breakfast and chatting men stuff.</p> <p>I must say I was surprised by the amount of food that was served, on each of the ~8 tables that were ready for guests. I also was very surprised by the quantity of meat that was served, at <em>8 in the morning</em>. Another thing that surprised me was that two entire tables were completely empty with food readily set on them - I assume they had prepared a seat for every single person they had invited, not accounting for no-shows. I feel like that it’s not customary to account for no shows at these celebrations - it seems fine to have way more food than needed, which, I imagine, showcases generous hosting attitude and wealth?</p> <p>The breakfast ceremony was “closed” after one of the older and religious man present at the event gave a little speech with a little prayer. After he put the mic down, every single person stood up and left the room in the span 3 minutes. Waiters started cleaning up immediately after, turning lights down and packing chairs away. I was so surprised by this because we were still seating and eating, and just very confused by how abruptly everyone had left.</p> <p>And that was it - the party was literally closed. And we all went back home.</p> <h4 id="wedding-day-part-1-1100---picking-up-the-groom">Wedding Day Part 1, 11:00 - Picking up the groom</h4> <p>Wedding day started on Tuesday with all of the groom’s family arriving at the groom’s house around midday. Men and women separation started at that point - our female friends Aline and Zenne from that point joined the mother and (female) cousin of Amir, while we stayed with the men. We found Dilshod Aka in his bedroom, seating on his bed in a great suit and holding flowers in the middle of a photoshoot. This is one such traditions that really felt odd to me, but was interesting to see. There is some sacrality over that bedroom, as it is the “marital bedroom”, where the bride and the groom move into on wedding night. Indeed, it is most common in Uzbekistan for the bride to move in with the family of the groom, where (if they can afford it), the newly wed couple will have their own little part of the house. Houses are also built as such, with several different “subhouses” rather than one big house where all rooms are directly communicating.</p> <p>We waited for the groom to finish his photoshoot, and got out of the house where we found three (rental) luxury cars waiting to take the groom and the closest family to the lunch ceremony.</p> <h4 id="wedding-day-part-2-1300---lunch-with-the-brides-family-but-without-the-bride">Wedding Day Part 2, 13:00 - Lunch with the bride’s family, but without the bride</h4> <p>This is the first ceremony where the family of the groom and the bride meet. It is fully organized (and paid for) by the bride’s family. Traditionally, it is done at the house of the bride’s family, but since they live in a not-so-big apartment, it was not possible and they had to do it at a reception hall. Interestingly, while vritually the entire family of the bride is present at the lunch, <em>the bride is not present</em>. She was still at home, waiting to get picked up by the groom, and taken care of by her mother, grandmother and sister (closest women of the family).</p> <p>The lunch felt similar to the men’s breakfast I mentionned earlier, with opening prayers, not-so-eventful lunch and closing prayers that prompted everyone to leave the place. The closing was however a bit more joyful than at the men’s breakfast - there was music and we (the groom’s close family) danced to accompany him out and go pick up the bride!</p> <h4 id="wedding-day-part-3-1500---picking-up-the-bride">Wedding Day Part 3, 15:00 - Picking up the bride</h4> <p>This was one of the more special moments of the day. We arrived near the apartment of the bride, where a great little band was playing music (which didn’t stop playing until we left with the bride), and sloooowly, after extensive dancing, started going up the stairs to accompany Dilshod Aka to pick up his wife. While walking up the stairs, we sang different things essentially wishing “good life to the newly-weds”, and slowly entered the apartment of the bride, where we found her in a beautiful white wedding dress and with a veil over her head and face. The following 20 minutes were full of little traditional gestures and prayers which I would not be able to appropriately narate here, but long story short, the close family of the groom was here (men and women), as well as the close family of the bride. Interestingly, the father was not there, he had stayed downstairs - as if his daughter now had to be left to her husband.</p> <p>We then accompanied them downstairs and danced for them while they got in the car.</p> <h4 id="wedding-day-part-4-1700---games">Wedding Day Part 4, 17:00 - Games?</h4> <p>This part of the ceremony was perhaps the strangest one for me, but maybe the most fun. We all arrived in a little hall that looked like a restaurant where the close (young) friends and family of both the groom and the bride were sitting, awaiting some dessert and refreshment fruits. In front of us, were the couple, seating next to one another in their wedding outfit. A few minutes in, a man shows up, takes up a microphone and starts talking in Tajik. Amir explains to us that it’s game time, and that this man will animate the games in a tv-game-show fashion. The animator calls 6 close friends of the bride, and 6 close friends of the groom in the center of the little hall, and explains to them the rules of the game: one has to start counting by saying a number, and the person on the left continues the count, except if the reached number is a multiple of 3, in which case the person should say a compliment to the groom or the bride. person 1: 1, person 2: 2, person 3: compliment, person 4: 4 person 5: 5, person 6: compliment. Etc… The second game was similar - they called different friends and were asked to describe why their friend (either the bride or the groom) was a great catch for their newly found partners. I remember that one of the bride’s friend said something along the lines of “she’s a doctor, so she’ll be able to take care of him if he is sick”. The animator, always making fun of the things the friends said, made fun of that one too “Dilshod Aka looks like a strong man who won’t need taking care of!”. Everyone laughed - I assume it was funnier in Tajik…</p> <p>It was honestly so cute, and a fun way to get families/friends from both sides to interact with one another.</p> <h4 id="wedding-day-part-5-2000---dinner-party">Wedding Day Part 5, 20:00 - Dinner party</h4> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/uzbekistan/hall-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/uzbekistan/hall-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/uzbekistan/hall-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/uzbekistan/hall.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>The dinner party took place in a beautiful big hall, with about 20 tables set (with ~14 seats each). We had a lot of fun, ate really well, and danced a lot. As expected, men and women were seating at separate tables, albeit in the same hall. The groom and the bride were sitting at the back of the hall alone, in elevation and facing everyone <d-footnote>Imagine where Dumbeldore would be seating, facing all students in Hogwarts. It was the same seating arrangement. </d-footnote>. The music really was great, with a fantastic band playing Uzbek, Russian, and even Arab standard songs - perfect music for dancing. A few notable highlights was the cousin of Dilshod Aka (groom) putting her kids on stage to sing a song - what an amazing sight at a wedding… To see four ~5 year old kids singing a song for the wedding of their uncle! Really beautiful. Another cool highlight is that Dilshod Aka and his wife recorded a professional video of their love story, set in different settings, of the both of them holding hands and walking together through different things, laughing, chatting etc… They projected this on a giant screen at the wedding, as well as photos of the two of them…</p> <h4 id="wedding-day-part-6-0000---walking-back-the-groom-to-the-marital-house">Wedding Day Part 6, 00:00 - Walking back the groom to the marital house</h4> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/uzbekistan/heart-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/uzbekistan/heart-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/uzbekistan/heart-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/uzbekistan/heart.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>After leaving the hall around midnight, we took the cars in the direction of Dilshod Aka’s house - the same house we had started the day at - the new marital house. We parked the car about 500m away from it, got out of them, and started a special ceremony, where we lit a giant heart of fire, and sang out loud untill we reached his house. His wife was in the car the entire time, and following the ceremony, untill she reached the house and got out towards the marital house - accompanied by the groom’s family’s women. Dilshod Aka danced a bit more with us, until the music stopped and people started leaving. I believe Dilshod Aka has not entered the marital house and bedroom that night - his wife was left sleeping alone to rest and get used to her new house, without having to add the pressure of doing the marital “deed” after such a long and stressful day. That was left for the night after wedding night…</p> <h3 id="spotlight-1---the-speech">Spotlight 1 - The Speech</h3> <p>Yeah, we had to give a speech….</p> <p>From the beginning of the day, and particularly at the dinner party, people were very curious of our presence in the wedding - we all clearly looked foreign, and that intrigued people - in a good way. I assume it’s rather special and unusual to have foreigners coming to a wedding in Samarkand, and I felt it was seen as a positive thing.</p> <p>The animator of the evening came to us and asked us (in Tajik - so Amir had to translate) to give a speech. Just 2-3 of us to say a few words about what we thought about the wedding, saying thank you to the family etc.. And well, we did! I actually started, Ayush continued, Zenne went on, and finally, the animator took the microphone, looked at Kevin (who is chinese-american, and chinese looking) and said while handing him the microphone “China, speech?”. <d-footnote>Woke culture hasn't reached Uzbekistan, they have many preconceptions about other countries, and do not make a real effort in hiding them - I think they don't relate with the culture of finding cultural and country stereotypes "offensive". </d-footnote>. Each of us spoke for about 30 seconds to extend our congratulations to the couple and thankfulness to the family, and admiration for Uzbek hospitality. All of this in English, and we knew that most people wouldn’t understand 5 words of what we’d say. So many people were filming us and looking at us in a very curious way. It felt like we also were an attraction of the wedding and people were happy about our presence - which felt great :)</p> <h3 id="spotlight-2---the-cake">Spotlight 2 - The Cake</h3> <p>The cake cutting and eating tradition was perhaps the most touching part of the wedding for me. It is tradition that the groom cuts cake and feeds it directly into the mouth of the bride’s family, and that in turn, the bride also feeds the cake directly into the groom’s (female) family’s mouth. I thought this was really beautiful and touching.</p> <h3 id="spotlight-well-not-really-3---the-bride">Spotlight (well, not really) 3 - The Bride</h3> <p>None of the men from the groom’s side (including Amir, Dilshod Aka’s direct cousin) heard the voice or made eye contact with the bride during the entire ceremony, and that is characteristic of Uzbek tradition. During the wedding, the bride is rather preserved, and it is inappropriate for other men (except her close family e.g. brother, close cousins) to engage in any contact with her. For women, it was however fine, but they still had very little interaction with her, eventhough they took her all the way to her bedroom in the marital house (which we, men, did not do). I imagine that she was very shy and didn’t speak much during the wedding, and I also imagine that it’s seen as some form of purity and innocence to not be extravagent for a women on her wedding day. I recall always seeing her, during the entire day of celebration, with her hand on her heart, smiling, and looking down. This also applies to every picture she had to pose for during the ceremony….</p> <p>This felt very different than most weddings I have experienced in my life - where the bride is the center of attention and should interact and be celebrated by people around her. Here, it felt like the bride was indeed the center of attention - but in a different way: while pictures of her were projected onto a big screen for everyone to look at, we would unfortunately not be able to speak to her…</p> <h2 id="random-stories-and-fun-facts">Random stories and fun facts</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Alcohol</strong>: Uzbek people have a specific sign between each other to signify alcohol - they typically do it to ask if the person they are speaking to is interested in a drink. They basically flick their fingers onto the side of their neck twice, always with a cocky smile on their face - and that’s Uzbek (universal for them, as they did it to us assuming we’d know this too) sign for alcohol.</li> <li><strong>Slim cigarettes</strong>: Uzbek people smoke “Slims” cigarettes - these are the super thin ones that are widely seen as “women” cigarettes in all countries I’ve ever been to. I was so confused by this.</li> <li><strong>Toilet Paper</strong>: The toilet paper there has longer single-paper than usual - about 1.5 times the size of the single paper from rolls we are used to see. Not only that, but it also is rolled up until the end - it doesn’t have the cardboard tube in the middle!</li> </ul> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/uzbekistan/toilet-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/uzbekistan/toilet-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/uzbekistan/toilet-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/uzbekistan/toilet.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <ul> <li><strong>How to have children</strong>: Perhaps the most curious interaction I had… While at Registan seating next to my (female) friend Zenne, a 50ish year old man seating just next to us asked us where we were from, and immediately after we had answered, asked us if we had children. He had just assumed we were married since we were seating close together and alone. He told us that he was one of the only ones in his surroundings whom had married his wife out of love instead of traditional arranged marriage, and he was really proud to tell us that all his 3 children also married out of love. Amir was doing most of the translation at this point because he got a bit in depth into his stories and of course did not speak a word of English. We got back to the children topic, where he also told us about the children of his own children, and told me he was sure I’d have children eventually. He’d always be looking and talking to me about this, never Zenne - eventhough he assumed she was my partner. At some point, he asked me apart from the rest of the group (with Amir for translation) and told me about a specific prayer that I should do before doing the bedroom deed in order to be able to have children, and assured me that he was certain we would manage to have children if we do so. This probably was one of the most special interaction of my life. I am neither married nor dating Zenne, nor am I typically keen on biology lessons from strangers in a language I don’t understand, but his kindness, authenticity, and genuine good wishes and intentions were just extraordinary. I most likely will never cross path again with this man, but I pray for his wellness and prosperity, as well as that of his entire family</li> <li><strong>Hamid El Shaeri and Snoop Dog</strong>: While virtually no one could speak English nor had left the country, they certainly knew their way around music. Snoop Dog was blasting in one of Amir’s cousin’s car - a rather religious cousin of course - I hope he didn’t know what the lyrics were about… I curiously heard at several instances Hamid El Shaeri, and several other popular arab songs. I hadn’t expected that.</li> <li><strong>Kidneys</strong>: In Uzbekistan, India is for some reason known for Kindey transplants, which created an urban legend that “Indian people have 4 kidneys”. Ayush, wanting to be nice, invited one of Amir’s cousin to visit India, to which he responded… “I don’t need to go to India because I have the 2 kidneys I need - why would I go there if not for kidneys?”</li> <li><strong>Surnames</strong>: The first grandson of the family gets to create his own “lineage”, which one does by taking the first name of your grandfather as last name. Amir is the first grandson of his family, so he indeed has a different surname than his own father and brothers. His surname is <em>Hirojidinov</em>, because his grandfather’s first name was Hirojidin. His brothers have the same last name as his father - <em>Djuraev</em>.</li> <li><strong>Surat Yassine</strong>: In Registan, I visited the Madrasa of Ulug Beg (famous astronomer and leader in Samarkand, grandson of Timur) and found a massive copy of the Quran, written in stunning calligraphy. It was open on Surat’ Yassine. I got emotional…</li> <li><strong>Happiness</strong>: Adding “jon” at the end of names means means happiness and “full of life”. Amir’s full name is Amirjon. I liked to call myself Yassinejon during the trip.</li> <li><strong>Kelin</strong>: We always referred to Dilshod Aka’s bride as “Kelin”. I looked up the word Kelin online, and found the following definition - I thought I’d share it directly here: <em>Literal translation: “daughter-in-law”, kelin, or kelinchak, (Turkmen gelin) is a newlywed woman who moves with the family of her husband and lives there until she advances to a higher position in the informal family hierarchy or the parents-in-law decide otherwise. Kelins carry out all the household chores in the in-law’s family, such as housekeeping, childcare, buying groceries, cooking, cleaning, serving meals and tea, taking care of her husband and his family, while paying due respect to all family members and following an austere code of conduct and social rituals.</em> While this definition doesn’t paint a joyful picture of the bride’s life, it is concordant with the reality of Uzbek marriages. It however seems to be an accepted norm which women happily follow. But how would I know if women indeed happily follow these norms, since the only woman I actually discussed with was Amir’s aunt, who is from a different generation and clearly thought women’s position in Uzbek society was nothing to be concerned about. She did acknowledge it was different to many other places in the world (which she had indirectly heard of), but not something problematic in any way.</li> <li><strong>Older brother</strong>: “Aka” means older brother in Uzbekistan, and they use it at all times - for respect. Amir calls all of his older cousin by their first name and “aka” at the end. This is why I wrote “Dilshod Aka” (the groom), and not “Dilshod” which is his real name. One can also comnunicate with strangers like this - calling them “Aka”. Since you asked, they say “ouka” for “litte brother”.</li> <li><strong>Discussing Paganini in Uzbekistan</strong>: Amir’s cousin is a great musician who studied at the conservatoire in Samarkand, and played multiple instruments. He was classically trained, and told me about many of his favourite composers, including a specific “one string etude” that he had played on the violin by the infamous Paganini. I was completely shocked to have this conversation with him - the same person who had been blasting Snoop Dog full volume in his car, dancing (really well) like there was no tomorrow at the wedding, and professing the most inappropriate (but funny) jokes during the day. Shaxboz, I hope we get to play music together one day.</li> <li><strong>Kunte</strong>: The number one insult between boys is “Kunte” - meaning “faggot”. Unsurprisingly, Uzbekistan is deeply homophobic. Although Amir already brought two lesbian friends which, he said, was not a problem, he acknowledges it would have been very different if it were two gay men.</li> <li><strong>Dal Bukhara</strong>: While in Bukhara, we met a lovely solo-traveler from Singapore (originally Indian). While having drinks together, he told us that he had always dreamed of coming to Bukhara, because he grew up eating a famous “Dal Bukhara” - a lentil based Indian dish. “Surely the best Dal Bukhara is to be found somewhere in Bukhara?”. He found the only Indian restaurant of Bukhara and asked for Dal Bukhara, only to be told by the owner of the restaurant that they had never heard of this dish.</li> <li><strong>Throwing money on wedding day</strong>: At several instances during the day, people threw large amount of small bills (e.g. 1000 SOM, ~0.1 USD), and the kids of the family (or the kids of the neighberhood when we picked up the bride) would be around picking them up!</li> <li><strong>Language fluidity</strong>: A Turkish friend of ours spoke Turkish to someone who replied to her in Uzbek at a restaurant - and they understood each other. A taxi driver spoke a mix of Tajik, Russian and Uzbek to people who spoke to him in Azerbaidjani. There are just so many different languages in the region, yet people understand each other and manage to communicate!</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In June 2024, I had the chance to travel to Uzbekistan for 10 days, visit the cities of Samarkand and Bukhara, and most importantly, extensively interact with my friend Amir’s family Although living in Uzbekistan and fluent in Uzbek, they consider themselves (ethnically) Tajik, as it is their first language and their ethnicity of origin. As such, they clearly differentiate themselves from Uzbek peope. and attend the wedding of his cousin - Dilshod Aka. This trip was nothing short of extraordinary, and I try here to give an overview of why. I attempted in this blogpost to synthetize the most interesting stories and observations about my stay in Uzbekistan - a country with rich historical relevance, strong culture and traditions, and most importantly, a country still very preserved from the cultural dilution caused by globalization and mass tourism.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflection on Gitex Africa 2024</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/gitex/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection on Gitex Africa 2024"/><published>2024-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/gitex</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/gitex/"><![CDATA[<p>I was invited to give a talk at Gitex Africa covering some of the current state of AI research, and its relevance for the tech world. It was my first ever public talk in Morocco, and also my first one in Africa. There are several things I’ll take away with me from this experience. Here are some of them, in no particular order. Full talk is available <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b716x6PI3uo">on Youtube</a>.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Gitex-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Gitex-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Gitex-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Gitex.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="my-message-to-gitex-and-africa">My message to Gitex, and Africa</h2> <p>I had originally planned to title my talk “The Struggles of AI with Bias, Generalization and Safety, and the responsibility of Africa to make itself heard”. I was planning to give an overview of these important AI issues, why they are especially relevant for the African continent, and why people in the room I was speaking in, who are essentially building Africa, should care about these and act upon them.</p> <p>As I was making progress with the talk preparation, I was getting more and more frustrated with my title, and the message I was communicating. My title and presentation perpetuated a “West vs Africa” kind of narrative - “Us vs them”. I feel more and more uncomfortable with this narrative. <d-footnote>Well, my friend Anas made me feel even more uncomfortable about it, and I am eternally grateful to him for that. He's doing great work, you should check him out: https://www.ryad.io/</d-footnote></p> <p>Wherever we are, whoever we are, we should just talk about the science, about what works or doesn’t work, and what needs to be done - at a global scale. Good work is a universal concept, without borders, and without nationality. Of course, context and application change from community to community - but particularly when it comes to humanity altering technologies like AI, the discourse must simply be a human one.</p> <p>This is why I renamed my talk: “The Struggles of AI with Bias, Generalization and Safety, a global human challenge”.</p> <h2 id="how-morocco-and-africa-are-surfing-the-tech-wave">How Morocco and Africa are surfing the tech wave</h2> <p>It was incredibly inspiring for me to see tens of thousands of people, from all backgrounds, from many different countries, being excited about the things exhibited during this massive event. After my talk, many people students and recent graduates, passionate about the technology, came to ask me the good moves to do in the space, sharing their project ideas, and just wanting to connect over their love for the tech. This was humbling for me - a priviledge to be in a position where I felt like I - even slightly - inspired others to keep pushing and doing good.</p> <p>There is something happening in the continent, a strange cocktail of effervescence, money and almost-blank slate. Effervescence because of the youth, energy, and the land of opportunity that even the blind can see. Almost-blank slate because of the infancy of this phase. And money because it feels like there is more money ready to be invested than start-ups to invest the money into - and that’s a bit of a crazy thing.</p> <p>What is still critically missing in Africa are globalist and competent individuals - who can resist greed, and slowly take an idea to a functional project, and most importantly, who stop caring about the fact that they are building for Africa, and just focus on building for humans.</p> <h2 id="lack-of-humour-too-many-suits-and-the-african-ethos-of-professionalism">(lack of) Humour, (too many) Suits, and the African Ethos of Professionalism</h2> <p>A Ghanaian friend - let’s call him Kevin - told me during the conference that looking as young as he does was a challenge for his work in Africa: “<em>People see me and wonder ‘who the fuck is this kid?’ and that makes it harder for me to be taken seriously.</em>” Kevin is 37, and appears to be in his late twenties/early thirties - not an immature age by all standards I think? Why is it a bad thing to look young for business in Africa? Why does a 30 year feel like they are not taken seriously because of their young age?</p> <p>This somewhat aligns with the overly-dressed and overly-serious average person at the conference. Many of the speakers and panelists spoke in suits, and did not dear to crack a single joke during their interventions. Despite all the energy and passion on what they were talking about, people don’t allow themselves to do humour or show youthfulness - the African work-culture perceives it as unprofessional and child-like.</p> <p>My own father <d-footnote>my father studied in Boston in the 90s, and is, by all means, a *very* modern and open-to-the-world person, especially for a Moroccan man of his generation</d-footnote>, when discussing the choice I had made of speaking in a tee-shirt <d-footnote>I wish you had seen the face of my mother when I said I'd be wearing a tee shirt and sneakers</d-footnote> and of cracking jokes at every slide during my talk, told me that although he thought my message was very relevant and well put <d-footnote>this isn't to brag, but rather to prove my point</d-footnote>, I still “looked like the student in town”.</p> <p>Now I have two options here - either I abide to this ethos where only overly-serious, overly-dressed people are deemed professional, or continue “looking like the student in town” for most professionals in the continent - i.e. focusing on getting more competent, doing good work, and most importantly, having fun along the way.</p> <p>I’m sure you can guess what I’ll be going going with.</p> <h2 id="on-arrogance-and-bullshit-overload">On arrogance and bullshit overload</h2> <p>What annoyed me a lot about my father saying that I “looked like the student in town”, is that I was one of the few speakers that had a slight idea of what they were talking about.</p> <p>I can say without a doubt that the vast majority of speakers had never written a single line of code in their life. Let aside explaining what backpropagation - the backbone of the entirety of modern ML - consists of.</p> <p>While it is certain that knowing to code is not a pre-requisite to have an opinion or even a public voice on AI, it surely helps avoiding bullshit.</p> <p>Let me tell you one of my favourite story of the event:</p> <p>I was moderating a discussion with Lola and Jeremy, two kind souls who work on topics related to the financial sector in Nigeria and Ghana, and whose work involve thinking through digitalization and “AI-transition” of the financial sector. At the end of their discussion, we opened questions to the public, and this man takes the microphone proudly <d-footnote>"*fier comme un paon*" is the best way to describe it</d-footnote> stands up and asks: “what do you think about overlooked technologies in the financial and security sectors like <strong>Swarm AI</strong>, which will revolutionise the way we handle the coordination of financial regulation and operations”. Jeremy, having no idea what “Swarm AI” was, masterfully improvised an answer, while I kept looking at the guy who had asked the question in deep confusion and disbelief. <em>What the hell is Swarm AI in the financial sector??</em> I obviously know what Swarm intelligence is, and it’s vocation to be applied to Robotics for instance, but how did this dude invent such nonsense and dared to ask with that much confidence? I went to him (and his business partner) at the end of the talk to ask if they could explain what they were talking about <d-footnote>I did so rather poorly: "guys this is bullshit it doesn't exist". I should have went for a more neutral "oh can you explain more?". My bad - but my bullshit barometer was through the roof and I couldn't contain myself.</d-footnote>, to which they threw a few meaningless buzzwords together. I pushed a bit and tried to challenge them and understand what they were saying, so when they felt like I understood that they were just talking about some kind of distributed network protocols - devote of any AI - they told me “ah we’ll put you in touch with our CTO so they tell you more about how the technology works - but it’s real!”.</p> <p>If you are out there publicly pushing a “revolutionary technology”, at least make sure you can explain what it consists of to someone’s who’s in the field. This really was ridiculous.</p> <p>While this story is particularly bad, the whole event gave parole to a high number of such people who talk significantly more than they know, and surf the AI wave without knowing what it really entails. So yes, many of them would benefit from spending a few minutes trying to learn how to write a few lines of code. Please don’t get me wrong, there were loads of great engineers doing great work, as well as many people who were not tech-savvy, but at least had the humility of admitting when they didn’t know something, and didn’t try to bullshit people to their own advantage.</p> <p>Like in the US, the attitude of talking more than one actually does and knows is deeply embedded in the Moroccan professional ethos (I cannot generalize to the rest of the contient as I know too little about other countries’ cultures), and I really hate it more and more.</p> <p>Today, I hold a particular contempt for people who talk more than they know, and also take advantage of the work of other people to push their own agenda in the process. Indeed, many people at the event were “passionate” <d-footnote>greedy saviour syndrome</d-footnote> about bringing this powerful tech to the entirety of the continent. Imagine how many people who don’t know what they are doing will be making a living out of exploiting people who understand even less than them, and so with a technology that is very powerful and with its fair share of risks.</p> <p>Well - this feels familiar, doesn’t it? Careless, sloppy and greedy people exploiting lack of education and powerlessness around them? Looks like there is no escaping this, and so even in a continent whose resources and people have been continously exploited by simiarly careless, sloppy and greedy people in the past. Are we going to let that happen again, this time <em>by our own people to our own people?</em></p> <p>I should have called them out for their bullshit in front of everyone in the room. We shouldn’t tolerate bullshiting the public. We shouldn’t normalize ignorant people pushing their sloppy agendas, we shouldn’t normalize arrogant-bullshiters. There is serious danger with arrogant-bullshiters.</p> <h2 id="some-fun-side-stories-about-these-5-days-in-morocco">Some fun side stories about these 5 days in Morocco</h2> <h3 id="hairdresser">Hairdresser</h3> <p>I have been getting my haircuts at the same Salon for about 5 years now, and come pretty much every time I’m in Morocco (~ 3 times a year). My brother also goes to this salon, but to a different hairdresser than mine. I know some other people in my family also go to the same salon, but not the same hairdresser as mine either - but I didn’t know which one.</p> <p>This time, my usual hairdresser was not around, so I <em>randomly</em> went with another one who was free when I arrived, whom had never cut my hair, and whom I had never spoken to.</p> <p>He greets me, and directly asks me whether I’m the brother of “Ismail” (my brother). Yes I am. In the next 5 minutes, he asks me about 4 of my uncles, and 6 of my cousins, whom he all calls by name. He asks me about my father (also calls him by name), whom, as he said, is the only one in the brotherhood who doesn’t go to him. Yes, he knew my father’s name, eventhoug my father doesn’t even go to get his haircut there.</p> <p>My favourite part of the conversation was when he told me that my cousin H. was there a couple days ago and told him that “a new client was on the way for him!” (i.e. his wife is pregnant with a boy). And yeah, that’s how I learnt that my cousin was expecting a child - through my hairdresser.</p> <h3 id="taxi-driver">Taxi driver</h3> <p>Ten minutes into a Taxi ride in Marrakesh, the taxi driver stops somewhere and asks me whether he can use my phone to make a call <d-footnote>In Morocco its very common that people run out of their pay-as-you-go fares and ask other people for calls.</d-footnote>. I let him use my phone, which he really appreciated and thanked me for. After a noisy and rather heated call, he hangs up and tells me he has to go pick up the guy he just spoke to. The taxi driver drives another 3 minutes and stops in a residential neighbourhood, and asks me to wait a bit. Eventually, some guy arrives and greets him; they talk for a about 1 minute, and my taxi driver gives the keys of the taxi to the new guy. The guy enters the taxi, says hi to me, and at the same time, my original taxi driver opens my door, and says “ah you were kind and I’m also feeling kind so I’ll get you another taxi to get you home”. After 3 minutes of effort and me being really confused, my original taxi driver asks again whether the new guy can drop me off. Eventually, the other guy takes pity and accepts to drop me since I’m only 10 minutes away from where we were.</p> <p>While he did take me to the place, he had the audacity to complain about the price I had agreed upon with the previous driver. WTF.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was invited to give a talk at Gitex Africa covering some of the current state of AI research, and its relevance for the tech world. It was my first ever public talk in Morocco, and also my first one in Africa. There are several things I’ll take away with me from this experience. Here are some of them, in no particular order. Full talk is available on Youtube.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">3 Months into my PhD</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/3-months-into-my-phd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3 Months into my PhD"/><published>2024-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/3-months-into-my-phd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/3-months-into-my-phd/"><![CDATA[<p>I officially started my PhD 3 months ago, and while my current results make me feel like I only started yesterday, I have already gone through quite a bit, and learned a few things about what it means to do Science and to conduct a PhD. Below are a few disconnected thoughts based on my experience — I’m aware that these reflections won’t generalize to everyone. I n fact, it might not even generalize to my future self — but I decided to put them in writing anyway — a <em>Memorabilia</em> for my future self.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="choosing-yourresearch">Choosing Your Research</h2> <p>During a PhD, figuring out what problem to work on is more challenging and critical than solving the problem.</p> <h3 id="good-research">Good research?</h3> <p>In the business world, the <em>loss function</em> is generally <d-footnote>There is an increasing number of businesses who claim to primarily optimize for quality of the product, as opposed to the profit they generate. While this may sometimes be true, the quality of product is almost always adjacent to revenues. Assuming that businesses loss function is to maximize money subsequently still holds in such cases. </d-footnote> obvious— maximize revenue. In the research world, the loss function is much more convoluted — “produce good research”? What is “good research” to begin with? </p> <p>There is no absolute way to evaluate what good research is. Is it research that gets cited a lot? Is it research that remains influential decades after its publication? Is it research that gets published in top journals? Is it research that manages to solve very difficult problems? Is it research that manages to solve problems that many people care about? While all of these can somewhat be considered metrics of research quality, they often are not adjacent. Highly cited and top journal papers are not necessarily works that significantly influence a field. Solving very difficult problems is not necessarily something that <em>a lot of people will care</em> about, nor is it necessarily something that <em>people will care a lot</em> about.</p> <p>Since we cannot find an absolute for what good research is, I feel it’s best to assess it relative to the person conducting it: <strong>doing good research is doing the kind of research you look up to</strong>. For some, it’s a technical and precise exploration of niche intricacies, for others, it’s information integration and rethinking the direction of a field, for others, it might be real-world-oriented technical breakthroughs.</p> <p>Our role as researchers is to produce research that aligns with what we look up to. And, <em>not</em> research just for the sake of publishing. This applies to every creative activity I guess - one should seek to produce the kind of work that they can be proud of and that they think other peers might look up to as well.</p> <p>Now this is hard. Not only do you have to be incredibly performant and perseverant to achieve this <d-footnote> particularly in today's hypercompetitive world </d-footnote>, but you also have to navigate the thorny landmine of academic pressure to publish. Playing this conflictual game is certainly the greatest challenge of modern academic research - and I can feel it already.</p> <p>A concrete example that applies to me is to decide on whether to pursue publishing in NeurIPS style conferences, where incremental performance on benchmarks is the general pursuit, vs work that gets traditionally published in journals - slower, more tedious, and more risky too. Both are good in their own way - but one should consciously position themselves. <d-footnote> I'm saying this but I'm not even sure that's the case. Consciously positioning oneself in advance is great for self-help textbooks - but the reality is often more nuanced, and life happens and takes you in unexpected directions.</d-footnote></p> <p>Successfully navigating this conflict takes a lot of discipline. One key aspect of this discipline is learning how to fight the right battles: the ones we’ll enjoy fighting and actually have a chance at winning.</p> <h3 id="navigating-scientific-distractions">Navigating Scientific Distractions</h3> <p>Academia can be an incredibly diverse and exciting universe, where ideas in all shapes and colors flow from everywhere.</p> <p>Sometimes you’ll read a paper and think “huh, this could be cool to try”. Sometimes, your supervisor comes to you with their new idea, and you know it would be a good thing for your relationship if you tried it. Sometimes (my personal favourite) you have a conversation with a scientist from a different field in a bar and see some parallels between both of your research and think that this would make a sexy and unconventional collaboration.</p> <p>It is undeniably a privilege to evolve in environments where this is the norm, but it comes with a price: the burden of choice, and the challenge of focused attention.</p> <p>The more ideas are around you and the more people are around you, the more difficult it becomes to focus your attention and have a clear sense of direction — especially for the curious and playful spirits — which I’m lucky to be. But I remember the famous Steve Jobs quote from his Stanford commencement address: “you can’t connect the dots looking forward; you can only connect them looking backward” <d-footnote>A friend pointed to me that this might have been inspired by Kierkegaard's famous quote "Life can only be understood backwards; but it must be lived forwards."</d-footnote>— trying to build your own direction while doing research is, I think, rather unrealistic: the story will emerge by itself towards the end — provided you consistently do <em>due diligence</em>. The trick is indeed in the last part: doing one’s due diligence.</p> <h3 id="due-dilligence">Due Dilligence</h3> <p>What’s due diligence for a PhD student?</p> <p>It’s a <em>continuous</em> dance between 4 core activities:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Create:</strong> This is the core of your research, and the reason you were hired. This is the work you do in the lab: conducting your experiments and writing about them. This is where the entirety of your knowledge comes to life to create something that people around you (and hopefully yourself) may care about. And yes, I call this “create” because it is supposed to be creative work, not just mere execution of pre-existing methodologies without any novelty. Research is a creative activity.</li> <li><strong>Read</strong>: Papers, textbooks, taking classes… This is the space where you discover ideas and internalize them.</li> <li><strong>Interact</strong>: Your discussion with your supervisors, your time at conferences, your time as a T.A., your meetings with the students you supervise, or casual science chit-chat with your friends and colleagues. This is where you get feedback on your ideas (and results), as well as share your ideas with people who care for them: sharing is learning. This is also where you find other people to work with.</li> <li><strong>Think</strong>: Integrate all of the other three elements, iterate and adjust accordingly. Ask yourself the difficult questions: is this project actually going anywhere? Is this person worth working with? Is this work routine working or should I adjust? This is where you decide on a macro-level what to change in your way of practicing the previous three activities.</li> </ol> <p>All of them are equally important and mutually beneficial. One can think of this like a control problem — where optimal state (successful research and timely graduation) can only be reached if these four are well balanced during the span of your PhD.</p> <p>The last part is probably the most often overlooked. A PhD can feel like a tight corridor that ones tries to escape - especially towards the middle of it (I’ve been told). It’s important to feel like one has the capacity to change their way of doing and their direction - the <em>Sunk-Cost Fallacy</em> can be brutal in Academia…</p> <p>During my first three months, I made a different mistake — I did very little 1) and only did 2), 3) and 4). Bad too — obviously. But I blame the beginning for this mistake — the future will be different, especially since I now have a bit more momentum on different projects and can prototype quickly.</p> <h2 id="collaborations-and-supervision">Collaborations and Supervision</h2> <h3 id="collaboration">Collaboration</h3> <p>Choose wisely.</p> <p>Don’t do too much. Don’t do too much. Did I say you shouldn’t do too much?</p> <h3 id="supervising-students">Supervising Students</h3> <p>Supervising students, even if they are incredibly well chosen, is no substitute for doing science yourself. It is neither sufficient nor even satisfying to only give them a project and let them be. I already have three students under my wing and feel a bit overwhelmed by having to manage them — I simply do not have the time to have a detailed look at the details of their science.</p> <p>This directly results in the well-known shortcoming of most PIs in the world out there: losing touch with the daily bread of research. I am first hand realizing what this means — it’s a weird thing to just let go of the daily intricacies of experiments, and trust someone else to properly do the details themselves. You eventually lose control over things, and also lose some level of understanding about what is being done and how it is achieved. Of course, in my case, where my students use technologies and experiment ideas that I have played with quite a bit, the issue is less problematic than PIs not having done lab work/coding in years — but one still feels the dangers of it and the struggle of giving up control, and its consequence on one’s understanding of the parts.</p> <p>So why do people delegate? 1. Because they judge that their time is better spent doing different things, and 2. because they can achieve more in less time. Do I feel like my time is better spent thinking about research direction than doing research itself — I’m not sure. Do I feel like I can achieve more by having other students around me conducting research that I think should be done? I think so, but it hasn’t happened yet. This is where having good students come into play — when they get up to speed quickly and are actually capable of doing more and better than you could have done. This is rare. Most often, one typically spends weeks accompanying a student to set up an experiment that would take the supervisor a day to complete. However, I believe one must do the effort — if you get lucky once, the outcome surpasses the multiple failures.</p> <p>Now supervision has an additional layer compared to mere “delegation” — teaching. This is one part I value a lot. I feel a responsibility towards the students I supervise. I feel like I must, to the best of my abilities, show them the way, explain them things the best I could, and most importantly, inspire them to do good Science. This is a humbling experience, that takes human discipline, but also scientific rigor and knowledge. While I know that a lot of student project I’ll oversee won’t lead to ground-breaking research, I know I have the opportunity to positively influence one’s scientific career and attitude to work — and that is a privilege and responsibility I’m happy to carry.</p> <p>Oh, before I forget - Choose your students wisely. And don’t get too many. Really, don’t get too many. Did I say you shouldn’t get too many?</p> <h3 id="disjointed-supervision-thoughts-and-stories--i-couldnt-find-a-way-to-smoothly-connect-these-with-my-previous-paragraphs-so-i-just-put-them-here-without-transition-oops">Disjointed Supervision Thoughts and Stories <d-footnote> I couldn't find a way to smoothly connect these with my previous paragraphs, so I just put them here without transition. Oops</d-footnote></h3> <p>There are a number of interesting problems that one experiences while mentoring students. A couple of weeks ago, I realized that I had sent a student in the wrong direction (dead-end method). No big deal, “only” a few days of work were lost, but I should have done my homework better. In the moment I realized, I was torn between apologizing or slightly downplaying the time-loss into a “it’s fine, we learnt about X and Y in the process”. I picked a mix of both.</p> <p>It’s also a difficult to challenge to find the best way to motivate students. Should one be very demanding, or should one let them do their thing and only put as much as they are willing to put. After all, we do not pay students, and the cost of a badly performing students is “only” some time lost. I so far have chosen to let them be, and be as here as possible whenever they need me — let’s see if the results follow.</p> <h2 id="stimulation">Stimulation</h2> <p>To get through a PhD, you <em>need</em> to be in a stimulating lab, with stimulating people around you — that push you, towards whom you feel some kind of accountability. There is no way you get through this sane without it — no way.</p> <p>I feel it — some days I feel a push because of a good conversation, or because someone I look up to asks me a difficult question or expects some good work from me. I also have days where I don’t feel that at all — and these days, not only am I not motivated to get anything done, but my work also feels significantly less meaningful.</p> <h2 id="sleeping-in-on-a-random-tuesday">Sleeping in on a random Tuesday</h2> <p>Non-PhD/Academic friends often ask me (and other PhDs) how do PhDs navigate the freedom of working on what they want, and the freedom of not showing up to work on a random Tuesday. Truth is, it completely fucks us up. There is this impression that a single day of work doesn’t matter - and it’s completely true: a single day of work doesn’t matter in the greater scheme of your PhD <d-footnote>completing a PhD typically takes 3 to 6 years. How does a single day matter?</d-footnote>. And since the only person you’re accountable to in a PhD is yourself <d-footnote>Yes, PhD students are also accountable to their supervisors, but it's often not perceived as such in practice. Students do PhD for themselves, not to please their boss and stay on the payroll.</d-footnote>, it makes it incredibly difficult to motivate oneself to do what should be done, to keep showing up every day, read the things no one asked you to read, do the projects no one asked you to work on, and explore the ideas no one is pushing you to explore.</p> <p>This makes the PhD experience very close to “creative” kind of careers, rather than “corporate” ones. Does it matter if you don’t compose that song? Does it matter if you don’t write that essay? Of course not - no one will know that you haven’t done it, and no one will care nor ask for it. But that song that you didn’t compose, that essay that you didn’t write, <em>that side-project that you never got to try out, that paper that you never took off your reading list</em> - it could have been the start of your best work. It could have been the start of a work that actually is the 10x kind of achievement that we are after in life.</p> <p>And why did you not do it? Because you didn’t show up on that random Tuesday - thus not putting time on anything else than strictly urgent work.</p> <p>Doing a PhD requires a special kind of discipline and organization. - to get you to show up every day, and master the exploration vs exploitation tradeoff. Every student who doesn’t manage to do so ends up depressed, and I think that even students who kind of manage to do so also end up depressed. Caring about your work makes life more difficult I guess <d-footnote>I should probably eventually write about why I care about my work and choose to do things the way I do them. Feel free to ask me if you are interested haha. Maybe I can also speculate on why others care about their work.</d-footnote>.</p> <p>One can also think of this as a <em>delayed gratification</em> problem. The work you do today has very minimal influence on the outcome of the end of the day. You’ll probably keep getting paid even if not a single gram of good work comes out of your mind for 6 months during your PhD <d-footnote>Many people I know went through such phases.</d-footnote>. But you need to firmly believe in the power of <em>compounded growth</em> to keep showing up.</p> <blockquote> <p>“Most people overestimate what they can achieve in a year and underestimate what they can achieve in ten years.”</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="kindness-and-stupid-questions">Kindness and Stupid Questions</h2> <p>Context: Due to various circumstances, I happen to be involved in a project where I have been struggling to contribute. The work is most often far-away from my expertise and current scientific focus, and I unfortunately do not have the time to catchup enough to manage contributing as I’d like to.</p> <p>After one project meeting where I had been particularly useless (in the presence of a <em>top</em> ETH professor), one of the other PhD students present in the meeting messaged a few minutes after the call ended to tell me that I shouldn’t feel left out, and that I should keep showing up, despite not managing to contribute yet. He told me about one project which he also got fortuitously involved in, and where he had no expertise either. But in his words, “I was part of the discussion and asked the stupid questions that only people without experience would ask, and that ended up being an actually helpful contribution.” The project has now been written up (with him as co-author) and sent to NeurIPs - not bad for a project where you have no experience!</p> <p>I found his message incredibly inspiring because I never saw it through this light - instead of asking the <em>useful</em> stupid questions, we always feel self-conscious about not sounding stupid and choose to shut up. Things don’t have to be this way.</p> <p>Even more so, I found his message inspiring because he perceived the struggle and embarassment I was going through, and was kind enough to take the initiative of encouraging me - just because. I’m eternally thankful for that - I really needed it at that moment.</p> <p>I’ll try to keep these lessons with me: ask the stupid questions, and most importantly, show kindness to people who are struggling.</p> <h2 id="purpose">Purpose</h2> <p>There is no reasonable justification to pursue a PhD program, except to enjoy the daily bread of one’s research. You won’t make the world a better place by getting your PhD. You won’t save lives through your PhD research (if you think that’s the case, think again). Oh, and you won’t earn money by doing your PhD either. In the best-case scenario, you make your grandmother a bit more proud of you than she already was. So why are you here, if it’s not to enjoy the process?</p> <p>Am I enjoying the day-to-day so far? Yes. Is it a bit painful? Also yes, but in a good way, the kind of painful that makes you grow as a scientist and human being.</p> <h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking ahead</h2> <p>I truly feel blessed to be part of the Institute of Neuroinformatics, and that I chose to pursue this PhD instead of going to industry. I love science, and I love being surrounded by people who care about producing interesting work, and discuss ideas constantly. I love that ideas are discussed, rather than money or means to money.</p> <p>The road will, however, be bumpy. Looking ahead, I must do a better job at focusing my attention on the things that matter and getting things done - if not for the sake of my PhD, rather for the sake of my enjoyment of it. Well actually, aren’t both equivalent two sides to the same coin?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I officially started my PhD 3 months ago, and while my current results make me feel like I only started yesterday, I have already gone through quite a bit, and learned a few things about what it means to do Science and to conduct a PhD. Below are a few disconnected thoughts based on my experience — I’m aware that these reflections won’t generalize to everyone. I n fact, it might not even generalize to my future self — but I decided to put them in writing anyway — a Memorabilia for my future self.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sharing my experience of the ETH/UZH Neural Systems Computation Masters</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/NSC/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sharing my experience of the ETH/UZH Neural Systems Computation Masters"/><published>2024-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/NSC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/NSC/"><![CDATA[<p>I frequently receive messages on LinkedIn or Twitter to share my experience of the Neural Systems Computation (NSC) master’s program, so I decided to write a little blog post to share it with everyone. Disclaimer: I’m rather biased in my judgment — I am still at the Institute of Neuroinformatics (INI), but now as a PhD student.</p> <p>I won’t be getting into the details of the program in this blog post, as everything is already explained <a href="https://www.nsc.uzh.ch/en.html">here</a>. Rather, I’ll share some of my perspectives on things I liked and disliked in the program.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="nscs-home-institution---ini">NSC’s Home Institution - INI</h2> <p>The NSC program is run by the Institute of Neuroinformatics, which is located in the beautiful Irchel Park, home of the University of Zurich’s Science campus. The walk through Irchel Park that you’ll get to do every day to get to INI, through the changing seasons, is a privilege in itself — a “commute” unlike others.</p> <p>INI was established between the University of Zurich and ETH Zurich at the end of 1995. The mission of the Institute is to discover the key principles by which brains work and to implement these in artificial systems that interact intelligently with the real world: INI’s research focus, while varying greatly from one group leader to another, is still aligned with the initial mission.</p> <p>INI is a special place — a weird and unusual combination of warmth, kindness, chaos, and intellect. INI is unlike your typical scientific department office floor — it’s full of frames and pictures on the wall, celebrating scientists giants of the past, scientific ideas, and milestone moments of the institute. It is a very social institute, with several events organized, such as the colloquium talk followed by an apero every friday evening, the book club, or drinks for Masters and PhD students every Wednesday evening. Maybe you will be the driving force behind new social traditions at INI?</p> <h2 id="the-nsc-program">The NSC Program</h2> <p>The NSC program is a 90-credit program that students typically complete within 2 years, with some crazy students managing in as quickly as 1 year and other tranquille ones in 3 years. You must take the 45 credits worth of classes, and complete 45 credits worth of projects, and you’re good to go, and you do so at your own pace.</p> <p>The way you arrange your 45 credits worth of classes is largely free, although you do have some requirements such as the “Readings in Neuroinformatics” or “Basics of Instrumentation” classes. Students have access to realistically (as long as it’s somewhat related to the aims of the masters — and that’s not hard to justify) all of UZH and ETH science classes — that’s A LOT of options. In effect, no students have the same path in the program, and some students end up having their highest focus in fundamental mathematics or even chemistry. After all — all of these core sciences are fundamental to our understanding of the brain.</p> <p>Another great thing about NSC is that you are not in any way limited in the number of courses you take. The only (approximate) limitation is that you have three years to complete the program and graduate — leaving you ample time to do a lot of things.</p> <p>Through time, every student ends up diverging into a unique path of their own, sometimes very different from other students of the program, albeit always with a common denominator: the brain. This interdisciplinarity and multiplicity in perspectives are deeply embedded into INI’s history and mission: “discovering the key principles by which brains work and implement these in artificial systems that interact intelligently with the real world.”</p> <h2 id="nsc-projects">NSC Projects</h2> <p>Project work will be the most important part of your master’s (and cover the other 45 ECTS you should complete). You have a choice between doing 2 short projects and a short thesis, or directly a long thesis. In terms of duration, expect the following:</p> <ul> <li>Short project: 2–3 months long, usually working 2–3 days a week. 9 ECTS each</li> <li>Short thesis: 6 months long — deadline decided at the start of the project. Work as much as you can. 27 ECTS</li> <li>Long thesis: 9 months long — deadline decided at the start of the project. Work as much as you can. 45 ECTS</li> </ul> <p>There is a lot of diversity at INI when it comes to the projects you can pursue — just have a look at the different research happening in the various INI research groups to get a feel of this.</p> <p>INI makes it a bit annoying to do projects “externally” from INI. This makes sense as the program is obviously run to recruit researchers for INI, and that starts with short projects and thesis work. That being said, there are so many different outside collaborations from INI professors — they most often are happy to send you to a partner lab or company, and also allow you to go pursue things on your own.</p> <h2 id="tips-to-do-well-in-the-program">Tips to do well in the program</h2> <p>I recommend students devote their first year to taking courses, especially the harder ones. Your patience for studying for exams will go down as a function of time, and your eagerness to do research will grow. Explore and take as many classes as you can in the first two semesters, and dedicate the rest of your time to doing practically only project work.</p> <p>Doing two different semester projects can be a good idea if you are unsure what to dedicate your thesis to or who you’d best like to work with. You always have the option of extending a short project into a thesis if you are certain this is the right project for you.</p> <p>If you can, don’t rush into finishing, producing good science requires time, and openness to the world of ideas. Take the time to explore.</p> <h2 id="social-life">Social life</h2> <p>Another key component of doing well in this program is to take advantage of its community. NSC is a very small program, with about 5–10 students coming in every semester (out of ~250 applicants!) from all areas of the world. You should get to know everyone. You might not realize it, but that will help you become a better scientist. The NSC students are especially lucky since they have an entire room of the lab that is dedicated to them. The “Masters room” is an amazing place where you’ll get to work surrounded by other students of the program, and where you’ll make great friends. This is where all the fun and bonding happens, when suffering together through project work or exam revision. I have had some of the most amazing work days moments in that room, laughing hard and discussing fascinating things.</p> <p>Don’t limite your socializing to NSC students, PhD students, professors, staff are all extremely nice and welcoming, and most often physically present. People at INI are often insanely nice, and the vibe is super super cool. No one will go chase you and ask you to hang out, just be around INI, go to lunch with people, and do some effort to bring people together.</p> <h2 id="how-to-get-in">How to get in?</h2> <p>INI, although it’s unlike most masters programs I know of, is actually just like most masters programs I know of when it comes to applications. The committee seeks:</p> <ul> <li>Motivated students, who understand and truly value what they are applying for and show that this application is not only one amongst many.</li> <li>Talented students, with great track record of academic or industry experience and performance.</li> <li>Recommended students, who have worked with serious people who can testify of students’ ability to do work.</li> </ul> <p>Before you ask, I’ll answer some frequent questions:</p> <ul> <li>Some students with average grades got into the program, because they had great project work or an academic paper out. At the same time, some students got in while never having done serious science research project but just from outstanding academic record. Both grades and work/scientific experience matter, and are taken into account when applying — there is no fixed rule</li> <li>NSC purposely tries to recruit students from a wide variety of scientific backgrounds. The whole purpose of the program is to have variety of students to work around Neuroinformatics from a variety of different perspectives. I know NSC students who have majored in pharmacology, chemistry, biomedical engineering, and even a (pretty damn smart) one that graduated from a business school!</li> <li>INI is an academic institution that does academic research, so they obviously will naturally prefer academic references. HOWEVER — this does not mean that they would not appreciate and value the word of a previous non-academic employer that can testify of anything that is relevant to the work or culture at INI.</li> <li>Personal statements, just like everywhere else, should be about 1 page long and present 1) who you are 2) what your interests are 3) why you are a great candidate for <em>this program</em> and 4) what you would want to use your experience in this program for.</li> <li>If you feel like your application is not mature enough yet, I recommend taking time to work in research or in industry. Take a research project from your home institution, or email some professor (could be an INI professor/student!) to work on a project with them, and do good work. That will earn you a good reference and a nice extra paragraph on your personal statement.</li> <li>If you are serious about getting in, get to know the institute, read through the works of the professors/students who work at INI, understand the purpose and the values of INI. If you do this research and have conviction that you actually fit here, sending a good application will be effortless, and it’s likely to work. Oh and if it ever does not work, don’t hesitate to try again — that worked for me :)</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I frequently receive messages on LinkedIn or Twitter to share my experience of the Neural Systems Computation (NSC) master’s program, so I decided to write a little blog post to share it with everyone. Disclaimer: I’m rather biased in my judgment — I am still at the Institute of Neuroinformatics (INI), but now as a PhD student.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Strange Summer Cocktail- Tolstoy and Sufism</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/tolstoi-and-sufism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Strange Summer Cocktail- Tolstoy and Sufism"/><published>2023-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/tolstoi-and-sufism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/tolstoi-and-sufism/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>Someone asked him: “Distraught fellow, what is this love?” The man replied: “Love is selling all of your wordly goods to buy a drop of wine.”</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <p>Last month, I went on vacation with two radically different books in my suitcase: a collection of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Death-Ilyich-Stories-Wordsworth-Classics/dp/1840224533/ref=sr_1_3?crid=1UU8ZIK0HF173&amp;keywords=The+Death+of+Ivan+Ilyich+and+Other+Stories&amp;qid=1692882786&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=the+death+of+ivan+ilyich+and+other+stories%2Cstripbooks-intl-ship%2C253&amp;sr=1-3">short stories</a> by Leo Tolstoy, and the 12th-century Sufi poem <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35187179-the-conference-of-the-birds"><em>The Conference of the Birds</em></a>, by Attar of Nishapur. I guess I just thought I’d switch from one to the other whenever bored. Well, I never got bored, and ended up reading both at the same time; turns out they’re not so unrelated.</p> <p>Tolstoi and Attar delve deep into the topic of love and the whole rainbow of colors associated with the strangest and most powerful human emotion. They agree on one thing: love can be — and will be — devastating.</p> <h2 id="love-chez-tolstoy">Love chez Tolstoy</h2> <blockquote> <p>The truth is, that the whole affair [“falling in love”] has been exalted by poets and romancers to an undue importance, and that love in its various developments is not a fitting object to consume the best energies of men.</p> </blockquote> <p>Overall, it’s not pretty in Tolstoy’s world. Two of the short novels I read are particularly noteworthy in understanding his stance on love and “romantic” relationships. Here is a very condensed outline of the account of love they make.</p> <p>Family Happiness: Masha, a young orphan (~18 years old), and a family friend, Sergei (~35 years old), come to fall in love in the purest of ways. They talk for hours about everything and nothing, dream about the future, and care so deeply for one another — nothing in the world matters to their eyes more than one another. They marry, and Masha starts to feel bored of their country life, Sergei is considerate enough to suggest moving to Petersburg for a while and living a social lifestyle. Masha navigates this new life with great success and becomes adored by the whole Russian bourgeoisie, but her husband slowly grows exacerbated by all of this social nonsense. Distance builds up, and they build resentment towards one another and eventually completely disconnect. Masha feels extremely depressed, angry, and lost — and a good part of the novel is dedicated to describing how she navigates (or rather, fails to navigate) this resentment and frustration. The novel however ends on a positive note — they manage to love one another again, albeit not as lovers anymore, but as the mother/father of their child, and live “happily” ever after. Kreutzer’s Sonata: A man, “Pozdnyshev”, within a (60-page long) uninterrupted monologue to a stranger on the train, tells the story of how he murdered his wife. He had always dreamt of a happy and peaceful family life. He eventually fell in love and married a “gentle soul”, but quickly realized that they were not a good match (and argues there is no such thing as a good match — lovers always end up growing away from one another, however good the original match — c.f. Family Happiness). They grow apart and develop resentment and jealousy toward one another, which consumes their energy, morals, and souls. Pozdnyshev’s wife eventually fills the void of her marriage with music — she plays piano and invites a (male) violinist friend of hers to play duets. Pozdnyshev is jealous and suspects adultery. One day, he comes back home from traveling and finds them playing music together in the living room, and in a burst of anger, kills his wife. In Pozdnyshev’s words, there can only be two outcomes of marriage: suicide or murder of one’s partner. The character in this story chose the latter. While both these stories have rather different flavors and outcomes, I believe they both are clear on something: the love of two individuals for one another, no matter the circumstances, will always lead to great pain and destruction. The intensity and strength of the emotion constrain lovers to forgo reason and morals.</p> <p>Tolstoy’s views on the topic, particularly influenced by the failure of his own marriage, turned increasingly grim and hopeless towards the end of his life — hence the much darker Kreutzer’s Sonata, where the beautiful and pure love only lasts for a mere few days (and is narrated within a few sentences only), as opposed to the years of happiness (and half the novel in writing) dedicated to narrating Masha and Sergei’s happy marriage.</p> <hr/> <p>To further comment on Tolstoy’s view on love, we should also discuss the afterword of Kreutzer’s Sonata, written a few years after the publication of the novel, where the author explicitly clarifies his views on marital life and the “fantasy of falling in love”. He argues that the only solution to a sane and elevated life is chastity and celibacy. Tolstoy is, especially at the end of his life, strongly influenced by his faith and biblical understanding in his warning and reservations with regard to marital life. Kreutzer’s sonata comes with not one, but two epigraphs from the Gospel of Matthew:</p> <blockquote> <p>“But I tell you that anyone who looks at a woman lustfully has already committed adultery with her in his heart.” Matthew 5:28 “The disciples said to him, “If this is the situation between a husband and wife, it is better not to marry.” Jesus replied, “Not everyone can accept this word, but only those to whom it has been given””. Matthew 19:10–11</p> </blockquote> <p>It seems that Tolstoy sees no difference between lust and love and that no matter what, besides it unavoidably leading to despair, is actually also sinful. A noteworthy justification of this argument is the fact that neither Jesus nor the apostles ever married — and they exemplify The Right Way in Christianity. Tolstoy however acknowledges that “not everyone can accept this word”, and that is the curse of mankind — only a handful few are capable of abstaining from love (or lust?) to manage living elevated lives.</p> <p>It is interesting to remind oneself that in the two other Abrahamic religions, marriage is the most natural of things for human beings, including for people of significant importance — for example, the Prophet Mohamed married multiple times, and two of his wives (Khadija and Aicha) have been of notoriously positive influence in his life — a life committed to God.</p> <h2 id="interlude---what-is-sufism">Interlude - What is Sufism?</h2> <p>This article (from which much of this section is paraphrased) makes a great account of the Sufi tradition and practice.</p> <p>Sufism can be described as Islamic mysticism or asceticism, which through belief and practice helps Muslims attain nearness to the Almighty by way of direct personal experience of God. Belief in pursuing a path that leads to closeness with God, ultimately through encountering the divine in the hereafter, is a fundamental component of Islamic belief. However, in the Sufi tradition, this proximity can be realized in this life.</p> <p>There is a rich body of Sufi literature, with its most prominent representant being the well known poet Rumi, whose many poems on the theme of Love are widly read and quoted in today’s world. His influence on the Sufi world is very significant — and we should note that Rumi’s repeatedly aknowledge as his main master and influence our very own Attar:</p> <blockquote> <p>“Attar traveled through all the seven cities of love, While I am only at the bend of the first alley.”</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="love-chez-attar-and-in-the-sufi-practice">Love chez Attar and in the Sufi practice</h2> <p>The Conference of the Birds is a Sufi poem telling the story of a group of birds who seek spiritual meaning and elevation. They seek advice from the wisest bird they know — the Hoopoe — who advises them to embark on a spiritual journey to meet their Almighty. The journey is long and arduous, and many birds give up along the way. Those who stay eventually discover that the Almighty was there all along the Way — within themselves.</p> <p>On their way to find God, the birds must go through the notorious 7 Valleys of 1) Quest, 2) Love, 3) Understanding, 4) Independence and Detachment, 5) Unity, 6) Astonishment and Bewilderment, and 7) Deprivation and Death. Love is discussed all around the poem, but we can start looking into Attar’s account of Love by discussing the passage of the birds through the Valley of Love.</p> <blockquote> <p>Next comes the Valley of Love. Walk here and drown in fire, for in this valley only fire lives. If you are not a lover of fire, then leave, because a true lover is one with fire; a true lover ignities, burns and flares like fire. […] Here, a lover joyfully gathers and throws a hunder worlds into the fire. Here, right and wrong are mates, because in love two becomes one.</p> </blockquote> <p>Love occupies a central place in Sufism, it’s the most noble pursuit of mankind, but also the most dangerous and difficult one. The above quote clearly exemplifies this — love is fire, with its danger, high spirit, and beauty. It’s also clear that, just like in Tolstoy, true love forces us to forgo reason. However one must note an important nuance — the love mentioned in the previous quote is the love of the Beloved, the Almighty — God. The quest to find God’s love and give all love to God is the most important pursuit in life in Sufism and Attar’s text.</p> <p>What about the love of other things? “Earthly things”. Attar is quite clear on the topic: nothing compares to the love of God, and anything that is not the love of God is not worthy of one’s time, but also doomed to vanish with time. For example, one chapter is dedicated to the story of a bird whose love of gold made him hesitant to embark on the quest to find God, he had all the happiness he needed in the gold he already had. The sage Hoopoe bird answers “Gold is merely a metal with a nice hue — you’re seduced by its color like a child. If gold diverts you from your Beloved, then it is an idol; throw it aside and be on the ground.” No surprises there, of course a spiritual text will warn one against the love of gold and material things. But what about the love people around you?</p> <p>A long parable tells the story of a sage (Sheik) who falls in love with a young Christian woman, so much that he abandons his faith to convert to Christianity, accepts to bow before an idol (the worst sin in Islam), eats swine, and drunk wine, all to please and seduce the woman he fell in love with. His earthly love completely corrupted him out of his faith, forced him to cease all his spiritual duties and abandon all his followers. While the love was strong, sincere, and “pure”, the Sheikh not only lost reason but at no point found true fulfillment, satisfaction, and peace which he had when in love and devoted to the Almighty.</p> <blockquote> <p>“In love’s wilderness, slaughter the swine, burn the idol or else become like the luckless sheik, disgraced in love”</p> </blockquote> <p>In the end, in Attar’s world, any “earthly” love is idolatry, and while not necessarily considered sinful in Islam, is clearly regarded as perilous and leads to the loss of the self and of The Way. The purest and only love that must be given is love to the Almighty.</p> <h2 id="so-what-do-tolstoy-and-attar-agree-on">So what do Tolstoy and Attar agree on?</h2> <p>Earthly love is fire, and won’t bring any human to supreme peace and happiness. Reaching God is human’s best chance at finding everlasting peace. However, the perceptions of the paths to God are very different for Attar and Tolstoy, and this is what I find most interesting. Tolstoy is, especially at the end of his life, clear on the idea that chastity and celibacy (and essentially, renunciation of all other earthly pleasures) are the only way to reach a stable and trouble-free, elevated life. Attar and the philosophy of Sufism are much more forgiving, and narrate countless stories of kings and peasants who have fallen into the trap of earthly love (or other “egocentric” and “earthly” traps), but every time, forgiveness is possible as long as the true search continues and the soul remains pure and honest. The search for God remains the purest of quests, and the one most likely to find peace in. It is also a source of great struggle, but these struggles, as opposed to the love of earthly things, are not caused by the source of Love itself (e.g. God), but rather by the earthly distractions of it all which corrupt the soul along The Way.</p> <p>While the path to an elevated life is very obvious and clear for Tolstoy, the search rarely ever ends for Sufis — finding God is the quest of a lifetime, and this will, exactly like the love of earthly things, come with its fair deal of struggles.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Someone asked him: “Distraught fellow, what is this love?” The man replied: “Love is selling all of your wordly goods to buy a drop of wine.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with jupyter notebook</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/jupyter-notebook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with jupyter notebook"/><published>2023-07-04T12:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T12:57:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/jupyter-notebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/jupyter-notebook/"><![CDATA[<p>To include a jupyter notebook in a post, you can use the following code:</p> <div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>{::nomarkdown}
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">jupyter_path</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s1">'assets/jupyter/blog.ipynb'</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">relative_url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">capture</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">notebook_exists</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">file_exists</span><span class="w"> </span>assets/jupyter/blog.ipynb<span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endcapture</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">notebook_exists</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s1">'true'</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
  <span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">jupyter_notebook</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">jupyter_path</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">else</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
  &lt;p&gt;Sorry, the notebook you are looking for does not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
{:/nomarkdown}
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Let’s break it down: this is possible thanks to <a href="https://github.com/red-data-tools/jekyll-jupyter-notebook">Jekyll Jupyter Notebook plugin</a> that allows you to embed jupyter notebooks in your posts. It basically calls <a href="https://nbconvert.readthedocs.io/en/latest/usage.html#convert-html"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jupyter nbconvert --to html</code></a> to convert the notebook to an html page and then includes it in the post. Since <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/configuration/markdown/">Kramdown</a> is the default Markdown renderer for Jekyll, we need to surround the call to the plugin with the <a href="https://kramdown.gettalong.org/syntax.html#extensions">::nomarkdown</a> tag so that it stops processing this part with Kramdown and outputs the content as-is.</p> <p>The plugin takes as input the path to the notebook, but it assumes the file exists. If you want to check if the file exists before calling the plugin, you can use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">file_exists</code> filter. This avoids getting a 404 error from the plugin and ending up displaying the main page inside of it instead. If the file does not exist, you can output a message to the user. The code displayed above outputs the following:</p> <div class="jupyter-notebook" style="position: relative; width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;"> <div class="jupyter-notebook-iframe-container"> <iframe src="/assets/jupyter/blog.ipynb.html" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; border-style: none;" width="100%" height="100%" onload="this.parentElement.style.paddingBottom = (this.contentWindow.document.documentElement.scrollHeight + 10) + 'px'"></iframe> </div> </div> <p>Note that the jupyter notebook supports both light and dark themes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="jupyter"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a blog post with jupyter notebook]]></summary></entry></feed>