<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-07-05T00:06:07+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Yassine Taoudi-Benchekroun</title><subtitle>PhD Candidate at the Institute of Neuroinformatics, ETH Zurich.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How 8 Gringos Gave a Speech at an Uzbek Wedding Where No One Spoke English</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/uzbekistan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How 8 Gringos Gave a Speech at an Uzbek Wedding Where No One Spoke English"/><published>2024-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/uzbekistan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/uzbekistan/"><![CDATA[<p>** THIS IS A WORK IN PROGRESS. PLEASE FEEL FREE TO REPORT TYPOS AND INACCURACIES. **</p> <p>In June 2024, I had the chance to travel to Uzbekistan for 10 days, visit the cities of Samarkand and Bukhara, and most importantly, extensively interact with my friend Amir’s Uzbek family and attend the wedding of his cousin - <em>Dilshod Aka</em>. This trip was nothing short of extraordinary, and I try here to give an overview of why. I tried in this blogpost to synthetize the most interesting stories and observations about my stay in Uzbekistan - a country with rich historical relevance, strong culture and traditions, and most importantly, a country still very preserved from the cultural dilution caused by globalization and mass tourism.</p> <p>Before jumping in, I’d like to extend my sincerest gratitude to Amir for organizing this trip, opening us the door to his loving family and translating the many idiosyncrasies of the Uzbek society. I’d also like to thank Dilshod Aka for having us at his wedding, taking care of us throughout the entire trip and always entertaining us with jokes and good spirit - I wish him and his <em>Keline</em> all the best for the life they are starting together.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/trio_uzbek-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/trio_uzbek-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/trio_uzbek-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/trio_uzbek.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="prelude---an-ode-to-friendship-hospitality-and-internationalization">Prelude - an Ode to Friendship, Hospitality and Internationalization</h2> <p>The story of my presence in Uzbekistan can be traced back to 2007, when Amir (10 years old at the time) and his family unexpectedly won the green card lottery and left their traditional Uzbek life in Samarkand to move to the U.S.A. In another part of the world, Ayush (around the same age as Amir), born in India, relocates with his family to the U.S A due to his father’s work. Amir and Ayush attended the same high school in New Jersey. The great <strong>friendship</strong> that brought me to Uzbekistan started when Amir spotted the only foreign looking kid at school, and with the hope of showing off his Bollywood knowledge, approached Ayush with a shy “Hey, what’s up?”.</p> <p>Fast forward to 2023, where Ayush and I, both living in Zurich and studying at ETH, end up joining the same music band, and start hanging out - the beginning of another great <strong>friendship</strong>.</p> <p>Amir’s cousin, Dilshod Aka, has finally found <d-footnote> finding her was a long and tedious process </d-footnote> the one and set a date to get married in June, and Amir decided to pause his accountant life in New York City and attend the wedding. Eager to share the beauty of his country with his friends, he kindly asks whether a few extra seats can be left for his friends at the wedding. Dilshod Aka and his family, being the incredibly <strong>hospitable</strong> and loving people that they are, happily agree. Amir invites his closest friends, Jordan, Jake and Ayush. Funnily enough, Ayush (having already visited Uzbekistan with Amir) gives himself green card to invite his own Zurich Friends to the wedding - the more the merrier he says. And this is how I got invited to Dilshod Aka’s wedding, while having met Amir only once before, and never knowing the existence of the groom Dilshod Aka.</p> <p>In the end, we were a very <strong>international</strong> group of 8 foreigners (as the mexicans say, a group of 8 <em>gringos</em>) present at the wedding: two Americans, one Dutch, one German, one Moroccan (me), one Indian, one Chinese-American and one Swiss. And of course, we were with our Uzbek-American host Amir during the entire trip, who took us around and translated the many conversations we had with his family members and with different locals we met throughout our journey.</p> <p>Now that one has the context about my presence at this wedding, let’s dig into specific aspects of interest in the way of life for Uzbek people.</p> <h2 id="context-and-history">Context and history</h2> <p>Some of the stories and observations I will discuss are best understood with some historical context in mind. However, if you know the situation of the country, or if you don’t really care about history, feel free to ignore and move on to the next section.</p> <h3 id="between-persia-the-mongols-and-ussr">Between Persia, the Mongols and USSR</h3> <p>Uzbekistan, situated in Central Asia, has historically been at the crossroads of multiple significant and diverse cultural, political, and religious movements, mainly due to its position along the Silk Road. The Persians established a presence in the region, substantially establishing growth and prosperity through trade. This era saw the area become an important centre during the Islamic Golden Age, with prominent intellectuals hanging out in Bukhara or Samarkand, such as Ibn Sina or Omar El Khayyam.</p> <p>The Persian influence was ended by the Mongol invasion led by Genghis Khan. A few generations later, Timur, descendant of the Mongol elite, established Samarkand as the capital of the vast Timurid Empire. Other great leaders, from the same lineage, came after Timur, notably the astronomer Ulugh Bek, who carried on the heritage of Samarkand as a renowned center of scientific study.</p> <p>Later, Babur, a descendant of both Timur and Genghis Khan, shifted his focus eastward, conquering parts of India and founding the Mughal Empire. While Uzbekistan was not directly part of the Mughal Empire, it remained culturally connected to this powerful dynasty.</p> <p>From the 19th century onward, Uzbekistan, along with much of Central Asia, was gradually incorporated into the Russian Empire. Tashkent, the current capital, became the political center of Russian Turkestan. This Russian influence continued until the dissolution of the Soviet Union in 1991, after which Uzbekistan declared its independence.</p> <p>This simplified historical context exemplifies the wide range of cultural influences that have shaped Uzbekistan throughout its history. Persian culture dominated for several centuries. The Mongol invasion led to a golden age of knowledge and science. Islam was a constant presence, both through Persian influence and during Timurid empire reign. The Mughal Empire, founded by Babur (who was born in present-day Uzbekistan), extended its influence to India. Finally, Russian and Soviet rule left their mark on the country. All of these diverse influences remain perceptible within modern day Uzbekistan.</p> <h3 id="languages">Languages</h3> <p>The influence of all these cultures is directly sensed through the diversity of languages that are spoken in Uzbekistan, and the different influences these languages have.</p> <p>The current official state language is <em>Uzbek</em>, which is a Turkic language, and written primarily in Latin alphabet since 1993. Indeed, after the fall of the Soviet union, Uzbekistan wanted to get rid of as much Russian influence as possible - so they enforced Latin alphabet as opposed to Cyrillic to write Uzbek - which had been in place since the 1920s. Educational establishments today only teach the Latin notation, even though the Cyrillic notation is all over the place, especially amongst older generations. Fun story: a Tunisian/Turkish friend whom we met in Bukhara spoke an entire conversation in a restaurant with an Uzbek lady - my friend spoke Turkish while the waiter answered in Uzbek, and they understood each other.</p> <p><em>Tajik</em> is another widely spoken language in Uzbekistan, particularly in the cities of Bukhara and Samarkand (where we were) because of the population of ethnic Tajiks, dominant in these cities. The Tajik language is a variety of Persian, which I guess makes the vast number of similar words I spotted between Tajik and Arabic less surprising. Still - I did find a wide range of similar words, which I was fascinated by - more on this later. While Persian is written in Persian characters (very similar to Arabic alphabet), Tajik is almost exclusively written in Cyrillic. It is not taught in schools - and is left as a spoken language between Tajik people of the region.</p> <p><em>Russian</em> is a bit like the English of the region - the common denominator for all surrounding countries. This is the language people do business with, both within Uzbekistan and across the region. The current relations between Uzbekistan and the Russian language are obviously difficult - seen by some as a language they don’t want to have anything to do with anymore, and by others as a prominent language of Uzbek history, widely spoken and useful in the region. It is today not recognized as an official language, but some people are pushing for it to be recognized as such. I imagine mostly in the western parts of Uzbekistan where the Russian influence is still significantly more pronounced.</p> <h3 id="end-of-dictatorship-opening-up-to-the-world-and-tourism">End of dictatorship, opening up to the world and tourism</h3> <p>In 2016, Uzbekistan’s first (authoritarian) president Islam Karimov passed - and that was the beginning of a (positive?) set of changes in the country. The new president Mirziyoyev started a gradual liberalization process, opening up the political system (although it still is far from being a democracy per se). Regional relations were drastically improved, particularly Tajikistan and Kyrgyzstan. Media have significantly more freedom, and a subsequent freedom of what people consume over the internet - you can imagine the influence of the internet in this country. Foreign investments became more attractive, with privatization efforts from originally state-owned companies. Bref, a large set of measures of the sort that basically started putting Uzbekistan on the international map, as a safe, flourishing, open, and good country to deal with. That’s what brought me there - despite us being 300 km away from the Afghan border where things are much less joyful.</p> <p>What I’d like you to remember from this is that Uzbekistan has essentially opened up less than 10 years ago. This process of opening up takes a lot of time, but is typically accelerated with the increase of tourism and now available access to internet. We are still in the early days of Open-Uzbekistan; early days where incredibly few people speak English, and people still live very strong and <em>non-diluted</em> cultural norms. If you are lucky enough to travel to Uzbekistan and interact with the local people, you’ll be interacting with people that might have almost never seen non Uzbek people in their lives, let aside spoken to them. And that’s an incredible way to experience a new culture - raw, pure and untouched - and that’s what it felt like for us, and what made it so fascinating to me.</p> <h2 id="disjoint-observations">Disjoint observations</h2> <h3 id="lost-and-found-in-translation">Lost (and found) in translation</h3> <p>The entire trip was a game of translation - cultural and linguistic - where Amir had to translate both the conversations we were having with locals and his family, as well as the background behind some of the things we’d observe and ask him about. Thankfully, not everything had to be translated - particularly to Ayush (Indian) and myself (Moroccan). Ayush, fluent in Hindi, and I, fluent in Arabic could understand multiple words of Tajik; even more importantly, we could understand and relate to many cultural norms that we observed within their society. Regarding the similarities between Tajik and Arabic, this is not very surprising given that Tajik is essentially a Persian dialect, and Persian and Arabic do share a lot of words, but I had not realized this before arriving there - so I took note and was amazed by the similarities between my language and a language I had never heard about before. Here is a list of these words, most often pronounced slightly differently, and funnily enough, written in Cyrillic…</p> <ul> <li>Amir: Means prince in both Arabic and Tajik. Interestingly, it also means rich in Hindi and Urdu.</li> <li>Maalem: Professor in both Tajik and Arabic. the root of the word can also be found in different contexts, similar to arabic “3ilm”</li> <li>Ostad: Professor in Arabic and Tajik</li> <li>Kitab: Book in Arabic, Tajik, Hindi and Urdu</li> <li>Rahmat: Thank you in Tajik, which relates to “ra7mat” in Arabic, signifying thankfulness and blessing.</li> <li>Mosibat: disaster in Tajik and Arabic</li> <li>Fil: Elephant in Tajik and Arabic</li> <li>Fa9at: only in Tajik and Arabi</li> <li>Saman: translates to “sky”, and very close to “Samaa” which is the arabic word for it. Interestingly, it means “atmosphere” or “surrounding” in Urdu.</li> <li>Istiqlol: independance</li> <li>Oua9t: time in Hindi, Arabic and Tajik</li> <li>Nakhs: sleep in Tajik and Arabic</li> <li>Characha: road in Tajik, which reminded me of chari3 in Arabic - also meaning road.</li> <li>Choukour: greatfulness in Tajik, which is the same as “Shoukr” in Arabic</li> <li>Nassib: destiny in Tajik and Hindi, and arabic</li> <li>Khizmat: duty to work to your brothers in Tajik (not simply “work”). Work in Arabic is “Kidma”.</li> <li>Lakin: “But” in arabic and Tajik.</li> </ul> <h3 id="relation-to-islam">Relation to Islam</h3> <p>This was perhaps the biggest surprise for me - as I come from a Muslim country and was raised Muslim myself.</p> <p>Uzbek people are very religious, speak about it all the time, and have it tightly embedded in their traditions - and so despite it officially being a secular state. Prayers were told during wedding, and every single (male) person whom I told I was Moroccan to hugged me when they realized I too was Muslim. This is also visible in the architecture, as mosques are order of magnitudes better built, designed and cared for than virtually every other construction in the country.</p> <p>Yet their relation to Islam feels very different than the one we have in Arab countries. First and foremost, I find incredibly curious that no one spoke a word of Arabic, yet they can recite a few verses of the Quran (sometimes, but not often, a lot). This is something I have trouble comprehending - believing in a book which language they use everyday without understanding. While they are not the only country in this case (e.g. Indonesia), it was my first time being exposed to this - and I found it rather intriguing.</p> <p>Another interesting point is how common it is to drink alcohol for Uzbek people - certainly, this must have remained from the Soviet influence, but it seems to be totally normalized and not hidden - which is completely different from Arab countries where Alcohol is taboo and hidden (not consumed in public).</p> <p>One must note however that Islam, although historically present since the early days of Islam, has seen a very important rise in the recent years, with many Uzbek people becoming increasingly radical and serious in their practice, especially in younger generations - which many Uzbek people do not see from a good eye. Perhaps the best testimony of this is a story we heard from Amir’s aunt, <em>Khola</em> who is a primary school teacher in Samarkand. She shared with us that the school refused to accept little girls wearing the headscarf, and that they’d always demand the girls take them off. Often, the girls would not accept to take their headscarf away, and the school would put the names of the girls on a “to watch list” (FOOTNOTE: the exact phrasing for this got lost in translation). This would be impossible to do in Morocco for example, where little girls wearing headscarf is totally normal and accepted. <em>Khola</em> certainly agreed with the measure from the school, and expressed clear reluctance to this new wave of “Islamization”, even criticizing some of her own family members who, as she says, become overly religious in the last few years. She said: “Uzbekistan doesn’t have a tradition of extreme Islam - it is not us - we are open minded and moderate in our practice.”.</p> <h3 id="men-and-women-dynamics">Men and Women dynamics</h3> <p>This also was fascinating to me, because it felt so different from what I am used to experience.</p> <p>I’ll always recall the great surprise I felt on our first evening in the new and modern (and gentrified) neighbourhood of “Silk Road Samarkand”, and seeing local woman dressed in a very liberal way - with colourful dresses, long hair down, taking pictures of themselves, and a complete feeling of safety and confidence in their attitude. This is not the norm in most Arab countries - at least not so freely in public places.</p> <p>In contrast, in this exact same place of great freedom for women, I observed that practically no table had men and women seating together in it. Single families (husband + wife + kids) would seat together, but as soon as more than one couple was dining, men and women had separate tables, and did not talk to one another. The kids, of course, would always be seated with the women, while men did men thing and their table.</p> <p>This was also very clear at the wedding, where amongst 20 tables, our table of foreigners was the only one where men and women were seating together - everything else was either men only or female only. Naturally, when it came to dancing, men and women would never dance together - two distinct groups formed and danced independently with one another. In fact, the only woman I made eye contact with at the wedding was the professional dancer they had hired who was the only person dancing with both men and women. Yes, I didn’t make eye contact with the bride either - but more on that later.</p> <p>In general, the social norms behind male/female dynamics are extremely strict in Uzbekistan. There is no culture of dating - only a culture of finding a wife/husband. The alternative for men is looking for women “to have fun with” - whom men openly say that they would never marry. Uzbek women are protected within their family before they find a husband, often not allowed to travel and engage in some activities to protect their reputation and keep them suited for a good marriage. Women get married young, and once they do, engage very little with other men in social settings - especially outside of their direct family.</p> <p>One thing that I also found fascinating was that it was perceived as extremely rude to ask questions about the wife of people we’d interact with, or see pictures of them. You would never see an Uzbek person with a picture of their wife as a background picture on their phone for instance. Of course (lol), you’re allowed to ask for a picture of the girl if the relationship is not serious, but as soon as marriage is on the table and the intentions are serious, don’t you dare asking for a picture of the wife, complimenting how she looks, or anything remotely similar to this.</p> <p>It overall was fascinating to me that women dress so freely, often do not wear headscarf, yet are perceived and treated in such a strict and conservative way - more so than most Arab countries I know of. And men take these traditions incredibly seriously when it comes to their wife!</p> <h3 id="social-classes-and-attitude-towards-money">Social classes, and attitude towards money</h3> <p>It’s usually rather straightforward for me to see through social dynamics and “classes” - I did not manage to in Uzbekistan.</p> <p>It felt like there wasn’t any strong social fracture between working, middle and high-earning classes - as if all of them peacefully lived together, in a not so different way. Being African (and having several Indian, European, North and South American friends), I know very well that countries often have notable high-earning classes that are clearly distinguished in their way of life from the rest of the population. I did not see anything resembling this in the two cities we have visited in Uzbekistan. Maybe I just didn’t see them? Maybe they are hidden? Well, probably not - we actually were staying in one of the rich neighbourhoods of Samarkand, and it certainly didn’t feel as strongly disparate compared to other countries I know. Of course, some people have more money than others, but it never felt like it really mattered.</p> <p>I discussed this with Amir, and he agreed that it also felt to him like people lived rather homogeneously together, and that people who had more money were not at all living in lavish and ostentatious ways. He suggested that there might be more of this going on in the capital Tashkent - but that ostentation and strong social fracture from wealth was not a significant thing in Uzbekistan.</p> <p>I also asked Amir a more specific question about marriage to try to get a queue of what was going on in terms of social expectations and ways people had of “climbing the social ladder”. Amir told us that socio economic status was not a major determining factor for marriage - women do not particularly seek wealth when choosing life partners. The ability of a man to provide decent life conditions is enough for him to be considered a suitable partner.</p> <p>Now I am not sure why I observed this, nor whether it is accurate. It might be very different in Tashkent, the capital, which is closer culturally to Russia, and where all big companies and government officials reside. But hearing from Amir that wealth did not matter so much for marriage was definitely not something I expected to hear. And what comforts me in my position about “class homogeneity” is that I never felt like people were hungry for money.</p> <p><strong>Attitude towards money</strong></p> <p>Tips are not really a thing in Uzbekistan. In fact, many people will almost get offended if you try to leave a tip. We had to ask one of our waiters who had given us stellar service whether he’d be okay to accept a tip (which was only worth ~10% of the bill). Although he accepted, he was initially reluctant and slightly embarrassed about it. Strange in a country where the living wage is so low?</p> <p>The many touristy shops we went to - the kind of shops and sellers that usually take great pleasure in ripping off tourists - always gave us reasonable prices. Of course, they were to be negotiated, but we never managed to get them under 20% under the initial asking price. In Morocco, I know that they would, without shame, ask you for 3 times what the product is actually worth, and you’d negotiate for a long time with them, and that’d be completely normal. Uzbek shop-owners did not appreciate us negotiating for too long, and again, never accepted to go below ~20% of the original asking price (and we tried! Remember I am Moroccan and can negotiate…).</p> <p>Perhaps the most shocking of all to me were taxi drivers. We’d always take uber-like taxis (to avoid getting scammed) where the price was calculated on the app, and we’d have to pay in cash at the end of the ride. Often, we’d have rides that would cost us something like 21500 UZS (~2 USD). If we gave 20.000 + 10.000 in bills, since they often did not have the change, they would always rather give us back the 10.000 and be paid less than they should rather than give us back 5000 and get paid more than they should. This was unheard of to me, taxi drivers preferring to be paid slightly less than slightly more!</p> <p>Both the “classes” dynamics and attitude towards money feel somewhat concordant. It feels like people live pious and decent lives, where what matters most is to be there for one’s family and children. Money is important of course, but it’s not the most important thing in life - values, respect and integrity are significantly above money.</p> <p>Globalization and liberalization have a very bad history with “values, respect and integrity”. Will Uzbekistan get corrupted through external influences, increase of tourism and globalization? Maybe they will, but I hope they won’t - because this was certainly one thing that makes Uzbek people extraordinary - not the only one though.</p> <h3 id="hospitality">Hospitality</h3> <p>Indeed, respect, moderation and integrity are not the only goods traits of Uzbek people. They are also incredibly hospitable - and guests are above everything else.</p> <p>You should just read again the context of my visit in Uzbekistan: me and 7 other people were invited to a wedding of someone we had never heard of before in our lives! Dilshod Aka, and the entirety of Amir’s family were so kind with us during our entire stay and took us around Samarkand at multiple instances despite being busy with the wedding preparation. I even remember Dilshod Aka who <em>invited all of us</em> to lunch the day after his wedding. I don’t even know what to say.</p> <h3 id="wedding-day-and-the-bride">Wedding day, and the bride</h3> <p><strong>TO WRITE</strong></p> <h3 id="sex-and-taboo">Sex and taboo</h3> <p>Perhaps this is best exemplified by one Amir’s favourite thing to say about his family: “I always say that my parents had sex four times in their lives, one for me, two for my two younger brothers, and one for the one who never was born because of my mother’s miscarriage”.</p> <p>Sex here is a non-topic. Ayush actually told us loads of stories from his last visit to Uzbekistan, and many conversations with Amir’s cousins where they covered some sex stuff. They couldn’t believe that men would ever want to “go down” on women. This was something that was incredibly gross to them and profoundly not virile.</p> <p>We went to several pharmacies, I did not see a single box of condoms. And yes, we saw kids everywhere. I guess you can do the maths here.</p> <h3 id="children">Children</h3> <p>Children are most certainly sacred in Uzbekistan. They are brought everywhere with their family when the family goes out, and obviously are the central goal of Uzbek life. We have been asked on multiple instances whether we had children (and not necessarily whether we were married) - with everyone wishing us as many children as possible, as quickly as possible - as if it was the most obvious of things that we would want to have children.</p> <p>On that regard, I was indeed struck by the large number of kids I saw and interacted with. These interactions were always amazing and striking to me in many ways. I cannot remember seeing a single kid crying during the entire trip - and all of them were (if not asleep) always smiling and playing. Most importantly, I did not see a single kind doom scrolling TikTok or Youtube or some silly Ipad Video game. I am not sure if it’s because Uzbek people cannot afford tablets for their kids or if it’s not in the culture to give electronics to your kids, but whatever it is, kids were playing with one another and always were respectful of adults. I’ll probably forever remember an interaction with a 3-4 year old little girl in the train, who was playing with a little balloon (and whatever she could find on her way) by going back and forth through the wagon. I’d play some form of hide and seek with her (where I’d somehow hide in my seat), and she laughed during the entire 10-15 minutes we played together. She was loud when laughing, but not a single passenger in the train complained - everyone was fine with it and smiled through the interaction. The mother was around, and made sure that the kid was not doing anything silly and not being too bothersome for the passengers, but she mostly let her be - and indeed she was,</p> <p>I am not sure how they educate their kids there, but I have never seen such a high number of kids and so well educated and well behaved than in Uzbekistan - and let me state this again - not a single kid on their iPad or their parents phone - even at the wedding ceremony!!!</p> <h3 id="food">Food</h3> <p>The food was simple, but incredibly tasty and tasteful. The main advantage that Uzbekistan has is the quality of its ingredients, the greatness of its herbs - mainly dill, which they put virtually everywhere, and of course, the low price of food production. They also eat a lot of meat - like at every dish. None of us was vegetarian thankfully, so we all enjoyed it :). The bread was also quite good and fresh. You’d see it sold in the market amongst fresh products rather than in bakeries, which was not something I had seen before.</p> <p>I’ll mainly remember how tasty the tomatoes, onions, cucumbers, beetroots, chickpeas and fruits were. Yes, fruits… Peaches, nectarines, watermelons, melons… All incredibly sweet and delicious! I really did not expect the amount of desert land that Uzbekistan has!</p> <h2 id="random-stories-and-fun-facts">Random stories and fun facts</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Alcohol</strong>: Uzbek people have a specific sign between each other to signify alcohol - they typically do it to ask if the person they are speaking to is interested in a drink. They basically flick their fingers onto the side of their neck twice, always with a cocky smile on their face - and that’s Uzbek (universal for them, as they did it to us assuming we’d know this too) sign for alcohol.</li> <li><strong>Vogues</strong>: Uzbek people smoke “vogue” cigarettes - these are the super thin ones that are widely seen as “women” cigarettes in all countries I’ve ever been to. I was so confused by this.</li> <li><strong>Toilet Paper</strong>: The toilet paper there has longer single-paper than usual - about 1.5 times the size of the single paper from rolls we are used to see.</li> <li><strong>Arians</strong>: Uzbek people love speaking about being Arians, and the fact that no one would have bothered them during the second world war if Nazi Germany had reached their land.</li> <li><strong>How to have children</strong>: Perhaps the most curious interaction I had… While at Registan seating next to my (female) friend Zenne, a 50ish year old man seating just next to us asked us where we were from, and immediately after we had answered, asked us if we had children. He had just assumed we were married since we were seating close together and talking in a very comfortable way - the kind of way that only wed couples would speak like here in Uzbekistan. He told us that he was one of the only ones in his surroundings whom had married his wife out of love instead of simply arranged marriage, and he was really proud to tell us that all his 3 children also married out of love. Amir was doing most of the translation at this point because he got a bit in depth into his stories and of course did not speak a word of English. At some point, he asked me apart from the rest of the group (with Amir for translation) and told me about a specific prayer that I should do before doing the bedroom deed in order to be able to have children, and assured me that he was certain we would manage to have children if we do so. This probably was one of the most special interaction of my life. I am neither married nor dating Zenne, nor am I typically keen on biology lessons from strangers in a language I don’t understand, but his kindness, authenticity, and genuine good wishes and intentions were just extraordinary. I most likely will never cross path again with this man, but I pray for the his wellness and prosperity, as well as that of his entire family</li> <li><strong>Hamid El Shaeri and Snoop Dog</strong>: While virtually no one could speak English nor had left the country, they certainly knew their way around music. Snoop Dog was blasting in one of Amir’s cousin’s car - a rather religious cousin of course - I hope he didn’t know what the lyrics were about… I curiously heard at several instances Hamid El Shaeri, and several other popular arab songs. I hadn’t expected that.</li> <li><strong>Kidneys</strong>: Uzbek people have this urban legend that “Indian people have 4 kidneys, because if you ever need a kidney, you go get it in India”. This is what one of Amir’s cousins said to Ayush when Ayush invited him to visit India… “I don’t need to go to India because I have the 2 kidneys I need - why would I go there if not for Kidneys?”</li> <li><strong>Surnames</strong>: The first grandson of the family gets to create his own lineage, which one does by taking the first name of your grandfather as last name. Amir is the first grandson of his family, so he indeed has a different surname than his own father and brothers. His surname is <em>Hirojedenov</em>, because his grandfather’s first name was Hirojeden. His brothers have the same last name as his father - <em>Djuarev</em>.</li> <li><strong>Surat Yassine</strong>: In Registan, I visited the Madrasa of Ulug Beg (famous astronomer and leader in Samarkand, grandson of Timur) and found a massive copy of the Quran, written in stunning caligraphy. It was open on Surat’ Yassine. I got emotional…</li> <li><strong>Happiness</strong>: Adding “jon” at the end of names means happiness. Amir’s full name is Amirjon. I liked to call myself Yassinejon during the trip…</li> <li><strong>Older brother</strong>: “Aka” means older brother in Uzbekistan, and they use it at all times - for respect. Amir calls all of his older cousin by their first name and “aka” at the end. This is why I wrote “Dilshod Aka” (the groom), and not “Dilshod” which is his real name. One can also comnunicate with strangers like this - calling them “Aka”. Since you asked, they say “ouka” for “litte brother”.</li> <li><strong>Kunte</strong>: The number one insult between boys is “Kunte” - meaning “faggot”. Obviously, Uzbekistan is deeply homophobic. Although Amir already brought two lesbian friends which he says was fine - though he said it would have been very different if it were two gay men.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[** THIS IS A WORK IN PROGRESS. PLEASE FEEL FREE TO REPORT TYPOS AND INACCURACIES. **]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflection on Gitex Africa 2024</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/gitex/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection on Gitex Africa 2024"/><published>2024-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/gitex</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/gitex/"><![CDATA[<p>I was invited to give a talk at Gitex Africa covering some of the current state of AI research, and its relevance for the tech world. It was my first ever public talk in Morocco, and also my first one in Africa. There are several things I’ll take away with me from this experience. Here are some of them, in no particular order. Full talk is available <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b716x6PI3uo">on Youtube</a>.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Gitex-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Gitex-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Gitex-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Gitex.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="my-message-to-gitex-and-africa">My message to Gitex, and Africa</h2> <p>I had originally planned to title my talk “The Struggles of AI with Bias, Generalization and Safety, and the responsibility of Africa to make itself heard”. I was planning to give an overview of these important AI issues, why they are especially relevant for the African continent, and why people in the room I was speaking in, who are essentially building Africa, should care about these and act upon them.</p> <p>As I was making progress with the talk preparation, I was getting more and more frustrated with my title, and the message I was communicating. My title and presentation perpetuated a “West vs Africa” kind of narrative - “Us vs them”. I feel more and more uncomfortable with this narrative. <d-footnote>Well, my friend Anas made me feel even more uncomfortable about it, and I am eternally grateful to him for that. He's doing great work, you should check him out: https://www.ryad.io/</d-footnote></p> <p>Wherever we are, whoever we are, we should just talk about the science, about what works or doesn’t work, and what needs to be done - at a global scale. Good work is a universal concept, without borders, and without nationality. Of course, context and application change from community to community - but particularly when it comes to humanity altering technologies like AI, the discourse must simply be a human one.</p> <p>This is why I renamed my talk: “The Struggles of AI with Bias, Generalization and Safety, a global human challenge”.</p> <h2 id="how-morocco-and-africa-are-surfing-the-tech-wave">How Morocco and Africa are surfing the tech wave</h2> <p>It was incredibly inspiring for me to see tens of thousands of people, from all backgrounds, from many different countries, being excited about the things exhibited during this massive event. After my talk, many people students and recent graduates, passionate about the technology, came to ask me the good moves to do in the space, sharing their project ideas, and just wanting to connect over their love for the tech. This was humbling for me - a priviledge to be in a position where I felt like I - even slightly - inspired others to keep pushing and doing good.</p> <p>There is something happening in the continent, a strange cocktail of effervescence, money and almost-blank slate. Effervescence because of the youth, energy, and the land of opportunity that even the blind can see. Almost-blank slate because of the infancy of this phase. And money because it feels like there is more money ready to be invested than start-ups to invest the money into - and that’s a bit of a crazy thing.</p> <p>What is still critically missing in Africa are globalist and competent individuals - who can resist greed, and slowly take an idea to a functional project, and most importantly, who stop caring about the fact that they are building for Africa, and just focus on building for humans.</p> <h2 id="lack-of-humour-too-many-suits-and-the-african-ethos-of-professionalism">(lack of) Humour, (too many) Suits, and the African Ethos of Professionalism</h2> <p>A Ghanaian friend - let’s call him Kevin - told me during the conference that looking as young as he does was a challenge for his work in Africa: “<em>People see me and wonder ‘who the fuck is this kid?’ and that makes it harder for me to be taken seriously.</em>” Kevin is 37, and appears to be in his late twenties/early thirties - not an immature age by all standards I think? Why is it a bad thing to look young for business in Africa? Why does a 30 year feel like they are not taken seriously because of their young age?</p> <p>This somewhat aligns with the overly-dressed and overly-serious average person at the conference. Many of the speakers and panelists spoke in suits, and did not dear to crack a single joke during their interventions. Despite all the energy and passion on what they were talking about, people don’t allow themselves to do humour or show youthfulness - the African work-culture perceives it as unprofessional and child-like.</p> <p>My own father <d-footnote>my father studied in Boston in the 90s, and is, by all means, a *very* modern and open-to-the-world person, especially for a Moroccan man of his generation</d-footnote>, when discussing the choice I had made of speaking in a tee-shirt <d-footnote>I wish you had seen the face of my mother when I said I'd be wearing a tee shirt and sneakers</d-footnote> and of cracking jokes at every slide during my talk, told me that although he thought my message was very relevant and well put <d-footnote>this isn't to brag, but rather to prove my point</d-footnote>, I still “looked like the student in town”.</p> <p>Now I have two options here - either I abide to this ethos where only overly-serious, overly-dressed people are deemed professional, or continue “looking like the student in town” for most professionals in the continent - i.e. focusing on getting more competent, doing good work, and most importantly, having fun along the way.</p> <p>I’m sure you can guess what I’ll be going going with.</p> <h2 id="on-arrogance-and-bullshit-overload">On arrogance and bullshit overload</h2> <p>What annoyed me a lot about my father saying that I “looked like the student in town”, is that I was one of the few speakers that had a slight idea of what they were talking about.</p> <p>I can say without a doubt that the vast majority of speakers had never written a single line of code in their life. Let aside explaining what backpropagation - the backbone of the entirety of modern ML - consists of.</p> <p>While it is certain that knowing to code is not a pre-requisite to have an opinion or even a public voice on AI, it surely helps avoiding bullshit.</p> <p>Let me tell you one of my favourite story of the event:</p> <p>I was moderating a discussion with Lola and Jeremy, two kind souls who work on topics related to the financial sector in Nigeria and Ghana, and whose work involve thinking through digitalization and “AI-transition” of the financial sector. At the end of their discussion, we opened questions to the public, and this man takes the microphone proudly <d-footnote>"*fier comme un paon*" is the best way to describe it</d-footnote> stands up and asks: “what do you think about overlooked technologies in the financial and security sectors like <strong>Swarm AI</strong>, which will revolutionise the way we handle the coordination of financial regulation and operations”. Jeremy, having no idea what “Swarm AI” was, masterfully improvised an answer, while I kept looking at the guy who had asked the question in deep confusion and disbelief. <em>What the hell is Swarm AI in the financial sector??</em> I obviously know what Swarm intelligence is, and it’s vocation to be applied to Robotics for instance, but how did this dude invent such nonsense and dared to ask with that much confidence? I went to him (and his business partner) at the end of the talk to ask if they could explain what they were talking about <d-footnote>I did so rather poorly: "guys this is bullshit it doesn't exist". I should have went for a more neutral "oh can you explain more?". My bad - but my bullshit barometer was through the roof and I couldn't contain myself.</d-footnote>, to which they threw a few meaningless buzzwords together. I pushed a bit and tried to challenge them and understand what they were saying, so when they felt like I understood that they were just talking about some kind of distributed network protocols - devote of any AI - they told me “ah we’ll put you in touch with our CTO so they tell you more about how the technology works - but it’s real!”.</p> <p>If you are out there publicly pushing a “revolutionary technology”, at least make sure you can explain what it consists of to someone’s who’s in the field. This really was ridiculous.</p> <p>While this story is particularly bad, the whole event gave parole to a high number of such people who talk significantly more than they know, and surf the AI wave without knowing what it really entails. So yes, many of them would benefit from spending a few minutes trying to learn how to write a few lines of code. Please don’t get me wrong, there were loads of great engineers doing great work, as well as many people who were not tech-savvy, but at least had the humility of admitting when they didn’t know something, and didn’t try to bullshit people to their own advantage.</p> <p>Like in the US, the attitude of talking more than one actually does and knows is deeply embedded in the Moroccan professional ethos (I cannot generalize to the rest of the contient as I know too little about other countries’ cultures), and I really hate it more and more.</p> <p>Today, I hold a particular contempt for people who talk more than they know, and also take advantage of the work of other people to push their own agenda in the process. Indeed, many people at the event were “passionate” <d-footnote>greedy saviour syndrome</d-footnote> about bringing this powerful tech to the entirety of the continent. Imagine how many people who don’t know what they are doing will be making a living out of exploiting people who understand even less than them, and so with a technology that is very powerful and with its fair share of risks.</p> <p>Well - this feels familiar, doesn’t it? Careless, sloppy and greedy people exploiting lack of education and powerlessness around them? Looks like there is no escaping this, and so even in a continent whose resources and people have been continously exploited by simiarly careless, sloppy and greedy people in the past. Are we going to let that happen again, this time <em>by our own people to our own people?</em></p> <p>I should have called them out for their bullshit in front of everyone in the room. We shouldn’t tolerate bullshiting the public. We shouldn’t normalize ignorant people pushing their sloppy agendas, we shouldn’t normalize arrogant-bullshiters. There is serious danger with arrogant-bullshiters.</p> <h2 id="some-fun-side-stories-about-these-5-days-in-morocco">Some fun side stories about these 5 days in Morocco</h2> <h3 id="hairdresser">Hairdresser</h3> <p>I have been getting my haircuts at the same Salon for about 5 years now, and come pretty much every time I’m in Morocco (~ 3 times a year). My brother also goes to this salon, but to a different hairdresser than mine. I know some other people in my family also go to the same salon, but not the same hairdresser as mine either - but I didn’t know which one.</p> <p>This time, my usual hairdresser was not around, so I <em>randomly</em> went with another one who was free when I arrived, whom had never cut my hair, and whom I had never spoken to.</p> <p>He greets me, and directly asks me whether I’m the brother of “Ismail” (my brother). Yes I am. In the next 5 minutes, he asks me about 4 of my uncles, and 6 of my cousins, whom he all calls by name. He asks me about my father (also calls him by name), whom, as he said, is the only one in the brotherhood who doesn’t go to him. Yes, he knew my father’s name, eventhoug my father doesn’t even go to get his haircut there.</p> <p>My favourite part of the conversation was when he told me that my cousin H. was there a couple days ago and told him that “a new client was on the way for him!” (i.e. his wife is pregnant with a boy). And yeah, that’s how I learnt that my cousin was expecting a child - through my hairdresser.</p> <h3 id="taxi-driver">Taxi driver</h3> <p>Ten minutes into a Taxi ride in Marrakesh, the taxi driver stops somewhere and asks me whether he can use my phone to make a call <d-footnote>In Morocco its very common that people run out of their pay-as-you-go fares and ask other people for calls.</d-footnote>. I let him use my phone, which he really appreciated and thanked me for. After a noisy and rather heated call, he hangs up and tells me he has to go pick up the guy he just spoke to. The taxi driver drives another 3 minutes and stops in a residential neighbourhood, and asks me to wait a bit. Eventually, some guy arrives and greets him; they talk for a about 1 minute, and my taxi driver gives the keys of the taxi to the new guy. The guy enters the taxi, says hi to me, and at the same time, my original taxi driver opens my door, and says “ah you were kind and I’m also feeling kind so I’ll get you another taxi to get you home”. After 3 minutes of effort and me being really confused, my original taxi driver asks again whether the new guy can drop me off. Eventually, the other guy takes pity and accepts to drop me since I’m only 10 minutes away from where we were.</p> <p>While he did take me to the place, he had the audacity to complain about the price I had agreed upon with the previous driver. WTF.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was invited to give a talk at Gitex Africa covering some of the current state of AI research, and its relevance for the tech world. It was my first ever public talk in Morocco, and also my first one in Africa. There are several things I’ll take away with me from this experience. Here are some of them, in no particular order. Full talk is available on Youtube.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">3 Months into my PhD</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/3-months-into-my-phd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3 Months into my PhD"/><published>2024-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/3-months-into-my-phd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/3-months-into-my-phd/"><![CDATA[<p>I officially started my PhD 3 months ago, and while my current results make me feel like I only started yesterday, I have already gone through quite a bit, and learned a few things about what it means to do Science and to conduct a PhD. Below are a few disconnected thoughts based on my experience — I’m aware that these reflections won’t generalize to everyone. I n fact, it might not even generalize to my future self — but I decided to put them in writing anyway — a <em>Memorabilia</em> for my future self.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="choosing-yourresearch">Choosing Your Research</h2> <p>During a PhD, figuring out what problem to work on is more challenging and critical than solving the problem.</p> <h3 id="good-research">Good research?</h3> <p>In the business world, the <em>loss function</em> is generally <d-footnote>There is an increasing number of businesses who claim to primarily optimize for quality of the product, as opposed to the profit they generate. While this may sometimes be true, the quality of product is almost always adjacent to revenues. Assuming that businesses loss function is to maximize money subsequently still holds in such cases. </d-footnote> obvious— maximize revenue. In the research world, the loss function is much more convoluted — “produce good research”? What is “good research” to begin with? </p> <p>There is no absolute way to evaluate what good research is. Is it research that gets cited a lot? Is it research that remains influential decades after its publication? Is it research that gets published in top journals? Is it research that manages to solve very difficult problems? Is it research that manages to solve problems that many people care about? While all of these can somewhat be considered metrics of research quality, they often are not adjacent. Highly cited and top journal papers are not necessarily works that significantly influence a field. Solving very difficult problems is not necessarily something that <em>a lot of people will care</em> about, nor is it necessarily something that <em>people will care a lot</em> about.</p> <p>Since we cannot find an absolute for what good research is, I feel it’s best to assess it relative to the person conducting it: <strong>doing good research is doing the kind of research you look up to</strong>. For some, it’s a technical and precise exploration of niche intricacies, for others, it’s information integration and rethinking the direction of a field, for others, it might be real-world-oriented technical breakthroughs.</p> <p>Our role as researchers is to produce research that aligns with what we look up to. And, <em>not</em> research just for the sake of publishing. This applies to every creative activity I guess - one should seek to produce the kind of work that they can be proud of and that they think other peers might look up to as well.</p> <p>Now this is hard. Not only do you have to be incredibly performant and perseverant to achieve this <d-footnote> particularly in today's hypercompetitive world </d-footnote>, but you also have to navigate the thorny landmine of academic pressure to publish. Playing this conflictual game is certainly the greatest challenge of modern academic research - and I can feel it already.</p> <p>A concrete example that applies to me is to decide on whether to pursue publishing in NeurIPS style conferences, where incremental performance on benchmarks is the general pursuit, vs work that gets traditionally published in journals - slower, more tedious, and more risky too. Both are good in their own way - but one should consciously position themselves. <d-footnote> I'm saying this but I'm not even sure that's the case. Consciously positioning oneself in advance is great for self-help textbooks - but the reality is often more nuanced, and life happens and takes you in unexpected directions.</d-footnote></p> <p>Successfully navigating this conflict takes a lot of discipline. One key aspect of this discipline is learning how to fight the right battles: the ones we’ll enjoy fighting and actually have a chance at winning.</p> <h3 id="navigating-scientific-distractions">Navigating Scientific Distractions</h3> <p>Academia can be an incredibly diverse and exciting universe, where ideas in all shapes and colors flow from everywhere.</p> <p>Sometimes you’ll read a paper and think “huh, this could be cool to try”. Sometimes, your supervisor comes to you with their new idea, and you know it would be a good thing for your relationship if you tried it. Sometimes (my personal favourite) you have a conversation with a scientist from a different field in a bar and see some parallels between both of your research and think that this would make a sexy and unconventional collaboration.</p> <p>It is undeniably a privilege to evolve in environments where this is the norm, but it comes with a price: the burden of choice, and the challenge of focused attention.</p> <p>The more ideas are around you and the more people are around you, the more difficult it becomes to focus your attention and have a clear sense of direction — especially for the curious and playful spirits — which I’m lucky to be. But I remember the famous Steve Jobs quote from his Stanford commencement address: “you can’t connect the dots looking forward; you can only connect them looking backward” <d-footnote>A friend pointed to me that this might have been inspired by Kierkegaard's famous quote "Life can only be understood backwards; but it must be lived forwards."</d-footnote>— trying to build your own direction while doing research is, I think, rather unrealistic: the story will emerge by itself towards the end — provided you consistently do <em>due diligence</em>. The trick is indeed in the last part: doing one’s due diligence.</p> <h3 id="due-dilligence">Due Dilligence</h3> <p>What’s due diligence for a PhD student?</p> <p>It’s a <em>continuous</em> dance between 4 core activities:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Create:</strong> This is the core of your research, and the reason you were hired. This is the work you do in the lab: conducting your experiments and writing about them. This is where the entirety of your knowledge comes to life to create something that people around you (and hopefully yourself) may care about. And yes, I call this “create” because it is supposed to be creative work, not just mere execution of pre-existing methodologies without any novelty. Research is a creative activity.</li> <li><strong>Read</strong>: Papers, textbooks, taking classes… This is the space where you discover ideas and internalize them.</li> <li><strong>Interact</strong>: Your discussion with your supervisors, your time at conferences, your time as a T.A., your meetings with the students you supervise, or casual science chit-chat with your friends and colleagues. This is where you get feedback on your ideas (and results), as well as share your ideas with people who care for them: sharing is learning. This is also where you find other people to work with.</li> <li><strong>Think</strong>: Integrate all of the other three elements, iterate and adjust accordingly. Ask yourself the difficult questions: is this project actually going anywhere? Is this person worth working with? Is this work routine working or should I adjust? This is where you decide on a macro-level what to change in your way of practicing the previous three activities.</li> </ol> <p>All of them are equally important and mutually beneficial. One can think of this like a control problem — where optimal state (successful research and timely graduation) can only be reached if these four are well balanced during the span of your PhD.</p> <p>The last part is probably the most often overlooked. A PhD can feel like a tight corridor that ones tries to escape - especially towards the middle of it (I’ve been told). It’s important to feel like one has the capacity to change their way of doing and their direction - the <em>Sunk-Cost Fallacy</em> can be brutal in Academia…</p> <p>During my first three months, I made a different mistake — I did very little 1) and only did 2), 3) and 4). Bad too — obviously. But I blame the beginning for this mistake — the future will be different, especially since I now have a bit more momentum on different projects and can prototype quickly.</p> <h2 id="collaborations-and-supervision">Collaborations and Supervision</h2> <h3 id="collaboration">Collaboration</h3> <p>Choose wisely.</p> <p>Don’t do too much. Don’t do too much. Did I say you shouldn’t do too much?</p> <h3 id="supervising-students">Supervising Students</h3> <p>Supervising students, even if they are incredibly well chosen, is no substitute for doing science yourself. It is neither sufficient nor even satisfying to only give them a project and let them be. I already have three students under my wing and feel a bit overwhelmed by having to manage them — I simply do not have the time to have a detailed look at the details of their science.</p> <p>This directly results in the well-known shortcoming of most PIs in the world out there: losing touch with the daily bread of research. I am first hand realizing what this means — it’s a weird thing to just let go of the daily intricacies of experiments, and trust someone else to properly do the details themselves. You eventually lose control over things, and also lose some level of understanding about what is being done and how it is achieved. Of course, in my case, where my students use technologies and experiment ideas that I have played with quite a bit, the issue is less problematic than PIs not having done lab work/coding in years — but one still feels the dangers of it and the struggle of giving up control, and its consequence on one’s understanding of the parts.</p> <p>So why do people delegate? 1. Because they judge that their time is better spent doing different things, and 2. because they can achieve more in less time. Do I feel like my time is better spent thinking about research direction than doing research itself — I’m not sure. Do I feel like I can achieve more by having other students around me conducting research that I think should be done? I think so, but it hasn’t happened yet. This is where having good students come into play — when they get up to speed quickly and are actually capable of doing more and better than you could have done. This is rare. Most often, one typically spends weeks accompanying a student to set up an experiment that would take the supervisor a day to complete. However, I believe one must do the effort — if you get lucky once, the outcome surpasses the multiple failures.</p> <p>Now supervision has an additional layer compared to mere “delegation” — teaching. This is one part I value a lot. I feel a responsibility towards the students I supervise. I feel like I must, to the best of my abilities, show them the way, explain them things the best I could, and most importantly, inspire them to do good Science. This is a humbling experience, that takes human discipline, but also scientific rigor and knowledge. While I know that a lot of student project I’ll oversee won’t lead to ground-breaking research, I know I have the opportunity to positively influence one’s scientific career and attitude to work — and that is a privilege and responsibility I’m happy to carry.</p> <p>Oh, before I forget - Choose your students wisely. And don’t get too many. Really, don’t get too many. Did I say you shouldn’t get too many?</p> <h3 id="disjointed-supervision-thoughts-and-stories--i-couldnt-find-a-way-to-smoothly-connect-these-with-my-previous-paragraphs-so-i-just-put-them-here-without-transition-oops">Disjointed Supervision Thoughts and Stories <d-footnote> I couldn't find a way to smoothly connect these with my previous paragraphs, so I just put them here without transition. Oops</d-footnote></h3> <p>There are a number of interesting problems that one experiences while mentoring students. A couple of weeks ago, I realized that I had sent a student in the wrong direction (dead-end method). No big deal, “only” a few days of work were lost, but I should have done my homework better. In the moment I realized, I was torn between apologizing or slightly downplaying the time-loss into a “it’s fine, we learnt about X and Y in the process”. I picked a mix of both.</p> <p>It’s also a difficult to challenge to find the best way to motivate students. Should one be very demanding, or should one let them do their thing and only put as much as they are willing to put. After all, we do not pay students, and the cost of a badly performing students is “only” some time lost. I so far have chosen to let them be, and be as here as possible whenever they need me — let’s see if the results follow.</p> <h2 id="stimulation">Stimulation</h2> <p>To get through a PhD, you <em>need</em> to be in a stimulating lab, with stimulating people around you — that push you, towards whom you feel some kind of accountability. There is no way you get through this sane without it — no way.</p> <p>I feel it — some days I feel a push because of a good conversation, or because someone I look up to asks me a difficult question or expects some good work from me. I also have days where I don’t feel that at all — and these days, not only am I not motivated to get anything done, but my work also feels significantly less meaningful.</p> <h2 id="sleeping-in-on-a-random-tuesday">Sleeping in on a random Tuesday</h2> <p>Non-PhD/Academic friends often ask me (and other PhDs) how do PhDs navigate the freedom of working on what they want, and the freedom of not showing up to work on a random Tuesday. Truth is, it completely fucks us up. There is this impression that a single day of work doesn’t matter - and it’s completely true: a single day of work doesn’t matter in the greater scheme of your PhD <d-footnote>completing a PhD typically takes 3 to 6 years. How does a single day matter?</d-footnote>. And since the only person you’re accountable to in a PhD is yourself <d-footnote>Yes, PhD students are also accountable to their supervisors, but it's often not perceived as such in practice. Students do PhD for themselves, not to please their boss and stay on the payroll.</d-footnote>, it makes it incredibly difficult to motivate oneself to do what should be done, to keep showing up every day, read the things no one asked you to read, do the projects no one asked you to work on, and explore the ideas no one is pushing you to explore.</p> <p>This makes the PhD experience very close to “creative” kind of careers, rather than “corporate” ones. Does it matter if you don’t compose that song? Does it matter if you don’t write that essay? Of course not - no one will know that you haven’t done it, and no one will care nor ask for it. But that song that you didn’t compose, that essay that you didn’t write, <em>that side-project that you never got to try out, that paper that you never took off your reading list</em> - it could have been the start of your best work. It could have been the start of a work that actually is the 10x kind of achievement that we are after in life.</p> <p>And why did you not do it? Because you didn’t show up on that random Tuesday - thus not putting time on anything else than strictly urgent work.</p> <p>Doing a PhD requires a special kind of discipline and organization. - to get you to show up every day, and master the exploration vs exploitation tradeoff. Every student who doesn’t manage to do so ends up depressed, and I think that even students who kind of manage to do so also end up depressed. Caring about your work makes life more difficult I guess <d-footnote>I should probably eventually write about why I care about my work and choose to do things the way I do them. Feel free to ask me if you are interested haha. Maybe I can also speculate on why others care about their work.</d-footnote>.</p> <p>One can also think of this as a <em>delayed gratification</em> problem. The work you do today has very minimal influence on the outcome of the end of the day. You’ll probably keep getting paid even if not a single gram of good work comes out of your mind for 6 months during your PhD <d-footnote>Many people I know went through such phases.</d-footnote>. But you need to firmly believe in the power of <em>compounded growth</em> to keep showing up.</p> <blockquote> <p>“Most people overestimate what they can achieve in a year and underestimate what they can achieve in ten years.”</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="kindness-and-stupid-questions">Kindness and Stupid Questions</h2> <p>Context: Due to various circumstances, I happen to be involved in a project where I have been struggling to contribute. The work is most often far-away from my expertise and current scientific focus, and I unfortunately do not have the time to catchup enough to manage contributing as I’d like to.</p> <p>After one project meeting where I had been particularly useless (in the presence of a <em>top</em> ETH professor), one of the other PhD students present in the meeting messaged a few minutes after the call ended to tell me that I shouldn’t feel left out, and that I should keep showing up, despite not managing to contribute yet. He told me about one project which he also got fortuitously involved in, and where he had no expertise either. But in his words, “I was part of the discussion and asked the stupid questions that only people without experience would ask, and that ended up being an actually helpful contribution.” The project has now been written up (with him as co-author) and sent to NeurIPs - not bad for a project where you have no experience!</p> <p>I found his message incredibly inspiring because I never saw it through this light - instead of asking the <em>useful</em> stupid questions, we always feel self-conscious about not sounding stupid and choose to shut up. Things don’t have to be this way.</p> <p>Even more so, I found his message inspiring because he perceived the struggle and embarassment I was going through, and was kind enough to take the initiative of encouraging me - just because. I’m eternally thankful for that - I really needed it at that moment.</p> <p>I’ll try to keep these lessons with me: ask the stupid questions, and most importantly, show kindness to people who are struggling.</p> <h2 id="purpose">Purpose</h2> <p>There is no reasonable justification to pursue a PhD program, except to enjoy the daily bread of one’s research. You won’t make the world a better place by getting your PhD. You won’t save lives through your PhD research (if you think that’s the case, think again). Oh, and you won’t earn money by doing your PhD either. In the best-case scenario, you make your grandmother a bit more proud of you than she already was. So why are you here, if it’s not to enjoy the process?</p> <p>Am I enjoying the day-to-day so far? Yes. Is it a bit painful? Also yes, but in a good way, the kind of painful that makes you grow as a scientist and human being.</p> <h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking ahead</h2> <p>I truly feel blessed to be part of the Institute of Neuroinformatics, and that I chose to pursue this PhD instead of going to industry. I love science, and I love being surrounded by people who care about producing interesting work, and discuss ideas constantly. I love that ideas are discussed, rather than money or means to money.</p> <p>The road will, however, be bumpy. Looking ahead, I must do a better job at focusing my attention on the things that matter and getting things done - if not for the sake of my PhD, rather for the sake of my enjoyment of it. Well actually, aren’t both equivalent two sides to the same coin?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I officially started my PhD 3 months ago, and while my current results make me feel like I only started yesterday, I have already gone through quite a bit, and learned a few things about what it means to do Science and to conduct a PhD. Below are a few disconnected thoughts based on my experience — I’m aware that these reflections won’t generalize to everyone. I n fact, it might not even generalize to my future self — but I decided to put them in writing anyway — a Memorabilia for my future self.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sharing my experience of the ETH/UZH Neural Systems Computation Masters</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/NSC/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sharing my experience of the ETH/UZH Neural Systems Computation Masters"/><published>2024-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/NSC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/NSC/"><![CDATA[<p>I frequently receive messages on LinkedIn or Twitter to share my experience of the Neural Systems Computation (NSC) master’s program, so I decided to write a little blog post to share it with everyone. Disclaimer: I’m rather biased in my judgment — I am still at the Institute of Neuroinformatics (INI), but now as a PhD student.</p> <p>I won’t be getting into the details of the program in this blog post, as everything is already explained <a href="https://www.nsc.uzh.ch/en.html">here</a>. Rather, I’ll share some of my perspectives on things I liked and disliked in the program.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="nscs-home-institution---ini">NSC’s Home Institution - INI</h2> <p>The NSC program is run by the Institute of Neuroinformatics, which is located in the beautiful Irchel Park, home of the University of Zurich’s Science campus. The walk through Irchel Park that you’ll get to do every day to get to INI, through the changing seasons, is a privilege in itself — a “commute” unlike others.</p> <p>INI was established between the University of Zurich and ETH Zurich at the end of 1995. The mission of the Institute is to discover the key principles by which brains work and to implement these in artificial systems that interact intelligently with the real world: INI’s research focus, while varying greatly from one group leader to another, is still aligned with the initial mission.</p> <p>INI is a special place — a weird and unusual combination of warmth, kindness, chaos, and intellect. INI is unlike your typical scientific department office floor — it’s full of frames and pictures on the wall, celebrating scientists giants of the past, scientific ideas, and milestone moments of the institute. It is a very social institute, with several events organized, such as the colloquium talk followed by an apero every friday evening, the book club, or drinks for Masters and PhD students every Wednesday evening. Maybe you will be the driving force behind new social traditions at INI?</p> <h2 id="the-nsc-program">The NSC Program</h2> <p>The NSC program is a 90-credit program that students typically complete within 2 years, with some crazy students managing in as quickly as 1 year and other tranquille ones in 3 years. You must take the 45 credits worth of classes, and complete 45 credits worth of projects, and you’re good to go, and you do so at your own pace.</p> <p>The way you arrange your 45 credits worth of classes is largely free, although you do have some requirements such as the “Readings in Neuroinformatics” or “Basics of Instrumentation” classes. Students have access to realistically (as long as it’s somewhat related to the aims of the masters — and that’s not hard to justify) all of UZH and ETH science classes — that’s A LOT of options. In effect, no students have the same path in the program, and some students end up having their highest focus in fundamental mathematics or even chemistry. After all — all of these core sciences are fundamental to our understanding of the brain.</p> <p>Another great thing about NSC is that you are not in any way limited in the number of courses you take. The only (approximate) limitation is that you have three years to complete the program and graduate — leaving you ample time to do a lot of things.</p> <p>Through time, every student ends up diverging into a unique path of their own, sometimes very different from other students of the program, albeit always with a common denominator: the brain. This interdisciplinarity and multiplicity in perspectives are deeply embedded into INI’s history and mission: “discovering the key principles by which brains work and implement these in artificial systems that interact intelligently with the real world.”</p> <h2 id="nsc-projects">NSC Projects</h2> <p>Project work will be the most important part of your master’s (and cover the other 45 ECTS you should complete). You have a choice between doing 2 short projects and a short thesis, or directly a long thesis. In terms of duration, expect the following:</p> <ul> <li>Short project: 2–3 months long, usually working 2–3 days a week. 9 ECTS each</li> <li>Short thesis: 6 months long — deadline decided at the start of the project. Work as much as you can. 27 ECTS</li> <li>Long thesis: 9 months long — deadline decided at the start of the project. Work as much as you can. 45 ECTS</li> </ul> <p>There is a lot of diversity at INI when it comes to the projects you can pursue — just have a look at the different research happening in the various INI research groups to get a feel of this.</p> <p>INI makes it a bit annoying to do projects “externally” from INI. This makes sense as the program is obviously run to recruit researchers for INI, and that starts with short projects and thesis work. That being said, there are so many different outside collaborations from INI professors — they most often are happy to send you to a partner lab or company, and also allow you to go pursue things on your own.</p> <h2 id="tips-to-do-well-in-the-program">Tips to do well in the program</h2> <p>I recommend students devote their first year to taking courses, especially the harder ones. Your patience for studying for exams will go down as a function of time, and your eagerness to do research will grow. Explore and take as many classes as you can in the first two semesters, and dedicate the rest of your time to doing practically only project work.</p> <p>Doing two different semester projects can be a good idea if you are unsure what to dedicate your thesis to or who you’d best like to work with. You always have the option of extending a short project into a thesis if you are certain this is the right project for you.</p> <p>If you can, don’t rush into finishing, producing good science requires time, and openness to the world of ideas. Take the time to explore.</p> <h2 id="social-life">Social life</h2> <p>Another key component of doing well in this program is to take advantage of its community. NSC is a very small program, with about 5–10 students coming in every semester (out of ~250 applicants!) from all areas of the world. You should get to know everyone. You might not realize it, but that will help you become a better scientist. The NSC students are especially lucky since they have an entire room of the lab that is dedicated to them. The “Masters room” is an amazing place where you’ll get to work surrounded by other students of the program, and where you’ll make great friends. This is where all the fun and bonding happens, when suffering together through project work or exam revision. I have had some of the most amazing work days moments in that room, laughing hard and discussing fascinating things.</p> <p>Don’t limite your socializing to NSC students, PhD students, professors, staff are all extremely nice and welcoming, and most often physically present. People at INI are often insanely nice, and the vibe is super super cool. No one will go chase you and ask you to hang out, just be around INI, go to lunch with people, and do some effort to bring people together.</p> <h2 id="how-to-get-in">How to get in?</h2> <p>INI, although it’s unlike most masters programs I know of, is actually just like most masters programs I know of when it comes to applications. The committee seeks:</p> <ul> <li>Motivated students, who understand and truly value what they are applying for and show that this application is not only one amongst many.</li> <li>Talented students, with great track record of academic or industry experience and performance.</li> <li>Recommended students, who have worked with serious people who can testify of students’ ability to do work.</li> </ul> <p>Before you ask, I’ll answer some frequent questions:</p> <ul> <li>Some students with average grades got into the program, because they had great project work or an academic paper out. At the same time, some students got in while never having done serious science research project but just from outstanding academic record. Both grades and work/scientific experience matter, and are taken into account when applying — there is no fixed rule</li> <li>NSC purposely tries to recruit students from a wide variety of scientific backgrounds. The whole purpose of the program is to have variety of students to work around Neuroinformatics from a variety of different perspectives. I know NSC students who have majored in pharmacology, chemistry, biomedical engineering, and even a (pretty damn smart) one that graduated from a business school!</li> <li>INI is an academic institution that does academic research, so they obviously will naturally prefer academic references. HOWEVER — this does not mean that they would not appreciate and value the word of a previous non-academic employer that can testify of anything that is relevant to the work or culture at INI.</li> <li>Personal statements, just like everywhere else, should be about 1 page long and present 1) who you are 2) what your interests are 3) why you are a great candidate for <em>this program</em> and 4) what you would want to use your experience in this program for.</li> <li>If you feel like your application is not mature enough yet, I recommend taking time to work in research or in industry. Take a research project from your home institution, or email some professor (could be an INI professor/student!) to work on a project with them, and do good work. That will earn you a good reference and a nice extra paragraph on your personal statement.</li> <li>If you are serious about getting in, get to know the institute, read through the works of the professors/students who work at INI, understand the purpose and the values of INI. If you do this research and have conviction that you actually fit here, sending a good application will be effortless, and it’s likely to work. Oh and if it ever does not work, don’t hesitate to try again — that worked for me :)</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I frequently receive messages on LinkedIn or Twitter to share my experience of the Neural Systems Computation (NSC) master’s program, so I decided to write a little blog post to share it with everyone. Disclaimer: I’m rather biased in my judgment — I am still at the Institute of Neuroinformatics (INI), but now as a PhD student.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Strange Summer Cocktail- Tolstoy and Sufism</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/tolstoi-and-sufism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Strange Summer Cocktail- Tolstoy and Sufism"/><published>2023-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/tolstoi-and-sufism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/tolstoi-and-sufism/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>Someone asked him: “Distraught fellow, what is this love?” The man replied: “Love is selling all of your wordly goods to buy a drop of wine.”</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <p>Last month, I went on vacation with two radically different books in my suitcase: a collection of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Death-Ilyich-Stories-Wordsworth-Classics/dp/1840224533/ref=sr_1_3?crid=1UU8ZIK0HF173&amp;keywords=The+Death+of+Ivan+Ilyich+and+Other+Stories&amp;qid=1692882786&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=the+death+of+ivan+ilyich+and+other+stories%2Cstripbooks-intl-ship%2C253&amp;sr=1-3">short stories</a> by Leo Tolstoy, and the 12th-century Sufi poem <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35187179-the-conference-of-the-birds"><em>The Conference of the Birds</em></a>, by Attar of Nishapur. I guess I just thought I’d switch from one to the other whenever bored. Well, I never got bored, and ended up reading both at the same time; turns out they’re not so unrelated.</p> <p>Tolstoi and Attar delve deep into the topic of love and the whole rainbow of colors associated with the strangest and most powerful human emotion. They agree on one thing: love can be — and will be — devastating.</p> <h2 id="love-chez-tolstoy">Love chez Tolstoy</h2> <blockquote> <p>The truth is, that the whole affair [“falling in love”] has been exalted by poets and romancers to an undue importance, and that love in its various developments is not a fitting object to consume the best energies of men.</p> </blockquote> <p>Overall, it’s not pretty in Tolstoy’s world. Two of the short novels I read are particularly noteworthy in understanding his stance on love and “romantic” relationships. Here is a very condensed outline of the account of love they make.</p> <p>Family Happiness: Masha, a young orphan (~18 years old), and a family friend, Sergei (~35 years old), come to fall in love in the purest of ways. They talk for hours about everything and nothing, dream about the future, and care so deeply for one another — nothing in the world matters to their eyes more than one another. They marry, and Masha starts to feel bored of their country life, Sergei is considerate enough to suggest moving to Petersburg for a while and living a social lifestyle. Masha navigates this new life with great success and becomes adored by the whole Russian bourgeoisie, but her husband slowly grows exacerbated by all of this social nonsense. Distance builds up, and they build resentment towards one another and eventually completely disconnect. Masha feels extremely depressed, angry, and lost — and a good part of the novel is dedicated to describing how she navigates (or rather, fails to navigate) this resentment and frustration. The novel however ends on a positive note — they manage to love one another again, albeit not as lovers anymore, but as the mother/father of their child, and live “happily” ever after. Kreutzer’s Sonata: A man, “Pozdnyshev”, within a (60-page long) uninterrupted monologue to a stranger on the train, tells the story of how he murdered his wife. He had always dreamt of a happy and peaceful family life. He eventually fell in love and married a “gentle soul”, but quickly realized that they were not a good match (and argues there is no such thing as a good match — lovers always end up growing away from one another, however good the original match — c.f. Family Happiness). They grow apart and develop resentment and jealousy toward one another, which consumes their energy, morals, and souls. Pozdnyshev’s wife eventually fills the void of her marriage with music — she plays piano and invites a (male) violinist friend of hers to play duets. Pozdnyshev is jealous and suspects adultery. One day, he comes back home from traveling and finds them playing music together in the living room, and in a burst of anger, kills his wife. In Pozdnyshev’s words, there can only be two outcomes of marriage: suicide or murder of one’s partner. The character in this story chose the latter. While both these stories have rather different flavors and outcomes, I believe they both are clear on something: the love of two individuals for one another, no matter the circumstances, will always lead to great pain and destruction. The intensity and strength of the emotion constrain lovers to forgo reason and morals.</p> <p>Tolstoy’s views on the topic, particularly influenced by the failure of his own marriage, turned increasingly grim and hopeless towards the end of his life — hence the much darker Kreutzer’s Sonata, where the beautiful and pure love only lasts for a mere few days (and is narrated within a few sentences only), as opposed to the years of happiness (and half the novel in writing) dedicated to narrating Masha and Sergei’s happy marriage.</p> <hr/> <p>To further comment on Tolstoy’s view on love, we should also discuss the afterword of Kreutzer’s Sonata, written a few years after the publication of the novel, where the author explicitly clarifies his views on marital life and the “fantasy of falling in love”. He argues that the only solution to a sane and elevated life is chastity and celibacy. Tolstoy is, especially at the end of his life, strongly influenced by his faith and biblical understanding in his warning and reservations with regard to marital life. Kreutzer’s sonata comes with not one, but two epigraphs from the Gospel of Matthew:</p> <blockquote> <p>“But I tell you that anyone who looks at a woman lustfully has already committed adultery with her in his heart.” Matthew 5:28 “The disciples said to him, “If this is the situation between a husband and wife, it is better not to marry.” Jesus replied, “Not everyone can accept this word, but only those to whom it has been given””. Matthew 19:10–11</p> </blockquote> <p>It seems that Tolstoy sees no difference between lust and love and that no matter what, besides it unavoidably leading to despair, is actually also sinful. A noteworthy justification of this argument is the fact that neither Jesus nor the apostles ever married — and they exemplify The Right Way in Christianity. Tolstoy however acknowledges that “not everyone can accept this word”, and that is the curse of mankind — only a handful few are capable of abstaining from love (or lust?) to manage living elevated lives.</p> <p>It is interesting to remind oneself that in the two other Abrahamic religions, marriage is the most natural of things for human beings, including for people of significant importance — for example, the Prophet Mohamed married multiple times, and two of his wives (Khadija and Aicha) have been of notoriously positive influence in his life — a life committed to God.</p> <h2 id="interlude---what-is-sufism">Interlude - What is Sufism?</h2> <p>This article (from which much of this section is paraphrased) makes a great account of the Sufi tradition and practice.</p> <p>Sufism can be described as Islamic mysticism or asceticism, which through belief and practice helps Muslims attain nearness to the Almighty by way of direct personal experience of God. Belief in pursuing a path that leads to closeness with God, ultimately through encountering the divine in the hereafter, is a fundamental component of Islamic belief. However, in the Sufi tradition, this proximity can be realized in this life.</p> <p>There is a rich body of Sufi literature, with its most prominent representant being the well known poet Rumi, whose many poems on the theme of Love are widly read and quoted in today’s world. His influence on the Sufi world is very significant — and we should note that Rumi’s repeatedly aknowledge as his main master and influence our very own Attar:</p> <blockquote> <p>“Attar traveled through all the seven cities of love, While I am only at the bend of the first alley.”</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="love-chez-attar-and-in-the-sufi-practice">Love chez Attar and in the Sufi practice</h2> <p>The Conference of the Birds is a Sufi poem telling the story of a group of birds who seek spiritual meaning and elevation. They seek advice from the wisest bird they know — the Hoopoe — who advises them to embark on a spiritual journey to meet their Almighty. The journey is long and arduous, and many birds give up along the way. Those who stay eventually discover that the Almighty was there all along the Way — within themselves.</p> <p>On their way to find God, the birds must go through the notorious 7 Valleys of 1) Quest, 2) Love, 3) Understanding, 4) Independence and Detachment, 5) Unity, 6) Astonishment and Bewilderment, and 7) Deprivation and Death. Love is discussed all around the poem, but we can start looking into Attar’s account of Love by discussing the passage of the birds through the Valley of Love.</p> <blockquote> <p>Next comes the Valley of Love. Walk here and drown in fire, for in this valley only fire lives. If you are not a lover of fire, then leave, because a true lover is one with fire; a true lover ignities, burns and flares like fire. […] Here, a lover joyfully gathers and throws a hunder worlds into the fire. Here, right and wrong are mates, because in love two becomes one.</p> </blockquote> <p>Love occupies a central place in Sufism, it’s the most noble pursuit of mankind, but also the most dangerous and difficult one. The above quote clearly exemplifies this — love is fire, with its danger, high spirit, and beauty. It’s also clear that, just like in Tolstoy, true love forces us to forgo reason. However one must note an important nuance — the love mentioned in the previous quote is the love of the Beloved, the Almighty — God. The quest to find God’s love and give all love to God is the most important pursuit in life in Sufism and Attar’s text.</p> <p>What about the love of other things? “Earthly things”. Attar is quite clear on the topic: nothing compares to the love of God, and anything that is not the love of God is not worthy of one’s time, but also doomed to vanish with time. For example, one chapter is dedicated to the story of a bird whose love of gold made him hesitant to embark on the quest to find God, he had all the happiness he needed in the gold he already had. The sage Hoopoe bird answers “Gold is merely a metal with a nice hue — you’re seduced by its color like a child. If gold diverts you from your Beloved, then it is an idol; throw it aside and be on the ground.” No surprises there, of course a spiritual text will warn one against the love of gold and material things. But what about the love people around you?</p> <p>A long parable tells the story of a sage (Sheik) who falls in love with a young Christian woman, so much that he abandons his faith to convert to Christianity, accepts to bow before an idol (the worst sin in Islam), eats swine, and drunk wine, all to please and seduce the woman he fell in love with. His earthly love completely corrupted him out of his faith, forced him to cease all his spiritual duties and abandon all his followers. While the love was strong, sincere, and “pure”, the Sheikh not only lost reason but at no point found true fulfillment, satisfaction, and peace which he had when in love and devoted to the Almighty.</p> <blockquote> <p>“In love’s wilderness, slaughter the swine, burn the idol or else become like the luckless sheik, disgraced in love”</p> </blockquote> <p>In the end, in Attar’s world, any “earthly” love is idolatry, and while not necessarily considered sinful in Islam, is clearly regarded as perilous and leads to the loss of the self and of The Way. The purest and only love that must be given is love to the Almighty.</p> <h2 id="so-what-do-tolstoy-and-attar-agree-on">So what do Tolstoy and Attar agree on?</h2> <p>Earthly love is fire, and won’t bring any human to supreme peace and happiness. Reaching God is human’s best chance at finding everlasting peace. However, the perceptions of the paths to God are very different for Attar and Tolstoy, and this is what I find most interesting. Tolstoy is, especially at the end of his life, clear on the idea that chastity and celibacy (and essentially, renunciation of all other earthly pleasures) are the only way to reach a stable and trouble-free, elevated life. Attar and the philosophy of Sufism are much more forgiving, and narrate countless stories of kings and peasants who have fallen into the trap of earthly love (or other “egocentric” and “earthly” traps), but every time, forgiveness is possible as long as the true search continues and the soul remains pure and honest. The search for God remains the purest of quests, and the one most likely to find peace in. It is also a source of great struggle, but these struggles, as opposed to the love of earthly things, are not caused by the source of Love itself (e.g. God), but rather by the earthly distractions of it all which corrupt the soul along The Way.</p> <p>While the path to an elevated life is very obvious and clear for Tolstoy, the search rarely ever ends for Sufis — finding God is the quest of a lifetime, and this will, exactly like the love of earthly things, come with its fair deal of struggles.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Someone asked him: “Distraught fellow, what is this love?” The man replied: “Love is selling all of your wordly goods to buy a drop of wine.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with jupyter notebook</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/jupyter-notebook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with jupyter notebook"/><published>2023-07-04T12:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T12:57:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/jupyter-notebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/jupyter-notebook/"><![CDATA[<p>To include a jupyter notebook in a post, you can use the following code:</p> <div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>{::nomarkdown}
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">jupyter_path</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s1">'assets/jupyter/blog.ipynb'</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">relative_url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">capture</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">notebook_exists</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">file_exists</span><span class="w"> </span>assets/jupyter/blog.ipynb<span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endcapture</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">notebook_exists</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s1">'true'</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
  <span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">jupyter_notebook</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">jupyter_path</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">else</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
  &lt;p&gt;Sorry, the notebook you are looking for does not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
{:/nomarkdown}
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Let’s break it down: this is possible thanks to <a href="https://github.com/red-data-tools/jekyll-jupyter-notebook">Jekyll Jupyter Notebook plugin</a> that allows you to embed jupyter notebooks in your posts. It basically calls <a href="https://nbconvert.readthedocs.io/en/latest/usage.html#convert-html"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jupyter nbconvert --to html</code></a> to convert the notebook to an html page and then includes it in the post. Since <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/configuration/markdown/">Kramdown</a> is the default Markdown renderer for Jekyll, we need to surround the call to the plugin with the <a href="https://kramdown.gettalong.org/syntax.html#extensions">::nomarkdown</a> tag so that it stops processing this part with Kramdown and outputs the content as-is.</p> <p>The plugin takes as input the path to the notebook, but it assumes the file exists. If you want to check if the file exists before calling the plugin, you can use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">file_exists</code> filter. This avoids getting a 404 error from the plugin and ending up displaying the main page inside of it instead. If the file does not exist, you can output a message to the user. The code displayed above outputs the following:</p> <div class="jupyter-notebook" style="position: relative; width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;"> <div class="jupyter-notebook-iframe-container"> <iframe src="/assets/jupyter/blog.ipynb.html" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; border-style: none;" width="100%" height="100%" onload="this.parentElement.style.paddingBottom = (this.contentWindow.document.documentElement.scrollHeight + 10) + 'px'"></iframe> </div> </div> <p>Note that the jupyter notebook supports both light and dark themes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="jupyter"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a blog post with jupyter notebook]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with videos</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/videos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with videos"/><published>2023-04-24T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-24T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/videos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/videos/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with videos. It supports local video files.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <video src="/assets/video/pexels-engin-akyurt-6069112-960x540-30fps.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" autoplay="" controls=""/> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <video src="/assets/video/pexels-engin-akyurt-6069112-960x540-30fps.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" controls=""/> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A simple, elegant caption looks good between video rows, after each row, or doesn't have to be there at all. </div> <p>It does also support embedding videos from different sources. Here are some examples:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jNQXAC9IVRw" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/524933864?h=1ac4fd9fb4&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="videos"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included videos could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Conducting an orchestra is hard.</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/conducting-is-hard/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Conducting an orchestra is hard."/><published>2022-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/conducting-is-hard</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/conducting-is-hard/"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I had the chance to organize and lead a concert series in London where we played Britten’s Simple Symphony, Mozart Divertimento k136 in D Major, and a strings-only arrangement of Mozart’s Concerto k466 in D minor (with the fantastic Adam Heron on the Piano). This was an incredibly intense and enriching experience for me, on both a musical and a human level. However it was also quasi-traumatic as the rehearsals were very difficult, and I felt like I was to blame for it. As the concerts went relatively well, I now feel more at peace with all of the hardship and I managed to reflect on all the things I learned. Things I had never really realized during my conducting training. This essay is an attempt to share these lessons, and hopefully save fellow starting conductors from doing the same mistakes I did.</p> <p>When I first stood in front of an orchestra rehearsing for a real concert, I had already taken multiple conducting masterclasses. During these masterclasses, we explored the depth of a given score and thought deeply about how to reshape the standard beating patterns in order to shine light on the inner intricacies of the music, and make it live. This is what all conducting classes are about: you learn the technique and study the score in order to create beautiful music, exactly like playing an instrument. The issue with this is that it often makes the student forget something of critical importance: the sound doesn’t come from your waving, it comes from the orchestra.</p> <p><em>Conducting classes teach you how to act, but the conductor’s job is mostly about how to react.</em></p> <p>Standing in front of an orchestra while preparing for a concert made me realize I completely overlooked this critical part. If you are leading the Berlin Philharmonic on a piece that they already know by heart, the way you wave matters enormously. If that’s not the case, it’s only a small part of what it takes to produce decent (I would not dare say “good”) music. In this short essay, I’ll attempt to outline a few critical lessons I learned about conducting an orchestra, all originating from this key realization.</p> <h2 id="the-conductors-first-job-listenning">The conductor’s first job: Listenning</h2> <p>I did hear this from my conducting professors, but I never realized the extent of the job this was, nor how challenging it was. It’s not about perfect pitch, relative pitch, or any of that. It’s about listening to a given excerpt of music, played for the first (or tenth) time by some musicians, integrating all of what is happening, and pinpointing exactly what is wrong. On the spot. Are the second violins playing too loud? Is that third desk viola player badly out of tune and messing up the whole sound texture? Is the oboe (who’s playing rather unimportant harmony notes) actually one bar late because he has wrong bar numbers, cannot count, or (most probably), because you forgot to give them an appropriate cue? All of these at once? A myriad of different problems can (and do) occur while rehearsing, and your job as a conductor is to immediately identify what the problem is, and find a way to fix it (if it even is fixable in the short rehearsal time you have). Spoiler alert, you won’t master this by attending conducting masterclasses. The only way to get there is by doing, and by doing I mean making a fool of yourself in front of the orchestra a few times. I’ll try to spare you some problems by telling you some of the things I learned about rehearsal preparation during a traumatic two rehearsals.</p> <h3 id="do-not-overthinkg-your-conducting-during-rehearsals">Do not overthinkg your conducting during rehearsals</h3> <p>I imagine this to be a first-timer classic mistake. You’re so focused on what you’re doing, and wondering if you’re doing it right, that you forget the golden rule: it’s as much about reacting as acting. You should arrive to your first rehearsal with the basics completely integrated within you, in such a way that you don’t need to think about them. These basics are:</p> <ul> <li>Clear start of the pieces.</li> <li>Clear ideas of tempo.</li> <li>Important cues.</li> <li>Important dynamics.</li> </ul> <p>That’s it. It isn’t much, right? But if you’re an apprentice conductor going in front of an orchestra that has never played a piece before, that’s all you need to worry about for your first rehearsal. If you don’t have this properly integrated into your first rehearsal, you won’t manage to do your job properly, because you’ll be reading the music with them and thinking about your own waving instead of listening. You should also note that the musicians will mostly be reading (likely even discovering) the music, and thus cannot be very reactive to your waving’s “subtleties”. Focus on giving a clear and simple beating, <em>nothing</em> more than what they need to play.</p> <p>There will be mistakes on your part (and on theirs too). There will be things where you feel like you didn’t show the music properly etc… This does not matter at the beginning — you can work on these things in your own time between the rehearsal(s) and the concert. What you cannot work on in between is what the orchestra is doing, and whether there are significant problems.</p> <p>Your job during the rehearsal is to step back and actually listen to what is happening, and take decisions accordingly.</p> <h3 id="know-every-line-including-the-ones-that-dont-matter-a-lot-because-theyre-the-ones-that-actually-will-fuck-up-the-music">Know every line, including the ones that don’t matter a lot, because they’re the ones that actually will fuck up the music.</h3> <p>I was conducting the introduction of the first movement of Mozart’s K466 piano concerto, and the first violins and cellos/double bass have the important lines while the seconds/violas are “only” doubling. I was putting all my brain power into conducting/listening to the firsts violins and the cellos — this made me very very slow at realizing that the core of the problem was that seconds and violas were playing too loud and barely managing the not-so-obvious syncopation. You’d think that this is an obvious thing to realize (if I had heard it from the outside, it 100% is), but it isn’t when you’re on the spot, partly focusing on your own way of conducting, and when there are many other things going on. Of course, what first and cellos are playing is not perfect and can be improved to fit the exact idea of the music you have, but you have an ongoing disaster happening on other instruments that are, when you studied the score, only playing “repeated doubling notes”. By the time you realize, precious minutes of rehearsal time have passed, and you’re never getting this time again. In the end, these lines are also very important because they build the overall sound texture.</p> <p>My conclusion is that one should spend a lot of time studying the inner notes, training yourself to hear them in recordings for example, or playing them on the piano, or anything else that would work in order to make you very quick at spotting things that are wrong when they are wrong.</p> <p>Music is a holistic experience, all individual components have to be good in order for the whole to be good. Conductors should never forget that.</p> <h3 id="deconstruct-the-music-and-rehearse-it-as-such">Deconstruct the music, and rehearse it as such.</h3> <p>It is very helpful to deconstruct the music when rehearsing and make subgroups of instruments play sections together. Of course, it is the conductor’s job to have everyone really playing together, essentially acting like everyone else’s ear, but it is extremely helpful to have the players’ ears also in use, and when there is a lot happening, it’s difficult to have that happen. Choose groups of players playing correlated lines, and rehearse them together — not only will they get better at playing these lines, but it will also be extremely helpful for the conductor to correct issues (as fewer instruments are playing, and there is a point of focus that is being looked upon). As long as you don’t spend too long doing this, it will also be useful to musicians not playing as they identify and internalize important parts of the whole piece rather than only their own parts. But please don’t ever spend too long doing that with all the orchestra there, they’ll hate you for it.</p> <h2 id="the-conductors-second-job-leading">The conductor’s second job: Leading</h2> <p>Some may argue that you’re either born with it, or you’re not. I’ve always thought of myself as someone who could lead people, and motivate them towards a common vision. I was proven wrong this time — big time. Leading an orchestra is nothing like what I’ve experienced before. Very rare are the people with the necessary self-confidence, musicianship, knowledge, and humanity to do this job properly. I realized it was far from given to me, and that I had to grow a lot as a musician and human to ever hope to do this well.</p> <h3 id="yes-youre-leading-but-dont-make-it-about-yourself-no-one-is-bigger-than-the-music">Yes, you’re leading, but don’t make it about yourself. No one is bigger than the music.</h3> <p>Musicians are there to play, as much as you are there to conduct. You’re the leader, but don’t ever make them feel like you are in the slightest way more important than they are. As a leader, you should also take the necessary initiatives to make them feel valued and listened to. Small things like putting their bios on a concert program, smiling at them when they have an important line to play (even if it’s not played perfectly!), or the way you make them stand after a concert… This all makes a significant difference, and can ultimately make them truly happy to play for you — or should I say, to play with you. This is what I mean by “no one is bigger than the music“— do not act or think that the musicians are playing for you, they’re playing with you. You’re all together trying to create beautiful music — this shift in attitude is so important to make the whole process, from rehearsals to concerts, more enjoyable and less stressful for everyone. And if everyone enjoys themselves, the music will be the best it can be.</p> <h3 id="managing-issues">Managing issues</h3> <p>Experience is the only way here. You learn the kind of issues that arise and are used to dealing with them. You thus prepare accordingly and have a better ability to deal with them on the spot. It will be difficult and stressful the first few times — there is nothing more terrifying than a musician asking you a question in front of the whole orchestra and you not having a clue of how to answer. I’ve been in this situation multiple times during the rehearsals, and what I often did was to tell them I wasn’t sure and that I’d think about it for the next rehearsal or that I’d let them know before the concert. It’s really really suboptimal, but that’s the only way I found to deal with it without losing rehearsal time and frustrating everyone with my own shortcomings. It takes a lot of experience to be able to look at a score and figure out complex things on the spot — experience that I do not yet have.</p> <p>There are other schools of thought, which can also work. I once heard: “if you’re asked about something and don’t know how to answer, just pick an answer that sounds acceptable, and act confident. If you then realize it doesn’t work, just say you’ve changed your mind”. For most people, this will sound like horrible advice. “One must know its limits and when they don’t know something”. Absolutely, but not in front of an orchestra. For a conductor, there is really nothing worse than not being able to answer a musician’s concerns. It not only stresses you out but also makes you look unprepared. And musicians are quick to judge…</p> <h3 id="managing-motivation">Managing motivation</h3> <p>I experienced a massive issue with this on the second (and last) concert of the series. We all had to travel for more than 2 hours to get to the venue, mainly because of a railway strike in London… The public turnout was also very disappointing. We arrived early and rehearsed things that were not great on concert 1, and it felt like everyone was much better prepared than at the previous concert, and things looked promising. The first half went quite okay, with some good moments. During the interval, I made the terrible mistake of going to the first violinist and first viola players (the most experienced players in the group) seeking reassurance and encouragement about the first half, before starting the second. I was not sensing much satisfaction at all from their ends. Digging a bit deeper and asking more, the first viola player finally said “I don’t know, it’s like musicians know the music and have played it already, we’re all a bit tired, so it feels like no one is very motivated to play. There isn’t much energy”. This threw me off so much, and whilst there was some truth to it regarding the first half, the second half felt 10 times worse. Why? Well because I was now over-sensing the lack of motivation, which unmotivated me as well and of course made it impossible to generate any excitement from the players. Imagine - as devoted to music as I am, as privileged as I felt to be in front of an orchestra playing the incredible Mozart k466, I still had the feeling that nothing good could possibly come out of this performance anymore.</p> <p>This was a very traumatic experience for me because I did not expect it and handled it so badly. Whatever happens, however bad the music has been in the previous minutes, the conductor should ALWAYS give their all when performing. Not communicating good energy when conducting is simply deadly for the performance, there cannot be a gram of passion from the players if the conductor is visibly unmotivated. The conductor is obliged to at least fake it. Fake motivation, fake excitement, until you make it in the eyes of only one musician. From that one musician, the whole group’s excitement can progressively regrow. Never stop smiling, always act as if you’re the happiest person in the world to be playing this music, no matter what — this will make all the difference in the world.</p> <h3 id="knowing-your-players">Knowing your players</h3> <p>“<em>Be aware of what you are rehearsing, and what you are not rehearsing</em>”. This is one of the many important pieces of advice I heard from my incredibly erudite professor, John Longstaff. A conductor should be very clearly aware of the musical level of the players in the orchestra, and of the time you have to rehearse. Sometimes, you should (unfortunately) only aim for decency, rather than goodness. In these moments, don’t lose time rehearsing the fine details of that beautiful line, spend time making sure that everyone is playing together and that all the difficult passages are clear, at a playable tempo, and that all notes can be heard. Musicians won’t be happy staying over the agreed time, they have other things to do and they get tired as well.</p> <h3 id="being-mindful-of-players-needs">Being mindful of player’s needs</h3> <p>Understand what they need, for their mental sanity, confidence, and motivation. Make sure you give them that. If you’re reading this far, you’re most likely a starting conductor, and I guess you’ll have to do the librarian work as well to prepare scores, etc… This is SO important — make sure all their parts are readable, well organized, that page turns are acceptable, etc… Give them clear indications to last minute adjustments in the music, what repeats you are playing / not playing, etc… I’d even go as far as saying you should put all of it in writing for the players not to get confused on concert day. Just imagine how terrifying it would be for you not to be 100% sure whether the conductor told you to play the repeat or not. This can happen so easily when making last-minute changes… Stupid issues like this are so easy to avoid if the conductor just tries a bit harder. Handling this well is a great way to earn your player’s respect, and failing to do so will inevitably make players hate you…</p> <hr/> <p>These humble thoughts are only a tiny aspect of what could and should be discussed about the colossal job of the conductor. What an irony that the only musician which doesn’t produce any sound bares so much responsibility.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="open"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few weeks ago, I had the chance to organize and lead a concert series in London where we played Britten’s Simple Symphony, Mozart Divertimento k136 in D Major, and a strings-only arrangement of Mozart’s Concerto k466 in D minor (with the fantastic Adam Heron on the Piano). This was an incredibly intense and enriching experience for me, on both a musical and a human level. However it was also quasi-traumatic as the rehearsals were very difficult, and I felt like I was to blame for it. As the concerts went relatively well, I now feel more at peace with all of the hardship and I managed to reflect on all the things I learned. Things I had never really realized during my conducting training. This essay is an attempt to share these lessons, and hopefully save fellow starting conductors from doing the same mistakes I did.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a distill-style blog post</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/distill/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a distill-style blog post"/><published>2021-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/distill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/distill/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="equations">Equations</h2> <p>This theme supports rendering beautiful math in inline and display modes using <a href="https://www.mathjax.org/">MathJax 3</a> engine. You just need to surround your math expression with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$$</code>, like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$$ E = mc^2 $$</code>. If you leave it inside a paragraph, it will produce an inline expression, just like \(E = mc^2\).</p> <p>To use display mode, again surround your expression with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$$</code> and place it as a separate paragraph. Here is an example:</p> \[\left( \sum_{k=1}^n a_k b_k \right)^2 \leq \left( \sum_{k=1}^n a_k^2 \right) \left( \sum_{k=1}^n b_k^2 \right)\] <p>Note that MathJax 3 is <a href="https://docs.mathjax.org/en/latest/upgrading/whats-new-3.0.html">a major re-write of MathJax</a> that brought a significant improvement to the loading and rendering speed, which is now <a href="http://www.intmath.com/cg5/katex-mathjax-comparison.php">on par with KaTeX</a>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="citations">Citations</h2> <p>Citations are then used in the article body with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;d-cite&gt;</code> tag. The key attribute is a reference to the id provided in the bibliography. The key attribute can take multiple ids, separated by commas.</p> <p>The citation is presented inline like this: <d-cite key="gregor2015draw"></d-cite> (a number that displays more information on hover). If you have an appendix, a bibliography is automatically created and populated in it.</p> <p>Distill chose a numerical inline citation style to improve readability of citation dense articles and because many of the benefits of longer citations are obviated by displaying more information on hover. However, we consider it good style to mention author last names if you discuss something at length and it fits into the flow well — the authors are human and it’s nice for them to have the community associate them with their work.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2> <p>Just wrap the text you would like to show up in a footnote in a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;d-footnote&gt;</code> tag. The number of the footnote will be automatically generated.<d-footnote>This will become a hoverable footnote.</d-footnote></p> <hr/> <h2 id="code-blocks">Code Blocks</h2> <p>Syntax highlighting is provided within <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;d-code&gt;</code> tags. An example of inline code snippets: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;d-code language="html"&gt;let x = 10;&lt;/d-code&gt;</code>. For larger blocks of code, add a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">block</code> attribute:</p> <d-code block="" language="javascript"> var x = 25; function(x) { return x * x; } </d-code> <p><strong>Note:</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;d-code&gt;</code> blocks do not look good in the dark mode. You can always use the default code-highlight using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">highlight</code> liquid tag:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript"><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">25</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">x</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
<span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">x</span> <span class="err">\</span><span class="o">*</span> <span class="nx">x</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure> <hr/> <h2 id="interactive-plots">Interactive Plots</h2> <p>You can add interative plots using plotly + iframes :framed_picture:</p> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/demo.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <p>The plot must be generated separately and saved into an HTML file. To generate the plot that you see above, you can use the following code snippet:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python" data-lang="python"><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">pandas</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">pd</span>
<span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">plotly.express</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">px</span>
<span class="n">df</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">pd</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">read_csv</span><span class="p">(</span>
<span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/plotly/datasets/master/earthquakes-23k.csv</span><span class="sh">'</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">fig</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">px</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">density_mapbox</span><span class="p">(</span>
<span class="n">df</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="n">lat</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">Latitude</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="n">lon</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">Longitude</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="n">z</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">Magnitude</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="n">radius</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="n">center</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nf">dict</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">lat</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">lon</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">180</span><span class="p">),</span>
<span class="n">zoom</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="n">mapbox_style</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">stamen-terrain</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">fig</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">show</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">fig</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">write_html</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">assets/plotly/demo.html</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span></code></pre></figure> <hr/> <h2 id="details-boxes">Details boxes</h2> <p>Details boxes are collapsible boxes which hide additional information from the user. They can be added with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">details</code> liquid tag:</p> <details><summary>Click here to know more</summary> <p>Additional details, where math \(2x - 1\) and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">code</code> is rendered correctly.</p> </details> <hr/> <h2 id="layouts">Layouts</h2> <p>The main text column is referred to as the body. It is the assumed layout of any direct descendants of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">d-article</code> element.</p> <div class="fake-img l-body"> <p>.l-body</p> </div> <p>For images you want to display a little larger, try <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.l-page</code>:</p> <div class="fake-img l-page"> <p>.l-page</p> </div> <p>All of these have an outset variant if you want to poke out from the body text a little bit. For instance:</p> <div class="fake-img l-body-outset"> <p>.l-body-outset</p> </div> <div class="fake-img l-page-outset"> <p>.l-page-outset</p> </div> <p>Occasionally you’ll want to use the full browser width. For this, use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.l-screen</code>. You can also inset the element a little from the edge of the browser by using the inset variant.</p> <div class="fake-img l-screen"> <p>.l-screen</p> </div> <div class="fake-img l-screen-inset"> <p>.l-screen-inset</p> </div> <p>The final layout is for marginalia, asides, and footnotes. It does not interrupt the normal flow of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.l-body</code> sized text except on mobile screen sizes.</p> <div class="fake-img l-gutter"> <p>.l-gutter</p> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="other-typography">Other Typography?</h2> <p>Emphasis, aka italics, with <em>asterisks</em> (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">*asterisks*</code>) or <em>underscores</em> (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_underscores_</code>).</p> <p>Strong emphasis, aka bold, with <strong>asterisks</strong> or <strong>underscores</strong>.</p> <p>Combined emphasis with <strong>asterisks and <em>underscores</em></strong>.</p> <p>Strikethrough uses two tildes. <del>Scratch this.</del></p> <ol> <li>First ordered list item</li> <li>Another item ⋅⋅* Unordered sub-list.</li> <li>Actual numbers don’t matter, just that it’s a number ⋅⋅1. Ordered sub-list</li> <li>And another item.</li> </ol> <p>⋅⋅⋅You can have properly indented paragraphs within list items. Notice the blank line above, and the leading spaces (at least one, but we’ll use three here to also align the raw Markdown).</p> <p>⋅⋅⋅To have a line break without a paragraph, you will need to use two trailing spaces.⋅⋅ ⋅⋅⋅Note that this line is separate, but within the same paragraph.⋅⋅ ⋅⋅⋅(This is contrary to the typical GFM line break behaviour, where trailing spaces are not required.)</p> <ul> <li> <p>Unordered list can use asterisks</p> </li> <li> <p>Or minuses</p> </li> <li> <p>Or pluses</p> </li> </ul> <p><a href="https://www.google.com">I’m an inline-style link</a></p> <p><a href="https://www.google.com" title="Google's Homepage">I’m an inline-style link with title</a></p> <p><a href="https://www.mozilla.org">I’m a reference-style link</a></p> <p><a href="http://slashdot.org">You can use numbers for reference-style link definitions</a></p> <p>Or leave it empty and use the <a href="http://www.reddit.com">link text itself</a>.</p> <p>URLs and URLs in angle brackets will automatically get turned into links. http://www.example.com or <a href="http://www.example.com">http://www.example.com</a> and sometimes example.com (but not on Github, for example).</p> <p>Some text to show that the reference links can follow later.</p> <p>Here’s our logo (hover to see the title text):</p> <p>Inline-style: <img src="https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/raw/master/src/common/images/icon48.png" alt="alt text" title="Logo Title Text 1"/></p> <p>Reference-style: <img src="https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/raw/master/src/common/images/icon48.png" alt="alt text" title="Logo Title Text 2"/></p> <p>Inline <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">code</code> has <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">back-ticks around</code> it.</p> <div class="language-javascript highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">s</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">JavaScript syntax highlighting</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="nf">alert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">s</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">s</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Python syntax highlighting</span><span class="sh">"</span>
<span class="k">print</span> <span class="n">s</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>No language indicated, so no syntax highlighting.
But let's throw in a &lt;b&gt;tag&lt;/b&gt;.
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Colons can be used to align columns.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Tables</th> <th style="text-align: center">Are</th> <th style="text-align: right">Cool</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>col 3 is</td> <td style="text-align: center">right-aligned</td> <td style="text-align: right">$1600</td> </tr> <tr> <td>col 2 is</td> <td style="text-align: center">centered</td> <td style="text-align: right">$12</td> </tr> <tr> <td>zebra stripes</td> <td style="text-align: center">are neat</td> <td style="text-align: right">$1</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>There must be at least 3 dashes separating each header cell. The outer pipes (|) are optional, and you don’t need to make the raw Markdown line up prettily. You can also use inline Markdown.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Markdown</th> <th>Less</th> <th>Pretty</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td><em>Still</em></td> <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">renders</code></td> <td><strong>nicely</strong></td> </tr> <tr> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <blockquote> <p>Blockquotes are very handy in email to emulate reply text. This line is part of the same quote.</p> </blockquote> <p>Quote break.</p> <blockquote> <p>This is a very long line that will still be quoted properly when it wraps. Oh boy let’s keep writing to make sure this is long enough to actually wrap for everyone. Oh, you can <em>put</em> <strong>Markdown</strong> into a blockquote.</p> </blockquote> <p>Here’s a line for us to start with.</p> <p>This line is separated from the one above by two newlines, so it will be a <em>separate paragraph</em>.</p> <p>This line is also a separate paragraph, but… This line is only separated by a single newline, so it’s a separate line in the <em>same paragraph</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Albert Einstein</name></author><category term="distill"/><category term="formatting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a distill-style blog post and main elements]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with code</title><link href="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/code/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with code"/><published>2015-07-15T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-07-15T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/code</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.yassine.fyi/blog/code/"><![CDATA[<p>This theme implements a built-in Jekyll feature, the use of Rouge, for syntax highlighting. It supports more than 100 languages. This example is in C++. All you have to do is wrap your code in markdown code tags:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">c++
</span><span class="n">code</span> <span class="n">code</span> <span class="n">code</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <div class="language-c++ highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">argc</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">char</span> <span class="k">const</span> <span class="err">\</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="n">argv</span><span class="p">[])</span>
<span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="n">string</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">;</span>

    <span class="n">cout</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="s">"input a string: "</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="n">getline</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">cin</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">length</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">length</span><span class="p">();</span>

    <span class="kt">char</span> <span class="n">charArray</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="kt">char</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="n">length</span><span class="p">];</span>

    <span class="n">charArray</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="k">for</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="n">length</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="o">++</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">){</span>
        <span class="n">cout</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="n">charArray</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="s">" "</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>For displaying code in a list item, you have to be aware of the indentation, as stated in this <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/34987908/embed-a-code-block-in-a-list-item-with-proper-indentation-in-kramdown/38090598#38090598">Stackoverflow answer</a>. You must indent your code by <strong>(3 * bullet_indent_level)</strong> spaces. This is because kramdown (the markdown engine used by Jekyll) indentation for the code block in lists is determined by the column number of the first non-space character after the list item marker. For example:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">1.</span> We can put fenced code blocks inside nested bullets, too.
<span class="p">
   1.</span> Like this:<span class="sb">

      ```c
      printf("Hello, World!");
      ```

</span><span class="p">   2.</span> The key is to indent your fenced block in the same line as the first character of the line.
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Which displays:</p> <ol> <li> <p>We can put fenced code blocks inside nested bullets, too.</p> <ol> <li> <p>Like this:</p> <div class="language-c highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">printf</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"Hello, World!"</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div> </div> </li> <li> <p>The key is to indent your fenced block in the same line as the first character of the line.</p> </li> </ol> </li> </ol> <p>By default, it does not display line numbers. If you want to display line numbers for every code block, you can set <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">kramdown.syntax_highlighter_opts.block.line_numbers</code> to true in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_config.yml</code> file.</p> <p>If you want to display line numbers for a specific code block, all you have to do is wrap your code in a liquid tag:</p> <p>{% highlight c++ linenos %} <br/> code code code <br/> {% endhighlight %}</p> <p>The keyword <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linenos</code> triggers display of line numbers. Produces something like this:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-c--" data-lang="c++"><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
</pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">argc</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">char</span> <span class="k">const</span> <span class="err">\</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="n">argv</span><span class="p">[])</span>
<span class="p">{</span>
<span class="n">string</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">;</span>

    <span class="n">cout</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="s">"input a string: "</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="n">getline</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">cin</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">length</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">length</span><span class="p">();</span>

    <span class="kt">char</span> <span class="n">charArray</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="kt">char</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="n">length</span><span class="p">];</span>

    <span class="n">charArray</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="k">for</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="n">length</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="o">++</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">){</span>
        <span class="n">cout</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="n">charArray</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="s">" "</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>

<span class="p">}</span>
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a blog post with some code]]></summary></entry></feed>